<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:40:00 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-1072/DERBY-1072.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-1072] Misleading/wrong error message while dropping a view</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1072</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;while dropping a view which does not really exist on a database , the error message thrown by ij says ERROR X0X05: Table &apos;VIEW222&apos; does not  exist. It looks like we should make the error message to say that  &quot;Table/View&quot; does not exist, instead of &quot;table&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at other messages that are shared for both Table and View.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment>windows xp , jdk1.5</environment>
        <key id="12329621">DERBY-1072</key>
            <summary>Misleading/wrong error message while dropping a view</summary>
                <type id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/bug.png">Bug</type>
                                            <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="mayureshnirhali">Mayuresh Nirhali</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="mkutty">Manjula Kutty</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 2 Mar 2006 03:05:04 +0000</created>
                <updated>Mon, 29 Jun 2009 14:13:26 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Thu, 7 Sep 2006 18:24:12 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.1.3.1</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.2.1.6</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>10.3.1.4</fixVersion>
                                    <component>SQL</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12370681" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Thu, 16 Mar 2006 20:16:56 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;While a view is being Dropped, the TableDescriptor for the specified view is read. If this TableDescriptor is null then error X0X05 is thrown with message &quot;Table &amp;lt;ViewName&amp;gt; does not exist.&quot;. This could be confusing to the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fix for this bug is to change the error message to &quot;Table/View &amp;lt;viewname&amp;gt; does not exist&quot;, as suggested earlier.&lt;br/&gt;
First, I would like to know if anyone has any other opinion reg. this fix ??&lt;br/&gt;
Please take a look at org/apache/derby/impl/sql/execute/DropViewConstantAction.executeConstantAction(Activation) for the case mentioned in the description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more similar case is when, select query is fired on a view that does not exist.&lt;br/&gt;
The error message in this case is, &quot;Error 42X05: Table &amp;lt;viewname&amp;gt; does not exist&quot;.&lt;br/&gt;
I am still looking for more cases, any more pointers are appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, I start looking into how to modify message_XX.properties, I would like to know the safest way to find out the characters to be added for all the locales.&lt;br/&gt;
One way of doing this to find out how &apos;/view&apos; is mapped in other locale properties file.&lt;br/&gt;
I am wondering if there are any tools available with us  for such conversion??&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12370730" author="bandaram" created="Fri, 17 Mar 2006 02:14:58 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for working on this... and for looking for other similarly misleading messages. If you want to make your task more interesting, you could also try synonyms to see if it generates right messages. Like trying to drop a non-existing synonym. Totally upto you if you want to try or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you have interesting suggestion to automatically edit message_XX.properties file, I wouldn&apos;t try it... if you don&apos;t understand the message in those languages. Typically people have been contributing translated messages to Derby during release process, so you could differ changes to other language messages.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12371041" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Mon, 20 Mar 2006 14:45:27 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for your response!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differing changes ( to the other languages messages) is a convinient option for me, but before deciding that, I would like to understand who and how is this going to happen before release!&lt;br/&gt;
Do I need to create any placeholder for this ??&lt;br/&gt;
Before release, is anyone going to identify if there are any inconsistencies between different language messages ??&lt;br/&gt;
Is it okay If I just modify the english messages  for now ??&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12371044" author="fuzzylogic" created="Mon, 20 Mar 2006 14:58:27 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;It is okay if there are messages in the message file that differ between languages at release time. If it is a new message, then the default English message is used when the new message is not changed in the other locale. There might be a problem if an existing message is changed so that it needs a parameter, but that is something that could be dealt with at the time that the new message is contributed. Otherwise, the old message continues to be used in other locales, so for a while those locales don&apos;t get the benefit of the updated message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In past releases, the new messages were translated by one of the companies interested in Derby, and the new translations were contributed back to Derby at a later date that was after the original release. For example, the new and changed messages introduced in Derby 10.1.1.0 were translated after the 10.1.1.0 release and contributed back a few months later. The translated messages were then released with Derby 10.1.2.1 a few months after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, please do go ahead and work on this if you like, and I think it is best to fix only the message in English. The translated messages will be dealt with at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12371064" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Mon, 20 Mar 2006 18:26:45 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Andrew,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have modified the messages_en.properties and submitting the DIFF with this comment.&lt;br/&gt;
I did clean and rebuilt my local binaries and tested my fix. It looks okay to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could anyone please take a look at the diff and also verify the fix.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12371419" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 22 Mar 2006 21:21:00 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I have uploaded another patch. The previous patch was only a partial one. After uploading that, I realized that there are many test master files, which should be modified to complete the fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has become a tidious bug fix to have simple changes in many files. I have finally made all of those and want someone to really run all possible tests with this fix, before it can be committed.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12372188" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 29 Mar 2006 16:31:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here is a complete patch now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V2 has some master files missing from master/j9_foundation directories, which are included in this latest V3 patch.&lt;br/&gt;
I searched the entire workspace for 42X05 and X0X05 error entries and it seems that all of them have been corrected now.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12373103" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 5 Apr 2006 00:13:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching svn status output for easy reference of modified files!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12413379" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Fri, 26 May 2006 14:42:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I was hoping that  this patch gets reviewed and committed before.&lt;br/&gt;
In the past few weeks, few additional files were changed which means that the patch is to be changed as well. This additional change depends on the recent changes to master/DerbyNet(/client)/jdk15/*stmt.out files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am posting the latest patch for this bug. The patch has  changes to lot of files so I would be happy to see this being looked at before anymore updates to the relevent files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dont see the &quot;patch available&quot; checkbox for this JIRA!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12413473" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Fri, 26 May 2006 21:59:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The earlier committed patch (409605) introduced 2 regression failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 of the canon files were not updated completely. In my previous testrun derbynetmats was skipped and hence could not see these failures.&lt;br/&gt;
I am attaching a new patch with updates to these files and have run tests locally.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12413514" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 27 May 2006 02:23:50 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed derby1072_patch2.diff to trunk revision 409713.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419399" author="fuzzylogic" created="Thu, 6 Jul 2006 12:07:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Marking resolved, as no further test diffs were noted. Manjula, please close this if you are satisfied with the resolution.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432829" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 6 Sep 2006 12:49:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;In the reference documentation, the section &apos;Interaction with the dependency system&apos; contains an example which refers to this particular error, 42X05 with the old string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not looked at the entire documentation to see if such minor errors exist elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433065" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 09:46:51 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Reopening the issue to fix the documenation.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433068" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 09:51:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The bug was found in the documentation in following places,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;./pt_BR/ref/crefsqlj22771.dita:92&lt;br/&gt;
./ref/crefsqlj22771.dita:83&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am attaching a patch with these 2 files fixed. I have built n verified the fix and attaching a zip file which contains HTML file for doc for english language only.&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12433098" author="johnemb" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 13:29:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Doc patch is available, so marking it as such (Mayuresh, you can find the check box by clicking on &quot;Edit&quot; on the left hand menu). Patch looks good to me.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433174" author="jta" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 18:24:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed patch 1072doc_v1.diff to the trunk, revision 441143 (not merged to 10.2 branch yet). Thanks, Mayuresh!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12551318" author="fuzzylogic" created="Thu, 13 Dec 2007 09:04:49 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;This issue has been resolved for over a year with no further movement. Closing.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12340348" name="1072doc_v1.diff" size="970" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 09:51:20 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340349" name="1072doc_v1.zip" size="3135" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 09:51:20 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12324927" name="derby1072-44.stat" size="4369" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 5 Apr 2006 00:13:19 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12324452" name="derby1072-v2.diff" size="57106" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 22 Mar 2006 21:20:58 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12324698" name="derby1072-v3.diff" size="96982" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Wed, 29 Mar 2006 16:31:35 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12334600" name="derby1072-v4.diff" size="92454" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Fri, 26 May 2006 14:42:53 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12334601" name="derby1072-v4.stat" size="3797" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Fri, 26 May 2006 14:42:53 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12324366" name="derby1072_032006.diff" size="1618" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Mon, 20 Mar 2006 18:26:45 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12334626" name="derby1072_patch2.diff" size="4996" author="mayureshnirhali" created="Fri, 26 May 2006 21:59:39 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>9.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Thu, 16 Mar 2006 20:16:56 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>22292</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0wrz:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>39128</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>