<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:32:34 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-1272/DERBY-1272.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-1272] Change sysinfo to print to error log (derby.log) on boot of derby  if derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1272</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;It is often very difficult to collect correct sysinfo output from user environments because  sysinfo run from the commandline does not have the same classpath as the jvm that started Derby or Derby was loaded with a custom classloader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be very helpful in assisting users in diagnosing their issues if sysinfo dumped to the error log if  derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0  or even by default.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12332982">DERBY-1272</key>
            <summary>Change sysinfo to print to error log (derby.log) on boot of derby  if derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0</summary>
                <type id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/improvement.png">Improvement</type>
                                            <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="2">Won&apos;t Fix</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="-1">Unassigned</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="kmarsden">Kathey Marsden</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Tue, 2 May 2006 11:19:46 +0100</created>
                <updated>Mon, 17 Jun 2013 10:19:37 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Thu, 19 May 2011 00:05:21 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.1.2.1</version>
                    <version>10.1.3.1</version>
                    <version>10.2.1.6</version>
                                                    <component>Tools</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>1</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12412422" author="fuzzylogic" created="Fri, 19 May 2006 05:04:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Q-n-D patch for this. Would love to get some feedback on whether this is acceptable and the right place for this or if I should investigate something more involved.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12412540" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 20 May 2006 01:29:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Questions from Kathey Marsden on IRC: I have to go but I looked at the patch briefly. 1)I need to look at all the tmpWriter stuff and see what that is about. 2) Might there be any potential issues with security excceptions or is that all cleared up now? 3) l ike that it will always dump for a sane build. 4) A few comments and using a constant for if (logSeverityLevel == 0) would be nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 - tmpWriter is our output PrintWriter before we&apos;ve started InfoStreams. If there&apos;s a catastrophic error, we end up writing to the tempWriter instead of the nicely formatted InfoStream. (tempWriter essentially == PrintWriter logging)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 - I&apos;m a little concerned about getting derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel, but I suppose if you can&apos;t get derby.* system props, you&apos;re in big trouble anyway. Sysinfo catches and deals with all security exceptions properly, even for an empty policy file (most restricted environment), so the call to sysinfo shouldn&apos;t be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 - yes, convenient. Before this is ready for submission, i need to make sure all tests pass in both sane and insane builds, although I suspect that we don&apos;t actually have a test that depends specifically on the output of the log file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 - I&apos;ll beef up the comments before the final. I think the most important part is explaining why we need to use the tempWriter PrintStream if systemStreams is null. (the answer is because if there&apos;s a catastrophic error and InfoStreams won&apos;t start, we need that sysinfo output somewhere)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4b - I can use ExceptionSeverity.NO_APPLICABLE_SEVERITY here, but is that more confusing than just 0 here, or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;response from kmarsden - Thanks Andrew, I agree that NO_APPLICABLE_SEVERITY is more confusing. Just a comment along with the hard coded 0 would be fine. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12412817" author="fuzzylogic" created="Tue, 23 May 2006 03:03:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated patch that includes tools src dir in sourcepath for impl/services so that it builds correctly on a clobber and rebuild. Needs to side-compile sysinfo, should be ok, since this is a source=1.3 compile.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419342" author="kmarsden" created="Thu, 6 Jul 2006 05:58:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Is it ok to go ahead and mark this issue as patch available?  It would be good to get input from those familiar with the Monitor and  add this for 10.2 if  possible.  So often it is difficult to  get correct sysinfo output because it is generated from the command line outside of the calling context.  This would be a very valuable addition.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12419372" author="fuzzylogic" created="Thu, 6 Jul 2006 08:38:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached patch -pre3. Disregard -pre2 patch, which got mixed up with the patch currently attached to 1273.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419783" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 05:19:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;After a brief discussion with Kathey on iRC, I think the -pre3 patch can be committed if no one sees any potential problems with this approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess my initial concern was that this introduces a dependency on tools code, specifically sysinfo, into the engine. However, since we package sysinfo into derby.jar, this may not actually be a concern at all.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419798" author="kmarsden" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 07:55:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Andrew for this great addition it will surely save many round trips trying to get accurate sysinfo information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applied the pre3 patch and noticed the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) After  ant clobber, I  built and got:&lt;br/&gt;
 compile_types:&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Compiling 1 source file to C:\p4\marsden_patch\classes&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; C:\p4\marsden_patch\opensource\java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\services\monitor\BaseMonitor.java:1949: package org.apache.derby.tools does not exist&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;                        org.apache.derby.tools.sysinfo.getInfo(systemStreams.stream().getPrintWriter());&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;                                              ^&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; C:\p4\marsden_patch\opensource\java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\services\monitor\BaseMonitor.java:1951: package org.apache.derby.tools does not exist&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;                        org.apache.derby.tools.sysinfo.getInfo(getTempWriter());&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;                                              ^&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; 2 errors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BUILD FAILED&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2)&lt;br/&gt;
I forced the build and tried the patch with derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0 and the sysinfo in the derby.log seemed to work great. I put it in one of the test derby.properties files to make sure it ran ok with security manager and that worked ok too.  It would be good to have this turned on for one of the tests just to make sure security manager issues don&apos;t creep in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;br/&gt;
I also tried it without the property and sysinfo still printed to the log, which is really fine by me as it will save that initial round trip of setting the property, but I don&apos;t know how others feel about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Just a minor nit I think it would be good if the sysinfo printed after the boot message but as it is fine by me too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks again&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kathey&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12419799" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 08:10:07 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;1) Are you sure you grabbed the right patch? The build.xml change in the -pre3 patch (which was absent from the -pre1 patch) should have taken care of the problem in #1. Check that your java/engine/org/apache/derby/impl/services/build.xml has been modified to include $&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.tools.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt; in the srcdir for the compile. If you do have this change in the build.xml, and are still getting this problem, I&apos;ll take another look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) a good idea. But then see also #3. I&apos;m not sure how often tests are being run with sane builds, if at all, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) as it is, sysinfo will always be printed in sane builds, so maybe you were running with a sane build? you liked this aspect of the patch last time you looked at it. &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) While that would be nice, the reason that I put it where it is in the code is that sysinfo will still be dumped to derby.log even if the engine fails to boot due to some catastrophic error. I&apos;m not sure if it is worth the effort to delay printing sysinfo until after the boot message has printed in order to get pretty formatting for something that is meant to be a diagnostic for serious failures.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419804" author="kmarsden" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 08:44:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;1) regarding build error &lt;br/&gt;
Andrew said.&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;Check that your java/engine/org/apache/derby/impl/services/build.xml has been modified to include $&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.tools.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt; in the srcdir for the compile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes I  do seem to have this part of the patch and tried clobber and build again and  seem to get the same error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2)  Regarding testing &lt;br/&gt;
Andrew said&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;  I&apos;m not sure how often tests are being run with sane builds, if at all, though. &lt;br/&gt;
It should  be testable with an insane build if  derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0 in one of the &amp;lt;test&amp;gt;_derby.properties files would be good.  Perhaps lang/errorStream test would be a good location but perhaps not critical as this is diagnostic info. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Regarding printing regardless of  derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0 with sane build.&lt;br/&gt;
My bad.  Too  long between looking at the patch and trying it #&lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;..  I verified  it does not print  if logSeverityLevel is the default with an insane build&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Regarding aesthetic positioning.  Your reasoning makes perfect sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Short story for me is that it all looks good except for the  build error.  However I am not so familiar with the Monitor and may not understand the implications especially if sysinfo fails for some reason,what the affect if any there might be on the server coming up, so  it would be great to see someone else review the code change with the next patch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419810" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 09:11:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve svn up&apos;d and now I&apos;m seeing this problem too, with the build failing in iapi/types/build.xml with the patch applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may have uncovered a potential problem, in that something in iapi/types eventually has a dependency on BaseMonitor, which lives in impl. I&apos;m not sure whether or not this is a serious problem, but I thought the iapi classes were not supposed to have dependencies on classes in impl.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419811" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 09:18:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching updated patch which resolves the build failure noted in the previous comments and adds setting logSeverityLevel=0 to the errorStream test as suggested by Kathey.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419835" author="kmarsden" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 13:30:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I get this with errorStream.java with insane build. Testing with classes and derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Test errorStream failed: access denied (java.io.FilePermission C:\p4\marsden_patch\classes read)&lt;br/&gt;
Test Failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;End:   errorStream jdk1.4.2_07 2006-07-07 22:06:41 **&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
		&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am not getting a trace in the tmp file.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419838" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 14:25:05 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This passes on my Mac OS X box, with either sane or insane. About which, btw, I&apos;m very confused. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Windows XP, it fails with the error you described. Based on the output, the failure is actually in errorStream/VombatusUrsinusHirsitus-err-4.log, and the log there provides a stack trace with the actual SecurityException.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an excellent choice of test for this, although I&apos;m a bit confused with the test results I have currently. Clearly some more investigation is required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for trying out the patch, Kathey. I think this has exposed a security manager issue that needs to be cleaned up inside of sysinfo.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12419839" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 14:28:51 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s the full stack for the SecurityException found by the errorStream test with the -v4 patch applied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test errorStream failed: access denied (java.io.FilePermission C:\derby-trunk\classes read) &lt;br/&gt;
        at java.security.AccessController.checkPermission(AccessController.java:401)&lt;br/&gt;
        at java.lang.SecurityManager.checkPermission(SecurityManager.java:524)&lt;br/&gt;
        at java.lang.SecurityManager.checkRead(SecurityManager.java:863)&lt;br/&gt;
        at java.io.File.exists(File.java:678)&lt;br/&gt;
        at java.io.Win32FileSystem.canonicalize(Win32FileSystem.java:360)&lt;br/&gt;
        at java.io.File.getCanonicalPath(File.java:513)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.tools.sysinfo.Main.formatURL(Main.java:1206)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.tools.sysinfo.Main.loadZipFromResource(Main.java:831)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.tools.sysinfo.Main.getAllInfo(Main.java:735)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.tools.sysinfo.Main.reportDerby(Main.java:212)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.tools.sysinfo.Main.getMainInfo(Main.java:119)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.tools.sysinfo.getInfo(sysinfo.java:200)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.services.monitor.BaseMonitor.dumpTempWriter(BaseMonitor.java:1949)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.services.monitor.BaseMonitor.runWithState(BaseMonitor.java:383)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.impl.services.monitor.FileMonitor.&amp;lt;init&amp;gt;(FileMonitor.java:59)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.iapi.services.monitor.Monitor.startMonitor(Monitor.java:288)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.iapi.jdbc.JDBCBoot.boot(JDBCBoot.java:68)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derby.jdbc.EmbeddedDriver.boot(EmbeddedDriver.java:178)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12422656" author="kmarsden" created="Fri, 21 Jul 2006 15:30:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Unchecking patch available as more investigation is needed for the security manager issue with sysinfo printing to derby.log.  It may be a generic security manager issue with sysinfo that requires another Jira entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew are you actively working on this issue?  I noticed it was unassigned. It would be a huge supportability improvement for 10.2 if it can get in.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12526030" author="moazeni" created="Sun, 9 Sep 2007 22:41:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching a new patch built on top of the latest trunk.&lt;br/&gt;
Please note that I added the $&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.tools.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt; to the &lt;br/&gt;
java/engine/org/apache/derby/iapi/build.xml to get the src to compile instead of&lt;br/&gt;
java/engine/org/apache/derby/impl/services/build.xml and&lt;br/&gt;
java/engine/org/apache/derby/iapi/types/build.xml since I was still &lt;br/&gt;
getting the  following errors:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Found 2 semantic errors compiling &quot;/home/ramin/opensource/derby/trunk/java/engine/org/apache/derby/impl/services/monitor/BaseMonitor.java&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;   1945.                        org.apache.derby.tools.sysinfo.getInfo(systemStreams.stream().getPrintWriter());&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;                                &lt;sup&gt;--------------------&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; *** Semantic Error: &quot;tools&quot; is either a misplaced package name or a non-existent entity. An expression name is expected in this context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;   1947.                        org.apache.derby.tools.sysinfo.getInfo(getTempWriter());&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;                                &lt;sup&gt;--------------------&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; *** Semantic Error: &quot;tools&quot; is either a misplaced package name or a non-existent entity. An expression name is expected in this context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the v5 patch, I am not able to reproduce this issue on Linux and WinXP. I ran the test using&lt;br/&gt;
classes and jars, sane and insane and they all completed successfully without any errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks&lt;br/&gt;
Ramin&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12526182" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 10 Sep 2007 17:16:49 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Ramin,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for bringing this issue back to life.  It will surely be very helpful to users and support folks.  I looked at the patch and tried it out and it all seemed to work fine.  A few comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I am concerned about adding $derby.tools.src.dir to the build.xml.  Sysinfo is available in derby.jar, but the other tools classes are not.  Adding derby.tools.src.dir allows access to all the tools classes, which is not ideal.  I wonder if using reflection can avoid the need to change the build.xml.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sysinfo prints security exceptions for information it can&apos;t access. e.g.&lt;br/&gt;
Java user name:  Security Exception: java.security.AccessControlException: Access denied (java.util.PropertyPermission user.name read)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am concerned that this might become a red herring for those debugging a problem and thinking this might be the root of it.   &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1273&quot; title=&quot;Sysinfo should print a better  message when it gets Security Exceptions accessing classpath info when run under security manager&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1273&quot;&gt;DERBY-1273&lt;/a&gt; is filed to improve the message though and I think we can handle that as a separate issue.  I asked for some feedback from some support people to get an additional opinion. I&apos;ll let you know what I hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The test doesn&apos;t seem to actually test that sysinfo printed.  It would be good to have a test that tests that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kathey&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12527636" author="kmarsden" created="Fri, 14 Sep 2007 22:13:34 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This is the feedback I got from support&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;How hard would it be to catch the exceptions:   java.security.AccessControlException&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;and replace the exception with a static message like:   &apos;Security Manager does not &amp;gt;permit reading  java.util.PropertyPermission&apos; ??&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;This will be less likely to raise any concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think  that this is the same as &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1273&quot; title=&quot;Sysinfo should print a better  message when it gets Security Exceptions accessing classpath info when run under security manager&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1273&quot;&gt;DERBY-1273&lt;/a&gt; and I think is a good idea, but I think it could go in after the patch for &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1272&quot; title=&quot;Change sysinfo to print to error log (derby.log) on boot of derby  if derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel=0&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1272&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1272&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12529264" author="kmarsden" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 22:18:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think just changing the build.xml as follows will restrict the access to sysinfo&lt;br/&gt;
     srcdir=&quot;$&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.engine.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt;;$&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.tools.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt;/org/apache/derby/impl/tools/sysinfo&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we should go ahead and check in this change even though the sysinfo output for the security exceptions is not ideal.  That can  be handled separately as &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1273&quot; title=&quot;Sysinfo should print a better  message when it gets Security Exceptions accessing classpath info when run under security manager&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1273&quot;&gt;DERBY-1273&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any objections to checking in this change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kathey&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12531868" author="moazeni" created="Tue, 2 Oct 2007 19:24:49 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;In writing test for Derby-1272, the main issue that I have is, the sysinfo&lt;br/&gt;
output is dependent on the platform that is being run. For example,&lt;br/&gt;
Java version, home, classpath, etc can all be different on different&lt;br/&gt;
platforms. I can keep a sysinfo output and save it in functionTests/master&lt;br/&gt;
directory, but this makes writing the test hard since I cannot easily compare the&lt;br/&gt;
entries with the master (canon) file. Do you have any suggestion on&lt;br/&gt;
how to proceed here?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12531882" author="kmarsden" created="Tue, 2 Oct 2007 20:17:43 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Is there some check that we can do just to see if sysinfo prints without trying to compare the full output?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540466" author="moazeni" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 16:04:18 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hello,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am attaching the v6 patch with this issue. &lt;br/&gt;
I appreciate your review/comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For testing this issue, I added a test for this issue to tools/DerbyLogTest.java.&lt;br/&gt;
Please note that by using&lt;br/&gt;
srcdir=&quot;$&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.engine.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt;;$&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.tools.src.dir}
&lt;p&gt;/org/apache/derby/impl/tools/sysinfo&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
 I still got errors during build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got errors during suites.All while running this test which was resolved by &lt;br/&gt;
changing the order of the junit tests. I will file a separate jira issue for&lt;br/&gt;
that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks&lt;br/&gt;
Ramin Moazeni&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540500" author="kmarsden" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 17:38:16 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;What were the problems you were having with the test order?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540507" author="moazeni" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 18:03:43 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I was getting the following error which indicates that the derby.stream.error.logSeverityLevel property &lt;br/&gt;
has not been set to 0. When I ran the test individually or _Suite, the test(s) completed successfully.&lt;br/&gt;
Therefore, I changed the test order and got a successful run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 2 failures:&lt;br/&gt;
1) testDerbyLog(org.apache.derbyTesting.functionTests.tests.tools.DerbyLogTest)junit.framework.ComparisonFailure: expected:&amp;lt;------------------ Java Information ------------------&amp;gt; but was:&amp;lt;java.sql.SQLException: Database &apos;wombat&apos; not found.&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derbyTesting.functionTests.tests.tools.DerbyLogTest.testDerbyLog(DerbyLogTest.java:110)&lt;br/&gt;
        at sun.reflect.NativeMethodAccessorImpl.invoke0(Native Method)&lt;br/&gt;
        at sun.reflect.NativeMethodAccessorImpl.invoke(NativeMethodAccessorImpl.java:39)&lt;br/&gt;
        at sun.reflect.DelegatingMethodAccessorImpl.invoke(DelegatingMethodAccessorImpl.java:25)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derbyTesting.junit.BaseTestCase.runBare(BaseTestCase.java:95)&lt;br/&gt;
2) testDerbyLog(org.apache.derbyTesting.functionTests.tests.tools.DerbyLogTest)junit.framework.ComparisonFailure: expected:&amp;lt;------------------ Java Information ------------------&amp;gt; but was:&amp;lt;java.sql.SQLException: Database &apos;wombat&apos; not found.&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derbyTesting.functionTests.tests.tools.DerbyLogTest.testDerbyLog(DerbyLogTest.java:110)&lt;br/&gt;
        at sun.reflect.NativeMethodAccessorImpl.invoke0(Native Method)&lt;br/&gt;
        at sun.reflect.NativeMethodAccessorImpl.invoke(NativeMethodAccessorImpl.java:39)&lt;br/&gt;
        at sun.reflect.DelegatingMethodAccessorImpl.invoke(DelegatingMethodAccessorImpl.java:25)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derbyTesting.junit.BaseTestCase.runBare(BaseTestCase.java:95)&lt;br/&gt;
        at junit.extensions.TestDecorator.basicRun(TestDecorator.java:22)&lt;br/&gt;
        at junit.extensions.TestSetup$1.protect(TestSetup.java:19)&lt;br/&gt;
        at junit.extensions.TestSetup.run(TestSetup.java:23)&lt;br/&gt;
        at org.apache.derbyTesting.junit.BaseTestSetup.run(BaseTestSetup.java:57)&lt;br/&gt;
        at junit.extensions.TestDecorator.basicRun(TestDecorator.java:22)&lt;br/&gt;
        at junit.extensions.TestSetup$1.protect(TestSetup.java:19)&lt;br/&gt;
        at junit.extensions.TestSetup.run(TestSetup.java:23)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FAILURES!!!&lt;br/&gt;
Tests run: 74,  Failures: 2,  Errors: 0&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12540512" author="kmarsden" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 18:13:08 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Is the issue perhaps be that previous tests have written to the log. If you look at derby.log directly does it perhaps have the sysinfo but later in the file?  If that is the case, perhaps setting derby.infolog.append=false would clean up the log before starting.&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12541451" author="kmarsden" created="Fri, 9 Nov 2007 22:01:51 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I backed out the change, because it was causing errors starting Derby wtih classes.  In addition to resolving whatever problem is causing sysinfo to fail, we should probably update the patch so that errors running sysinfo are only logged and cannot cause the server to fail to boot.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12545514" author="moazeni" created="Mon, 26 Nov 2007 17:14:59 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Kathey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not able to reproduce this problem with sane=true&lt;br/&gt;
in ant.properties. I am attaching another patch with this&lt;br/&gt;
issue. Can you please try this and let me know if you can&lt;br/&gt;
reproduce the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks&lt;br/&gt;
Ramin&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12547932" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 3 Dec 2007 18:42:42 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Ramin,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your continued work on this patch. With the patch I do not see the initializer error pointing my classpath to the classes directory, but I don&apos;t really understand how your changes sought to fix it. Could you explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running lang/triggerGeneral.sql I see a JVM crash with both IBM 1.5 and Sun 1.6 JDK&apos;s.  The problem seems to arise from the fact that sysinfo registers the JCC driver in the following code in&lt;br/&gt;
package org.apache.derby.impl.tools.sysinfo.Main.checkFile(String filename)&lt;/p&gt;

{
		    c = Class.forName(&quot;com.ibm.db2.jcc.DB2Driver&quot;);
		    m = c.getMethod(&quot;getJCCBuildNumber&quot;, null);
		    o = c.newInstance();
		    build = (Integer)m.invoke(o,null);
}
&lt;p&gt;	} catch (ClassNotFoundException cnfe) &lt;/p&gt;
{
		    c = Class.forName(&quot;com.ibm.db2.jcc.DB2Version&quot;);
		    m = c.getMethod(&quot;getBuildNumber&quot;, null);
		    o = c.newInstance();
		    build = (Integer)m.invoke(o,null);
	        }
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then there seems to be some bug in JCC that we are getting the T2 driver for &lt;br/&gt;
jdbc:default:connection.  But it seems like a bad side effect of sysinfo that the JCC Driver is getting loaded.  I think it would be acceptable for sysinfo to just use &lt;br/&gt;
com.ibm.db2.jcc.DB2Version.getBuildNumber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the thread that fails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NULL           ----------------------&lt;br/&gt;
3XMTHREADINFO      &quot;main&quot; (TID:0x41431300, sys_thread_t:0x000382D8, state:R, native ID:0x000012E0) prio=5&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/uw/UWConnection.DBConnect(Native Method)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/uw/UWConnection.a(UWConnection.java:673)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/uw/f.b(f.java:254)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/uw/UWConnection.a(UWConnection.java:610)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/uw/UWConnection.b(UWConnection.java:463)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/uw/UWConnection.&amp;lt;init&amp;gt;(UWConnection.java:255)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at com/ibm/db2/jcc/DB2Driver.connect(DB2Driver.java:236)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at java/sql/DriverManager.getConnection(DriverManager.java:562)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at java/sql/DriverManager.getConnection(DriverManager.java:208)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derbyTesting/functionTests/tests/lang/userDefMethods.derby388(userDefMethods.java:89)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/exe/ac12564092x0116xa132x1d95xffffa334cdd074.g0(Bytecode PC:36)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at sun/reflect/NativeMethodAccessorImpl.invoke0(Native Method)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at sun/reflect/NativeMethodAccessorImpl.invoke(NativeMethodAccessorImpl.java:64(Compiled Code))&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at sun/reflect/DelegatingMethodAccessorImpl.invoke(DelegatingMethodAccessorImpl.java:43(Compiled Code))&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at java/lang/reflect/Method.invoke(Method.java:615(Compiled Code))&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/services/reflect/ReflectMethod.invoke(ReflectMethod.java:46)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/sql/execute/CallStatementResultSet.open(CallStatementResultSet.java:57)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/sql/GenericPreparedStatement.execute(GenericPreparedStatement.java:370(Compiled Code))&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/jdbc/EmbedStatement.executeStatement(EmbedStatement.java:1228)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/jdbc/EmbedStatement.execute(EmbedStatement.java:618)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/jdbc/EmbedStatement.execute(EmbedStatement.java:550)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/ij.executeImmediate(ij.java:330(Compiled Code))&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/utilMain.doCatch(utilMain.java:508)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/utilMain.runScriptGuts(utilMain.java:350)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/utilMain.go(utilMain.java:248)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/Main.go(Main.java:215)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/Main.mainCore(Main.java:181)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/impl/tools/ij/Main.main(Main.java:73)&lt;br/&gt;
4XESTACKTRACE          at org/apache/derby/tools/ij.main(ij.java:59)&lt;br/&gt;
NULL &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a white space diff in AllPackages.  There is commented out code that should be removed.  There should be comments explaining the class DumpTempWriter, what bothPlaces means and the run method.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12549482" author="dyret" created="Fri, 7 Dec 2007 17:31:02 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Removing &apos;patch available&apos; since it would appear that the latest comments cannot be addressed without uploading a new version of the patch. (Feel free to change it back if I&apos;ve mis-understood something).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12703920" author="kmarsden" created="Wed, 29 Apr 2009 01:45:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;No activity in over a year, so unassigning this issue. Ramin, please reassign yourself if you are still interested in pursuing this issue.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12777323" author="kmarsden" created="Fri, 13 Nov 2009 01:41:11 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;It has become apparent to me that having sysinfo in the derby.log, especially in combination with &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-4441&quot; title=&quot;Change sysinfo to print out more specific JVM information&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-4441&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-4441&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would improve supportability significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In complex systems it has been difficult to gather the important version details because there may be many different distributions of java and derby on the problematic machine.  There is no guarantee that sysinfo run from the comand line will match up with the environment causing the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be so useful, in fact, that I think sysinfo should print with the boot message by default and we should just provide an option to turn it off.  It could eliminate many round trips with instructions to set properties and gather information.  It would however,  increase the size of the boot message significantly.  Are there objections to implementing the sysinfo dump to the log on boot by default?&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12778661" author="myrna" created="Tue, 17 Nov 2009 00:07:11 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I can understand how valuable it will be in a Tech Support situation of a product that embeds another product that embeds another product that embeds Derby to have sysinfo - with additional jvm data - show up in derby.log without having to figure out where to set a property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do think if someone has already set derby.infolog.append=true, and is used to doing a lot of starting and shutting down, the derby.log could now grow quite large quickly. So I worry about doing this by default...&lt;br/&gt;
Did you intend to backport such a change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking perhaps sysinfo output could go to a separate log file, to show up wherever derby.log lives...?&lt;br/&gt;
But likely I over-estimate the growth of derby.log; and I agree something more than what we get currently will be useful.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12879380" author="kmarsden" created="Wed, 16 Jun 2010 17:53:43 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about this issue, perhaps the full sysinfo is just overkill for derby.log, especially considering all the extra permissions that are required. The critical information that is routinely needed in derby.log that is not there already is the jvm version and if possible the derby.jar location (not sure how to do this).  Maybe we should try to print just this information compactly to derby.log and not go for the full sysinfo.&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="13035483" author="kmarsden" created="Wed, 18 May 2011 17:48:57 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think now  what is needed from  sysinfo is now logged to derby.log by default with the diagnostics added in various other issues. We have &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The full derby version for derby.jar&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The class loader that loads derby.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The location from which derby.jar was loaded.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The full java version&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The user.dir and derby.system.home  locations.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The log location if it has been redirected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The only things that are missing from sysinfo are the full classpath, the exact version of other derby jar files  and the OS information . &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I don&apos;t think that the non-derby classpath entries are usually  relevant for embedded derby support  when looking at the derby.log and actually having the full classpath might be information users don&apos;t wish to share with the list.  Regarding the versions of the other derby.jar files, I could see that in rare cases it might be relevant if versions are mixed but in those  cases, the client or tools or whatever would typically have a separate running environment where sysinfo output would be more relevant.  Also adding these things would add bulk to the boot message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do think the OS information would be useful to have, e.g,&lt;br/&gt;
OS name:         Windows XP&lt;br/&gt;
OS architecture: x86&lt;br/&gt;
OS version:      5.1 build 2600 Service Pack 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if nobody objects. I would like to open an issue to add the OS  info to the boot message and close this issue.&lt;/p&gt;







</comment>
                            <comment id="13035833" author="kmarsden" created="Thu, 19 May 2011 00:03:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Linking to &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-5340&quot; title=&quot;Comment in demo server policy should follow RFC 2606 convention&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-5340&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-5340&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is for logging operating system information&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13035838" author="kmarsden" created="Thu, 19 May 2011 00:05:21 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The solution of logging this information directly in derby.log  without going through the sysinfo tools code and without any special properties  seems preferable.. &lt;br/&gt;
Functionality has been implemented except fro &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-5240&quot; title=&quot;Log Operating system information to derby.log on boot&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-5240&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-5240&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is pending.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13685304" author="knutanders" created="Mon, 17 Jun 2013 10:19:37 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;bulk update&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Close all resolved issues that haven&apos;t been updated for more than one year.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="12310010">
                    <name>Incorporates</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="incorporates">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12467914">DERBY-4715</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                        </issuelinktype>
                            <issuelinktype id="10030">
                    <name>Reference</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="relates to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12345608">DERBY-1487</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
            <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12507684">DERBY-5240</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is related to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12382070">DERBY-3188</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
            <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12440557">DERBY-4441</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12365434" name="DERBY-1272v5.diff" size="2481" author="moazeni" created="Sun, 9 Sep 2007 22:41:35 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12369031" name="DERBY-1272v6.diff" size="9873" author="moazeni" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 16:04:18 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369032" name="DERBY-1272v6.stat" size="438" author="moazeni" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 16:04:18 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12370221" name="DERBY-1272v8.diff" size="5310" author="moazeni" created="Mon, 26 Nov 2007 17:14:58 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12334287" name="derby-1272-pre.diff" size="1142" author="fuzzylogic" created="Fri, 19 May 2006 05:04:08 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12334419" name="derby-1272-pre2.diff" size="5776" author="fuzzylogic" created="Tue, 23 May 2006 03:03:39 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12336395" name="derby-1272-pre3.diff" size="1760" author="fuzzylogic" created="Thu, 6 Jul 2006 08:37:10 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12336522" name="derby-1272-v4.diff" size="3690" author="fuzzylogic" created="Sat, 8 Jul 2006 09:18:01 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>8.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Fri, 19 May 2006 04:04:08 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>29923</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0g93:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>36451</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>