<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:40:58 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-1522/DERBY-1522.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-1522] Switch(if supported) from Derby Authorization to Derby SQL Standard Authorization needs to be tested</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1522</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;There has been discussions on the Derby-dev list about switch from Derby Authorization to Derby SQL Standard Authorization for existing databases. If we do decide to support a switch like that, testing needs to be done/added to make sure everything works fine after the switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ps I have added this JIRA entry to JDBC component but I am not 100% sure if that is the right component.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12346114">DERBY-1522</key>
            <summary>Switch(if supported) from Derby Authorization to Derby SQL Standard Authorization needs to be tested</summary>
                <type id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/task.png">Task</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="deepa">Deepa Remesh</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="mamtas">Mamta A. Satoor</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Mon, 17 Jul 2006 18:12:48 +0100</created>
                <updated>Thu, 13 Dec 2007 09:05:03 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Fri, 15 Sep 2006 22:41:53 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.2.1.6</version>
                    <version>10.3.1.4</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.2.1.6</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>10.3.1.4</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Test</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12424694" author="bandaram" created="Tue, 1 Aug 2006 00:33:16 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I was looking through all GRANT/REVOKE sub-tasks and related bugs. I am not sure exactly what this entry was filed to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derby already supports switching from Derby authorization mode to SQL authorization mode. I think some of Deepa&apos;s tests already test this, though her changes are not committed yet. Not sure how much coverage those tests provide.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12424696" author="deepa" created="Tue, 1 Aug 2006 00:52:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I am covering a part of this in upgrade testing. I have a patch attached to &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1521&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade test needs to be enhanced to test grant revoke&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1521&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1521&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is pending review. In this patch, I have added a test to check that an upgraded database will support basic grant/revoke after switching to Derby SQL standard authorization. I am planning to add some more grant/revoke tests to be run after upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I am wondering if we should also test this switch for databases created in 10.2 itself. I mean test that a database created in 10.2 without SQL standard authorization can be switched to SQL standard authorization. Maybe, the code paths are not different for the switch of an upgraded database and a 10.2 database ? In that case, we may not need this test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also be good to know what kind of test coverage is expected to test the &quot;switch&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12424701" author="mamtas" created="Tue, 1 Aug 2006 02:16:51 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I filed this jira entry to make sure that we test the switching and make sure everything works fine. Satheesh, you probably already added the test when you wrote the switching code but I was not sure and hence thought this jira entry would a good place holder for that task.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12424703" author="mamtas" created="Tue, 1 Aug 2006 02:29:36 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Deepa, you are right about testing the switch for both of following cases&lt;br/&gt;
1)As part of pre-10.2 db upgrade&lt;br/&gt;
2)A database created in 10.2  w/o SQL Standard Authorization gets switched to SQL Standard Authorization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&apos;t given much thought to what kind of testing is involved. One thing that comes to my mind though is after the upgrade, all the existing schemas and objects in them should be owned by the dba and any other users will need to have permissions granted to them by the dba. Also, right after the upgrade, there should be nothing in the permissions related system tables because dba owns everything and no permissions has been granted to anyone yet. Similarly, the dependency manager should not have any permission related dependencies because dba does not need any permissions. Currently, dependency manager uses SYSDEPENDS table to keep track of permissions required for various objects. So, a check of SYSDEPENDS for permission dependencies will be a good idea in the tests right after the upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks of any other tests that we should be writing, please add them to this Jira entry.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12425269" author="deepa" created="Wed, 2 Aug 2006 17:01:54 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Mamta for sharing your thoughts on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading this and the comments in &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I am confused and wondering what the planned behaviour for 10.2 is regarding the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Mamta says: &quot;after the upgrade, all the existing schemas and objects in them should be owned by the dba and any other users will need to have permissions granted to them by the dba.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current behaviour is what Mamta says. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is open to change the behaviour as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Upgrading a database from 10.1 to 10.2 should automatically change database owner, recorded as owner of system schemas in sysschemas, from pseudo user &apos;DBA&apos; to authorizationID of the user attempting upgrade.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is same as what the spec says.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; mentions adding 5 system routines to routine permission table after a full upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; planned for 10.2 or are we planning to keep the current behaviour?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12425289" author="mamtas" created="Wed, 2 Aug 2006 17:48:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Deepa, to be more precise, in my statement&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;after the upgrade, all the existing schemas and objects in them should be owned by the dba and any other users will need to have permissions granted to them by the dba.&quot; , the &lt;b&gt;dba&lt;/b&gt; is the user who is attempting the upgrade. So, the correct behavior should be what &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is proposing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; should go into 10.2 but I am not sure if anyone is looking into it.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12425295" author="deepa" created="Wed, 2 Aug 2006 17:56:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the clarification, Mamta. I&apos;ll take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12425338" author="bandaram" created="Wed, 2 Aug 2006 19:45:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;1) Mamta says: &quot;after the upgrade, all the existing schemas and objects in them should be owned by the dba and any other users will need to have permissions granted to them by the dba.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t think that is true... Even in Derby authorization mode, schemas created by regular users have their authorizationId recorded in sysschemas. Derby authorization mode only recognises fullAccessUsers (who can modify any object owned by anyone) or readOnlyAccess or no access. But once switching to SQL authorization mode, only schema owners would have access to objects in their schema and others would need explicit GRANT from schema owner to be able to access them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as additional testing for switching from Derby authorization mode to SQL mode, tests to cover include new restrictions we currently have on SQL authorization mode and to make sure they are actually enforced correctly. Some of the items to check, after switching to SQL authorization mode, include 1) Only owners can access their objects 2) regular users can only create a schema that matches their authorizationId 3) Database owner can access any object in the system 4) definer model being correctly enforced etc. 5) Access to many system routines are restricted 6) Cann&apos;t switch mode back to Derby authorization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Deepa for looking at &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1544&quot; title=&quot;Address remaining upgrade task(s) to complete full upgrade mechanism for GRANT/REVOKE, specifically with changing database owner name from &amp;#39;DBA&amp;#39; to authorizationId of user invoking upgrade.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1544&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1544&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12427361" author="deepa" created="Thu, 10 Aug 2006 23:39:31 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I had briefly looked at this task as I was working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1521&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade test needs to be enhanced to test grant revoke&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1521&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1521&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I think we can cover the testing suggested by doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Create a database without setting derby.database.sqlAuthorization system property.&lt;br/&gt;
2) Test that grant/revoke statements are not supported&lt;br/&gt;
3) Set derby.database.sqlAuthorization (as a database property) to true. Shutdown and reconnect to database.&lt;br/&gt;
4) Test grant/revoke works by running lang/grantRevokeDDL.sql. This test seems to cover all the scenarios suggested.&lt;br/&gt;
5) Set derby.database.sqlAuthorization (as a database property) to false. Shutdown and reconnect to database.&lt;br/&gt;
6) Test that grant/revoke still works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me. only step 4 (running the existing test) seems to be a bit involved. Dan has suggested few options for this in &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1521&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade test needs to be enhanced to test grant revoke&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1521&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1521&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Just posting this in case someone is planning to get to it soon.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12430258" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 24 Aug 2006 15:41:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Bumping the urgency of this issue.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432941" author="deepa" created="Wed, 6 Sep 2006 20:12:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I was trying to write a JUnit test case for this issue. The attached patch &apos;d1522_junit_v1.diff&apos; (which is not for commit) covers the first part of the test. It is a small JUnit test which just checks grant/revoke is not available when sql authorization property is not set. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I would like to set this property to true and then check grant/revoke is supported. I see that DatabasePropertyTestSetup has some methods to set database properties. I tried this but for the sql authorization property to take effect, we would need to shutdown and reconnect to the database. Shutdown can be done using existing TestUtil method but I wanted to check if there is something for this in JUnit helper classes. Also, is it possible to use DatabasePropertyTestSetup to set a property only for a particular test method?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first attempt in writing a JUnit test and would appreciate help in how to proceed with this.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433121" author="djd" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 15:02:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The TestUtil class will not correctly report the &quot;framework&quot; when a JUnit test is run standalone. It would be great to have&lt;br/&gt;
some shutdown database and shutdown server method in the junit classes that works from TestConfiguration. I assume&lt;br/&gt;
that its location would be in TestConfiguration to match the openConnection() methods there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the second issue I think you can do something like this, if you had a test fixture method called &quot;grantTestAfterChange&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;public static Suite suite() &lt;/p&gt;
{
    // Adds all methodsthat  start with &apos;test &apos;as test fixtures
   TestSuite suite = new TestSuite(MyClass.class);

    suite.addTest(new DatabasePropertyTestSetup (new MyClass(&quot;grantTestAfterChange&quot;, props));
}</comment>
                            <comment id="12433152" author="deepa" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 17:03:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Dan for the suggestions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try this, I used TestUtil methods for now. I&apos;ll open a Jira for adding shutdown methods in JUnit classes. I am able to run a particular test method with a specific setup. I think we need a small change in DatabasePropertyTestSetup.tearDown method where it tries to reset the properties to null. This gives an exception for &apos;derby.database.sqlAuthorization&apos; property. Setting to null may not be supported for all properties.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12433273" author="deepa" created="Fri, 8 Sep 2006 00:23:23 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching a patch &apos;derby1522_v2.diff. It includes a JUnit test for testing the switch to SQL standard authorization. It tests following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. grant/revoke is not available if derby.database.sqlAuthorization property is not set.&lt;br/&gt;
2. grant/revoke is available when derby.database.sqlAuthorization is set to true.&lt;br/&gt;
3. Once derby.database.sqlAuthorization is set to true, it cannot be set to any other value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This patch also modifies DatabasePropertyTestSetup.tearDown method. The tearDown method resets the property values to old values. It will now ignore exceptions when property reset is not supported. I am including this small change in the above patch. (I had opened &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1827&quot; title=&quot;DatabasePropertyTestSetup.tearDown method gives exception when resetting properties&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1827&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1827&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the issue with tearDown method. ). I am using TestUtil.getConnection method to shutdown the database. I have opened &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1826&quot; title=&quot;Add JUnit utility methods for database/server shutdown&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1826&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1826&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to add methods to Derby&apos;s JUnit classes for shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the new test internally sets derby.database.sqlAuthorization property which cannot be reset, it may cause problems in tests which share the same database and rely on the value of this property. I am checking it does not affect any current tests by running derbyall. I have successfully run the new JUnit test standalone and as part of harness using Sun JDK 1.4.2 on Windows XP.  Please take a look at this patch and provide feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433396" author="deepa" created="Fri, 8 Sep 2006 14:56:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;derbyall passed with &apos;derby1522_v2.diff&apos; patch using Sun jdk 1.4.2 on Windows XP. Please review/commit this patch. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433454" author="mikem" created="Fri, 8 Sep 2006 18:38:19 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I ran full set of tests against ibm14.2, committed test only change to trunk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;m3_142:222&amp;gt;svn commit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding         java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\lang\SQLAuthorizationPropTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\lang&amp;#95;Suite.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\SQLStateConstants.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\junit\DatabasePropertyTestSetup.java&lt;br/&gt;
Transmitting file data ....&lt;br/&gt;
Committed revision 441584.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433478" author="deepa" created="Fri, 8 Sep 2006 20:29:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Mike for committing the patch. I would like this patch to be merged to 10.2. Merge command:&lt;br/&gt;
svn merge -r 441583:441584 &lt;a href=&quot;https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/db/derby/code/trunk&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/db/derby/code/trunk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried the merge and ran the new test successfully in 10.2 branch. Can a committer please merge this change to 10.2? &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435131" author="deepa" created="Fri, 15 Sep 2006 22:41:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Verified the fix for this issue is in trunk and 10.2. Thanks Mike and Rick for the commits.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12551373" author="fuzzylogic" created="Thu, 13 Dec 2007 09:05:03 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;This issue has been resolved for over a year with no further movement. Closing.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="12310010">
                    <name>Incorporates</name>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is part of">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12312336">DERBY-464</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12340285" name="d1522_junit_v1.diff" size="4000" author="deepa" created="Wed, 6 Sep 2006 20:12:53 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340286" name="d1522_junit_v1.status" size="187" author="deepa" created="Wed, 6 Sep 2006 20:12:53 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340423" name="derby1522_v2.diff" size="10460" author="deepa" created="Fri, 8 Sep 2006 00:23:23 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340424" name="derby1522_v2.status" size="351" author="deepa" created="Fri, 8 Sep 2006 00:23:23 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>4.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Mon, 31 Jul 2006 23:33:16 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>30031</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy106n:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>39680</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310050" key="com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.customfieldtypes:select">
                        <customfieldname>Urgency</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                                <customfieldvalue key="10051"><![CDATA[Urgent]]></customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                    </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>