<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:12:25 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-1784/DERBY-1784.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-1784] When qualifying a column name with its synonym name in the select list, Derby throws SQLSTATE 42X04.</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1784</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;When qualifying a synonym with its name in the select list, Derby throws SQLSTATE 42X04 but if there is no qualification of the column, then the select statement executes successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ij version 10.3&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; connect &apos;jdbc:derby:wombat;create=true&apos; user &apos;user1&apos; as user1;&lt;br/&gt;
WARNING 01J01: Database &apos;wombat&apos; not created, connection made to existing database instead.&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; create schema test1;&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; create schema test2;&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; create table test1.t1 ( id bigint not null );&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; create synonym test2.t1 for test1.t1;&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; set schema test1;&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; select t1.id from t1;&lt;br/&gt;
ID&lt;br/&gt;
--------------------&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0 rows selected&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; set schema test2;&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; select t1.id from t1;&lt;br/&gt;
ERROR 42X04: Column &apos;T1.ID&apos; is either not in any table in the FROM list or appears within a join specification and is outside the scope of the join specification or appears in a HAVING clause and is not in the GROUP BY list. If this is a CREATE or ALTER TABLE  statement then &apos;T1.ID&apos; is not a column in the target table&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ij&amp;gt; select id from t1;&lt;br/&gt;
ID&lt;br/&gt;
--------------------&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0 rows selected&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;------------------ Java Information ------------------&lt;br/&gt;
Java Version:    1.4.2_12&lt;br/&gt;
Java Vendor:     Sun Microsystems Inc.&lt;br/&gt;
Java home:       C:\Program Files\Java\j2re1.4.2_12&lt;br/&gt;
Java classpath:  classes;.&lt;br/&gt;
OS name:         Windows XP&lt;br/&gt;
OS architecture: x86&lt;br/&gt;
OS version:      5.1&lt;br/&gt;
Java user name:  Yip&lt;br/&gt;
Java user home:  C:\Documents and Settings\Yip&lt;br/&gt;
Java user dir:   C:\work3\derby\trunk&lt;br/&gt;
java.specification.name: Java Platform API Specification&lt;br/&gt;
java.specification.version: 1.4&lt;br/&gt;
--------- Derby Information --------&lt;br/&gt;
JRE - JDBC: J2SE 1.4.2 - JDBC 3.0&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;C:\work3\derby\trunk\classes&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
----------------- Locale Information -----------------&lt;br/&gt;
Current Locale :  [English/United States &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;en_US&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;de_DE&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;es&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;fr&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;it&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;ja_JP&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;ko_KR&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;pt_BR&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;zh_CN&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
Found support for locale: &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;zh_TW&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
         version: 10.3.0.0 alpha - (438358)&lt;br/&gt;
------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment>Any environment</environment>
        <key id="12348939">DERBY-1784</key>
            <summary>When qualifying a column name with its synonym name in the select list, Derby throws SQLSTATE 42X04.</summary>
                <type id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/bug.png">Bug</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="yipng">Yip Ng</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="yipng">Yip Ng</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Wed, 30 Aug 2006 20:39:34 +0100</created>
                <updated>Mon, 5 Jul 2010 18:32:29 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Fri, 22 Sep 2006 18:06:51 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.1.3.1</version>
                    <version>10.2.1.6</version>
                    <version>10.3.1.4</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.1.3.3</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>10.2.2.0</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>10.3.1.4</fixVersion>
                                    <component>SQL</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>1</votes>
                                    <watches>1</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12432266" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 02:53:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Just went through the related code area for this issue and I think I have a fix for this but need abit more time to confirm before I post the fix.  The problem is somewhat obvious, the column reference in the select list  is not resolved properly when it is qualified by a synonym table name at bind time of the column reference.  &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432277" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 08:39:42 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching patch for &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1784&quot; title=&quot;When qualifying a column name with its synonym name in the select list, Derby throws SQLSTATE 42X04.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1784&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1784&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for trunk.  derbyall passes.  The patch fixes the problem when a column reference is qualified by a synonym.  It is relatively small patch, appreciate if someone can review it.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432288" author="mikem" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 15:45:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I took a quick look at this patch.  Looks like it fixes the problem.  I have not looked at bind code before, so just looking for info.  I was sort of surprised to see this code at this level, I was expecting the check for synonym to be at a lower level, like when the ColumnReference was first initialized - maybe even totally hidden in the ColumnReference.  Is this possible, or does it have to wait  for this time/level in the code. &lt;br/&gt;
Hopefully someone more familar with the code can comment/take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of nits:&lt;br/&gt;
line longer than 80&lt;br/&gt;
2 different styles of open bracket in the same code segment, looks like surround code wants open bracket on newline.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432297" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 19:01:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Yes,  the resolution code may be move up to its caller ColumnReference&apos;s bindExpression() instead.  This method will eventually call FromList&apos;s bindColumnReferences().  I&apos;ll resubmit the patch but need to rerun derbyall to make sure.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432298" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 19:04:49 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Submitting derby1784-trunk-diff02.txt, moved the resolution logic for column references from FromList&apos;s bindColumnReference to ColumnReference&apos;s bindExpression.  &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432314" author="yipng" created="Sun, 3 Sep 2006 02:01:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Just noticed that my previous comments got cut off for some reason.  Here is the original comment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the resolution code may be move up to its caller ColumnReference&apos;s bindExpression() instead. This method will eventually call FromList&apos;s bindColumnReferences(). I&apos;ll resubmit the patch but need to rerun derbyall to make sure.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the column reference binding logic happens in ColumnReference&apos;s bindExpression(); however, the actual execution of such logic is delegated to FromList&apos;s bindColumnReferences() in the current existing code.  (bindTables() needed to be called before this method.)  So that is why I put the synonym resolution at the beginning of FromList&apos;s bindColumnReferences() since the actual logic is here.  I am also fine in placing this logic at ColumnReference&apos;s bindExpression() which may make more sense for locality reason.  &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432553" author="yipng" created="Tue, 5 Sep 2006 02:11:03 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;derbyall passes with patch derby1784-trunk-diff02.txt.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432590" author="yipng" created="Tue, 5 Sep 2006 10:15:22 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Unchecking patch available.  The current patch resolves the problem but is not yet optimal.&lt;br/&gt;
Will submit a follow-up patch after abit more investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12432875" author="mikem" created="Wed, 6 Sep 2006 16:27:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I ran a full test run on XP sun jdk1.4 run and got only some of the existing intermittent network server test failures - &lt;br/&gt;
I reran those individually and they passed.  The full set of tests ran in a reasonable time for my machine.   I am ok with committing your second patch, let me know if you want that patch committed or if I should wait for a different patch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12433007" author="yipng" created="Thu, 7 Sep 2006 01:54:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for verifying the patch.  I will be submitting another patch soon as I have found the current patch fails in some additional testcases that I wrote.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12434314" author="yipng" created="Wed, 13 Sep 2006 00:24:42 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching derby1784-trunk-diff03a.txt for &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1784&quot; title=&quot;When qualifying a column name with its synonym name in the select list, Derby throws SQLSTATE 42X04.&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1784&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1784&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The previous patches&apos;&lt;br/&gt;
technique is not optimal and does not work in all cases.  After studying the&lt;br/&gt;
compiler code abit more, I found that DML statements such as INSERT, UPDATE and DELETE also suffer from the same problem (they use different bind logic)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, this patch attempts to address all the stated problems above &lt;br/&gt;
when column reference is qualified with a synonym table name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental problem is that Derby does not keep the original unbound table name around once the synonym is resolved.  So the fix is to address this case and apply the qualification properly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the VIEW resolution case, the system needs to preserve the synonym name as VIEW gets expanded to a subquery, the name to be set should be the exposed name of the table and not the resolved table name.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For * expansion in the SELECT list, if the FROM clause happens to be a synonym, the system should prepend it with the unbound name and not the resolved table name.  This way the binding logic is normalized.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For DML cases, the synonym name needs to be normalized to its base table so that &lt;br/&gt;
setColumnDescriptor can apply correctly.  When the system binds the expression for this result column, it will resolve this properly since the column binding logic are in the respective FromTable subclasses implementation where they will use the exposed name this time to check for qualification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote more testcases for synonym.sql but I found out that this SQL file is actually not part of derbylang suite, so the patch added this back to the test bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;derbyall ran successfully.  Appreciate if someone can spend some time to review it.&lt;br/&gt;
Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12434317" author="yipng" created="Wed, 13 Sep 2006 00:33:49 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Comment correction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yip stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;For * expansion in the SELECT list, if the FROM clause happens to be a synonym, the system should prepend it with the unbound name and not the resolved table name.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should read as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;For * expansion in the SELECT list, if the table in FROM clause happens to be a synonym, the system should prepend it with the unbound name and not the resolved table name.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435117" author="army" created="Fri, 15 Sep 2006 21:56:23 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I reviewed derby1784-trunk-diff03a.txt and the changes look good overall.  I confirmed that the patch applies and builds, and I ran the new test cases with and without the code changes--as expected, they fail without the fix and pass with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have two questions/comments about the patch.  I don&apos;t think either of these is worthy of blocking the patch, but I&apos;m nonetheless curious...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1)  FromBaseTable.java:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two places where uses of &quot;tableName&quot; have been replaced with&lt;br/&gt;
calls to getOrigTableName():&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;(correlationName != null) ? correlationName : tableName.getTableName(),&lt;br/&gt;
+					(correlationName != null) ? correlationName : getOrigTableName().getTableName(), &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;return tableName.getFullTableName();&lt;br/&gt;
+			return getOrigTableName().getFullTableName();&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;return getResultColumnsForList(allTableName, resultColumns, tableName);&lt;br/&gt;
+		return getResultColumnsForList(allTableName, resultColumns, &lt;br/&gt;
+				getOrigTableName());&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But all other occurrences of &quot;tableName&quot; are left as they are.  Can you perhaps explain the distinction between when one should be used over the other?  Or put another way, can you explain why these three-&lt;del&gt;and only these three&lt;/del&gt;&lt;del&gt;occurrences were changed but the rest were left alone?  If possible, I think it&apos;d be good to add comments&lt;/del&gt;&lt;del&gt;perhaps as part of the javadoc for the new &quot;getOrigTableName()&quot; method?&lt;/del&gt;&lt;del&gt;explaining when that method should be used (as opposed to just using the tableName field).  That might help developers down the road avoid using the method incorrectly.  The other option is to simply add comments to the places where you used &quot;getOrigTableName()&lt;/del&gt;-you could perhaps just use what you wrote in your previous comment for this Jira, which I think gives a good enough explanation...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2)  DMLModStatementNode.java:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+			ResultColumn column = (ResultColumn) rcl.elementAt( i );&lt;br/&gt;
+			ColumnReference	reference = column.getReference();&lt;br/&gt;
+			String crTableName = reference.getTableName();&lt;br/&gt;
+&lt;br/&gt;
+			if ( reference != null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; crTableName != null)&lt;br/&gt;
+			{&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s a check to see if &quot;reference&quot; is null, but that check happens AFTER &quot;reference&quot; is used.  This seems to suggest to me that either 1) reference can never be null, in which case there&apos;s no need to check for it, or 2) reference CAN be null but there aren&apos;t any test cases for such a situation.  Do you know which of these is true?  I &lt;b&gt;think&lt;/b&gt; it&apos;s the former--i.e.that in case of updates or inserts, the result column will be for the target base table and thus cannot have a reference that is null...but can you confirm this?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435146" author="mikem" created="Sat, 16 Sep 2006 00:07:30 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I plan to work on committing this change.  I have run full set of tests against ibm1.4.2 JVM and got 2 unrelated &quot;expected/intermittent&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
test failures in :&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbynetmats/DerbyNet/derbynetmats/ShutDownDBWhenNSShutsDownTest.diff&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbynetmats/DerbyNet/jdbcapi/blobclob4BLOB.diff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will wait for a response to army&apos;s comments before going ahead with this patch, just to know what contributer wants.  If anyone else wants a chance to review before committing let me know.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435152" author="yipng" created="Sat, 16 Sep 2006 00:43:42 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for taking the time to review the patch, Army.  Responses to your questions/comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1)  One would use getOrigTableName() for qualifying column names at bind phase only ( if the column name is qualified by the user)  There are alot of code in the compiler layer and I have spent quite some time to determine where the fix should go with minimal code impact.  I only applied the additonal logic at areas where the binding logic uses &quot;exposedName&quot; and it makes perfect sense to place the logic here since&lt;br/&gt;
the correlation name are handled in a similar manner.  Once the underlying table descriptor is determined and bound, the table name can be just thought of an alias to the table descriptor.  For other methods that still use the tableName member field, I left them AS IS because there are many places in the code that relies on its name to find the actual table descriptor, so changing those methods will certainly break the system.  If synonym is not involved, getOrigTableName() will return tableName anyway; thus, limiting the impact on the compiler subsystem.  I think it is a good idea to put additional comments to getOrigTableName(), I&apos;ll submit another follow up patch for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2)  Good catch, it looks like a refactor error on my part, I meant to do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if ( reference != null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; reference.getTableName() != null)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll fix this also and resubmit the patch.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12435157" author="yipng" created="Sat, 16 Sep 2006 01:04:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching derby1784-trunk-diff03b.txt to address Army&apos;s comments and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435522" author="mikem" created="Mon, 18 Sep 2006 17:55:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I ran full set of successful tests against ibm 1.4.2.  Thanks Army for doing the technical review.&lt;br/&gt;
I made some minor formatting changes to the patch to make it fit in 80 characters.  I would like&lt;br/&gt;
to see this fix get into 10.2 and 10.1.  I plan on looking at the merge to 10.1 and will look at merge to 10.2 if that is not done by a rick &quot;mega-merge&quot;.  If the merge to 10.1 is not clean may need help from the contributer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;m1_ibm142:91&amp;gt;svn commit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending        java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\sql\compile\DMLModStatementNode.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\sql\compile\FromBaseTable.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\sql\compile\FromTable.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\sql\compile\InsertNode.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\engine\org\apache\derby\impl\sql\compile\UpdateNode.java&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\master\synonym.out&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\suites\derbylang.runall&lt;br/&gt;
Sending        java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\lang\synonym.sql&lt;br/&gt;
Transmitting file data ........&lt;br/&gt;
Committed revision 447469.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435530" author="mikem" created="Mon, 18 Sep 2006 18:01:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;meant to include in last comment that my commit to trunk was based on the derby1784-trunk-stat03b.txt patch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435607" author="yipng" created="Tue, 19 Sep 2006 00:14:13 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching 10.1 backport patch derby1784-10.1-diff01.txt.  derbylang passes successfully.  Running derbyall now.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435625" author="yipng" created="Tue, 19 Sep 2006 03:58:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I ran derbyall against a &lt;b&gt;clean&lt;/b&gt; 10.1 build and the following tests failed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;derbyall/derbyall.fail:unit/T_Diagnosticable.unit&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbyall.fail:i18n/urlLocale.sql&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbyall.fail:i18n/messageLocale.sql&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbyall.fail:i18n/iepnegativetests_ES.sql&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbynetclientmats/derbynetmats.fail:derbynet/sysinfo.java&lt;br/&gt;
derbyall/derbynetmats/derbynetmats.fail:derbynet/sysinfo.java&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are these tests known issues in 10.1?  I ran derbyall again with the patch and got the same result, so the patch didn&apos;t cause these failures.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12435804" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 19 Sep 2006 15:32:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Moving to 10.2.2.0.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12436067" author="mikem" created="Wed, 20 Sep 2006 01:08:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Ran full set of tests against 10.1 codeline, windows XP,  sun 1.4.2 jvm.  I got a complete clean run!!&lt;br/&gt;
Committed as is the provided derby1784-10.1-diff01.txt patch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving issue open until fix makes its way into the 10.2 branch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12436923" author="yipng" created="Fri, 22 Sep 2006 18:06:51 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This issue is resolved as it is now integrated into 10.1, 10.2 and trunk.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12551413" author="fuzzylogic" created="Thu, 13 Dec 2007 09:05:12 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;This issue has been resolved for over a year with no further movement. Closing.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12341090" name="derby1784-10.1-diff01.txt" size="33892" author="yipng" created="Tue, 19 Sep 2006 00:14:13 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12341089" name="derby1784-10.1-stat01.txt" size="676" author="yipng" created="Tue, 19 Sep 2006 00:14:13 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340091" name="derby1784-trunk-diff01.txt" size="4211" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 08:39:42 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340096" name="derby1784-trunk-diff02.txt" size="4130" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 19:04:49 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340697" name="derby1784-trunk-diff03a.txt" size="29749" author="yipng" created="Wed, 13 Sep 2006 00:24:42 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340978" name="derby1784-trunk-diff03b.txt" size="29912" author="yipng" created="Sat, 16 Sep 2006 01:04:26 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340090" name="derby1784-trunk-stat01.txt" size="324" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 08:39:42 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340095" name="derby1784-trunk-stat02.txt" size="331" author="yipng" created="Sat, 2 Sep 2006 19:04:49 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340696" name="derby1784-trunk-stat03a.txt" size="700" author="yipng" created="Wed, 13 Sep 2006 00:24:41 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12340977" name="derby1784-trunk-stat03b.txt" size="700" author="yipng" created="Sat, 16 Sep 2006 01:04:26 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>10.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Sat, 2 Sep 2006 14:45:32 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>22703</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0prb:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>37991</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>