<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:34:23 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-2377/DERBY-2377.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-2377] Document language based ordering which will be implemented by code related sub-tasks of DERBY-1478.</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-2377</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an effort going on to implement language based ordering. This will be implemented by various code-related subtasks of &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1478&quot; title=&quot;Add built in language based ordering and like processing to Derby&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1478&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1478&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The functional spec is attached to &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1478&quot; title=&quot;Add built in language based ordering and like processing to Derby&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1478&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1478&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This feature will need accompanying documentation changes and this Jira entry is to track that work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12363710">DERBY-2377</key>
            <summary>Document language based ordering which will be implemented by code related sub-tasks of DERBY-1478.</summary>
                <type id="7" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/subtask_alternate.png">Sub-task</type>
                            <parent id="12345445">DERBY-1478</parent>
                                    <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="scotsmatrix">Laura Stewart</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="mamtas">Mamta A. Satoor</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Tue, 27 Feb 2007 16:00:16 +0000</created>
                <updated>Fri, 21 Jan 2011 17:49:50 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Fri, 8 Jun 2007 18:02:54 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.3.1.4</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.3.1.4</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Documentation</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12483281" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 22 Mar 2007 19:22:28 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I looked over the latest spec attached to Derby-1478.  I have a few questions about the documentation required for this new capability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) How will the new attribute be specifed when a database is created?&lt;br/&gt;
Is the example below accurate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;       jdbc:derby:MexicanDB;create=true;territory=es_MX;collation=TERRITORY_BASED &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Where should this new capability be documented.&lt;br/&gt;
Here is what I have come up with but you might have other thoughts &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Reference Guide&lt;br/&gt;
Section = Setting attributes for the database connection URL   &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/ref/rrefattrib24612.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/ref/rrefattrib24612.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Create a new section under this section called &quot;collation = collation attribute&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Developers Guide&lt;br/&gt;
Section = Working with the database connection URL attributes   &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/devguide/cdevdvlp51654.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/devguide/cdevdvlp51654.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Add the new attribute to this list&lt;br/&gt;
Create a new section under this section called &quot;Creating a database with territory-based collation&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Are there any other places that you can think of?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12483285" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 22 Mar 2007 19:27:15 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Another topic (or set of topics) that is needed is a &lt;br/&gt;
conceptual topic explaining collation and how it works in Derby. &lt;br/&gt;
Which data types it works with, the fact that system tables are not included in the collation attribute, etc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to discuss the best place (book) for this type of information...&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12484156" author="mamtas" created="Mon, 26 Mar 2007 17:51:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Laura, I didn&apos;t forget about getting back to you on this. I am just too deep down in the design phase of this feature &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; so didn&apos;t put a response back. If it is ok with you, let me get back to you in couple of days. But if you are stuck, I can most certainly spend some time looking through the doc to suggest where should this attribute go.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12484161" author="scotsmatrix" created="Mon, 26 Mar 2007 18:05:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s fine, later in the week is okay. I do want to make sure that I have enough time to prepare the documentation before the end of April.  It seems that we might be looking at a new release in early May...&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12484552" author="mamtas" created="Tue, 27 Mar 2007 20:14:50 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Laura, answers to your questions&lt;br/&gt;
1) Yes, the example below is accurate. This collation attribute can only be specified at database create time.&lt;br/&gt;
       jdbc:derby:MexicanDB;create=true;territory=es_MX;collation=TERRITORY_BASED &lt;br/&gt;
Two possible values for collation are &quot;TERRITORY_BASED&quot; and &quot;UCS_BASIC&quot;.&lt;br/&gt;
2)The 2 places suggested by you in the doc sound good to me.  I didn&apos;t realize that 2 different docs talk about eh JDBC url attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12494417" author="scotsmatrix" created="Wed, 9 May 2007 00:12:43 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached are html versions of the updated files associated with this issue.&lt;br/&gt;
I would like to create a general topic that explains how Derby handles collation.&lt;br/&gt;
What I need is advice on where to put that topic - which is the best book to put that in...&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12494768" author="mamtas" created="Thu, 10 May 2007 16:01:18 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Laura, you changes look good. I only have one comment on the Reference Manual&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the lines in the Reference Manual change is as follows&lt;br/&gt;
*******&lt;b&gt;start existing line&lt;/b&gt;**********&lt;br/&gt;
If you include the collation attribute when you create the Derby database, the collation is based on the language and country codes that you specify with the territory attribute.&lt;br/&gt;
*******&lt;b&gt;end existing line&lt;/b&gt;************&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line should be modified to say follwoing&lt;br/&gt;
*******&lt;b&gt;start new line suggestion&lt;/b&gt;**&lt;br/&gt;
If you include the collation attribute with value TERRITORY_BASED when you create the Derby database, the collation is based on the language and country codes that you specify with the territory attribute.&lt;br/&gt;
*******&lt;b&gt;end new line suggestion&lt;/b&gt;****&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12494770" author="mamtas" created="Thu, 10 May 2007 16:18:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I looked through the existing documentation layout quickly and I am wondering if we should include a section on how Derby handles collation in Developer&apos;s Guide. It can go as a separate section either under &quot;Deploying Derby applications&quot; or as a separate section after &quot;Localizing Derby&quot; and at the same level as &quot;Localizing Derby&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12494790" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 10 May 2007 17:59:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Mamta. I&apos;ll make the change that you indicated for the Ref Manual and draft the text for the Dev Guide.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12494794" author="djd" created="Thu, 10 May 2007 18:21:17 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Another topic (or set of topics) that is needed is a&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt; conceptual topic explaining collation and how it works in Derby. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds good, getting a definition of what &quot;terrority based&quot; collation actually means is really needed in the documentation,&lt;br/&gt;
especially so app developers can understand how the collation in the database interacts with other systems that use&lt;br/&gt;
that provide collation. Some reference to a standard so that folks can see if the Derby collation is based upon known algorithms.&lt;br/&gt;
The standards most likely be from unicode.org and the SQL standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be great to figure out if the &quot;terrority based&quot; collation is actually the well-defined &quot;UNICODE&quot; collation from the SQL standard,&lt;br/&gt;
then a well-defined term could be used, &quot;UNICODE&quot; instead of the Derby specific &quot;TERRITORY_BASED&quot;. This would mean Derby&apos;s&lt;br/&gt;
collation would be well defined by both the SQL and the Unicode standards.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12496755" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 03:05:51 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching a DRAFT of a concept topic that is supposed to explain collation in Derby.&lt;br/&gt;
Please help me fill in the holes &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also Mamta suggested several places where the this topic might reside in the Developers Guide.&lt;br/&gt;
I believe that it should go immediately after the Loccalizing Derby section (which talks about locales).&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12496807" author="mikem" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 08:42:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;looked at latest html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3rd line about setting collation with no territory is interesting, I am not sure what the system should do.  mamta and I need to figure out what the system should do.  Seems like we should at least print a warning if we are not going to have basic collation in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last table is confusing to me.  What are you trying to say by listing the statements?  Also personally I would find it easier to&lt;br/&gt;
understand if you just grouped CHAR and VARCHAR together, and CLOB and LONG VARCHAR together.  I found myself trying &lt;br/&gt;
to figure out what is different between CHAR and VARCHAR - when the anser is none.  Collation can also affect any statement that can have a comparison operator  (ie. select, update, delete).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, I found it easiest to understand with a few simple examples.  Using basic vs english locale , I found the following &lt;br/&gt;
explanation useful.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In basic collation the numerical values of the unicode encoding of the characters is used directly for ordering.  So given a &lt;br/&gt;
dataset such as:  CREATE TABLE  FRUIT (NAME VARCHAR(20))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;apple&lt;br/&gt;
orange&lt;br/&gt;
Banana&lt;br/&gt;
Grape&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In default collation where all lower case letters sort before upper case letters, SELECT * FROM FRUIT ORDER BY NAME gives:&lt;br/&gt;
apple&lt;br/&gt;
orange&lt;br/&gt;
Banana&lt;br/&gt;
Grape&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In english teritory, ordering is different.  So in database created with english territory and territory based collation, the same &lt;br/&gt;
query: SELECT * FROM FRUIT ORDER BY NAME gives:&lt;br/&gt;
apple &lt;br/&gt;
Banana&lt;br/&gt;
Grape&lt;br/&gt;
orange&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collation also will affect comparison operators on the character datatypes.  So in default:&lt;br/&gt;
SELECT * FROM FRUIT WHERE NAME &amp;gt; Banana&lt;br/&gt;
Grape&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the the english territory, territory based collation&lt;br/&gt;
SELECT * FROM FRUIT WHERE NAME &amp;gt; Banana&lt;br/&gt;
Grape&lt;br/&gt;
orange&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO - provide LIKE example using norway example from kathy, a like query looking for _ should match aa:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think ascii is the same as the default except for my favorite norwegian character &apos;aa&apos; which is one character and sorts after z in Norway and is two and sorts before z in the default encoding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ij&amp;gt; connect &apos;jdbc:derby:wombat;create=true;collation=TERRITORY_BASED;territory=no&apos;;&lt;br/&gt;
WARNING 01J01: Database &apos;wombat&apos; not created, connection made to existing database instead.&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; create table t (vc varchar(30));&lt;br/&gt;
0 rows inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; insert into t values(&apos;acorn&apos;);&lt;br/&gt;
1 row inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; insert into t values(&apos;aacorn&apos;);&lt;br/&gt;
1 row inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; insert into t values(&apos;zebra&apos;);&lt;br/&gt;
1 row inserted/updated/deleted&lt;br/&gt;
ij&amp;gt; select * from t order by vc;&lt;br/&gt;
VC&lt;br/&gt;
------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
acorn&lt;br/&gt;
zebra&lt;br/&gt;
aacorn&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12496809" author="mikem" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 08:46:14 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;In  rrefattribcollation.html  :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the line:&lt;br/&gt;
The following example show the URL to create the MexicanDB database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;should be:&lt;br/&gt;
The following example shows the URL to create the MexicanDB database.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12496941" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 17:31:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Great feedback Mike.  I&apos;ll update the file accordingly and post a new version shortly.&lt;br/&gt;
Mamta - I will include Dan&apos;s comment on Derby-2669.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW - How do you determine the territory of the JVM?  Is there some Java command users can run?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12496944" author="mamtas" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 17:39:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Laura, I did a check in BasicDatabase.boot method and I see that we determine the territory of the JVM using following&lt;br/&gt;
Locale.getDefault()&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12497027" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 21:41:07 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching the updated conceptual file = cdevcollation.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still some collation questions on derby-dev that need to be answered.&lt;br/&gt;
Also, one lingering question from me about JVM in the comments on this issue Derby-2377.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12498850" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 24 May 2007 22:31:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I would appreciate a review of the new concept topic for collation.&lt;br/&gt;
This issue is for 10.3. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12498871" author="mikem" created="Thu, 24 May 2007 23:29:42 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I still having a hard time seeing the value of the table of valid expressions, and worry that the list is wrong - I have not had a chance to think about how collation may affect every statement.  I wonder if there is anything we can tie this to.  Somewhere we must explain where it is valid to use CHAR (because it can be compared) but can not use CLOB.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;again I am not sure of the right wording, but create index statement does not really include a comparison operator.   Internally the ordering of the index is very dependent on the collation of the datatypes but I don&apos;t think that is ever a user documented.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;going from our reference guide many of the things listed as statements are actually clauses.  So at least from the chapter of contents the following clauses could be affected:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;SQL clauses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;CONSTRAINT clause&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;GROUP BY clause&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;HAVING clause&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ORDER BY clause&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;WHERE clause&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12499248" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 25 May 2007 23:43:15 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching the latest version of the cdevcollation.html file (25 May 07)&lt;br/&gt;
Based on comments from Mike.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502044" author="mikem" created="Wed, 6 Jun 2007 20:05:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;i just noted none of your attachments have &quot;granted asf license&quot; ,  there is a box to tick when attach a file.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502046" author="mikem" created="Wed, 6 Jun 2007 20:07:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here is some updated text which I think would better fit at the top of the document.  I don&apos;t think we should try to describe the mechanics of the algorithm, just that we use the java support for this.  We are not providing support in this release for people to change these rules, we use the rules and the logic based on these rules that the JVM provides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Character-based collation in Derby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A character set is a set of symbols and encodings.  Derby supports a wide&lt;br/&gt;
range of character sets and encodes all of them using the&lt;br/&gt;
Unicode support provided by the java.lang.Character&lt;br/&gt;
class in the JVM in which it runs. See JVM specific documentation for this&lt;br/&gt;
class for exact level of Unicode Standard supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collation is a set of rules for comparing characters in a character set.&lt;br/&gt;
In Derby collation rules affect comparisons of the CHAR and VARCHAR data&lt;br/&gt;
type.  Collation rules also affect how the LIKE Boolean operator processes&lt;br/&gt;
CHAR, VARCHAR, CLOB, and LONG VARCHAR data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default Derby collation rule is based on the binary Unicode values of&lt;br/&gt;
the characters.  So a character is &amp;lt;, =, or &amp;gt; based on the numeric comparison&lt;br/&gt;
of the Unicode value.  This rule allows for very efficient comparison of&lt;br/&gt;
strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derby also supports the ability to define collation rules based on those&lt;br/&gt;
appropriate to a territory, and is referred to as &quot;territory based collation&quot;.&lt;br/&gt;
One can specifically set the territory of a database when it is created, or&lt;br/&gt;
it will default to the default territory of the JVM in which the database&lt;br/&gt;
is created.  Non default collation support is provided through the JVM&apos;s&lt;br/&gt;
java.text.RuleBasedCollator class and the JVM&apos;s set of rules associated with&lt;br/&gt;
the specified territory.   Details of how these rules are used to provide&lt;br/&gt;
territory specific collation can be seen by referring to the JVM specification.&lt;br/&gt;
Derby currently only supports running those rules that can be loaded dynamically&lt;br/&gt;
from the running JVM based on the territory attribute, user overrides to these&lt;br/&gt;
rules are not supported.  Territory based&lt;br/&gt;
collation will add extra procession overhead to all character based comparison&lt;br/&gt;
operations versus the default collation performance.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502052" author="mikem" created="Wed, 6 Jun 2007 20:16:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I am not really happy with how I refer to the JVM documentation, suggestions are welcome.  Basically I want to refer the reader to the JVM specification specific to his/her version of the JVM.  This could be 1.4 vs. 1.5 or sun vs. ibm vs. apache ....&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502368" author="chaase3" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 15:45:14 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think you&apos;re correct in referring to &quot;the JVM in which it runs&quot; or &quot;the JVM in which the database is created.&quot; For the first occurrence you might want to say &quot;Java Virtual Machine (JVM)&quot; for clarity. But when you mention documentation it is probably best to say &quot;Java API documentation&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API doc for java.lang.character points to the Unicode site (www.unicode.org) for details without giving an indication of exactly which version is supported. (See, for instance, &lt;a href=&quot;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/index.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/index.html&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502371" author="chaase3" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 15:51:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I meant to mention that the writeup in general looks excellent &amp;#8211; very clear.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502456" author="mikem" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:11:57 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;What I see when I go to :&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/lang/Character.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/lang/Character.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Is:&lt;br/&gt;
Character information is based on the Unicode Standard, version 4.0. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/lang/Character.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/lang/Character.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Is:&lt;br/&gt;
Character information is based on the Unicode Standard, version 3.0. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://java.sun.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/lang/Character.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://java.sun.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/lang/Character.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Is:&lt;br/&gt;
Character information is based on the Unicode Standard, version 4.0&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502472" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:52:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching the updated files for the Dev Guide&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502473" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:54:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching the updated files for the Ref Guide &lt;br/&gt;
and the patch derby2377_1.diff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that these are ready for final review and (hopefully) commit.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502480" author="mikem" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 20:13:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve reviewed all the attachments and am ok with commit of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the following is a little unclear, but would not hold up commit:&lt;br/&gt;
Non-default collation support is provided through the java.text.RuleBasedCollator class and the set of rules associated with the specified territory of the JVM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want it to be clear that each JVM can support many territories, it has a set of rules for each of these territories and it is independent of the the default territory of the JVM.  &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502602" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 8 Jun 2007 02:47:22 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;What about this replacement for the sentence you have concerns about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each JVM can support many territories that are independent from the default territory for the JVM.  Collation support for these additional territories is provided through the java.text.RuleBasedCollator class and the set of rules for these territories. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502876" author="mikem" created="Fri, 8 Jun 2007 17:49:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;the proposed sentence change sounds good.  With that change I have no additional comments on the proposed checkin.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502880" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 8 Jun 2007 18:02:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed revision 545561.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12502883" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 8 Jun 2007 18:03:50 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch updated based on Mikes approval of the sentence I proposed.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12359202" name="cdevcollation.html" size="8874" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:52:32 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12358284" name="cdevcollation.html" size="7139" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 25 May 2007 23:43:15 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12357658" name="cdevcollation.html" size="8044" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 21:41:07 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12357600" name="cdevcollation.html" size="5640" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 18 May 2007 03:05:51 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12359203" name="cdevdvlp51654.html" size="9607" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:52:32 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12356945" name="cdevdvlp51654.html" size="9607" author="scotsmatrix" created="Wed, 9 May 2007 00:12:43 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12359206" name="derby2377_1.diff" size="20494" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:54:38 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12359292" name="derby2377_2.diff" size="20591" author="scotsmatrix" created="Fri, 8 Jun 2007 18:03:50 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12359205" name="rrefattribcollation.html" size="4988" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:54:38 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12356944" name="rrefattribcollation.html" size="4855" author="scotsmatrix" created="Wed, 9 May 2007 00:12:43 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12359204" name="tdevdvlpcollation.html" size="4277" author="scotsmatrix" created="Thu, 7 Jun 2007 19:52:32 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12356946" name="tdevdvlpcollation.html" size="4265" author="scotsmatrix" created="Wed, 9 May 2007 00:12:43 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>12.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Thu, 22 Mar 2007 19:22:28 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>30407</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0mm7:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>37482</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>