<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:43:48 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-3149/DERBY-3149.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-3149] Add ant targets for building and running the package private tests against the classes directories</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3149</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Create ant targets in build.xml to compile and run the package private tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step will be to run the tests against the classes directories. Implementing a solution that runs against jars is not technically difficult, it just brings a host of decisions to be taken... Maybe even more important, does running against the jars add any value?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compile will be included in the &apos;all&apos; target to test the implementation. Feel free to post your concerns if you think building the package private tests should be a manual action only.&lt;br/&gt;
The tests will also be run as part of junit-all / junitreport.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12381134">DERBY-3149</key>
            <summary>Add ant targets for building and running the package private tests against the classes directories</summary>
                <type id="7" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/subtask_alternate.png">Sub-task</type>
                            <parent id="12365113">DERBY-2460</parent>
                                    <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="kristwaa">Kristian Waagan</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="kristwaa">Kristian Waagan</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 25 Oct 2007 10:02:16 +0100</created>
                <updated>Sun, 16 Mar 2008 14:41:06 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Wed, 9 Jan 2008 12:11:15 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>10.4.1.3</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.4.1.3</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Build tools</component>
                    <component>Test</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12537551" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 25 Oct 2007 10:12:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&apos;derby-3149-1a.diff&apos; implements the targets &apos;pptesting&apos; and &apos;junit-pptesting&apos;. The former compiles the package private test, the latter runs them against the classes directories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new directory has been added; classes.pptesting.&lt;br/&gt;
The is to avoid that package private test classes are included in any of the jars, and it might be beneficial for later extensions (i.e. package the tests in multiple separate testing jars, merge with the other jars etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that because I couldn&apos;t find any compile classpath for Java SE 5.0, I used the one for Java SE 6. This means that you must have specified the property jdk16 in your ant.properties file to compile the tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patch ready for review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12541346" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 9 Nov 2007 15:24:16 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;&apos;derby-3149-1b.diff&apos; refreshes the patch (there was a merge conflict in build.xml) and I decided not to run the junit-pptesting as part of junit-all/junitreport. The reason is that those targets are capable of running against jars or classes, whereas the package-private tests must be run against classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Two new targets; &apos;pptesting&apos; (compile) and &apos;junit-pptesting&apos; (run).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Compile target &apos;pptesting&apos; is included in target &apos;all&apos;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Compile target &apos;pptesting&apos; is not included in target &apos;testing&apos;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Class files are put into &apos;classes.pptesting&apos;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Currently there are 94 tests, and they take around 6 seconds to run on my machine.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12541353" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 9 Nov 2007 15:43:31 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed &apos;derby-3149-1b.diff&apos; to trunk with revision 593571.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not marked the issue as resolved yet, because there are a few things that must be cleaned-up, and it would also be nice if someone tested the targets (&apos;pptesting&apos;, &apos;junit-pptesting&apos;).&lt;br/&gt;
Targets are now dependent on Java SE 6, which they don&apos;t have to be. This is because I couldn&apos;t find a compile classpath for Java SE 5.0. Maybe this has already been introduced?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12541741" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 12 Nov 2007 11:09:51 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Dag H. Wanvik commented on derby-dev:&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;The patch seems to compile some files every time, even if already&lt;br/&gt;
compiled. Is that intentional?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No this was not intentional.&lt;br/&gt;
I had a look at it, and it turned out I had specified the wrong path for the srcdir attribute in the javac ant target. Ant expects the srcdir and destdir hierarchies to be the same. These properties are used to determine which files have to be compiled based on their timestamps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I decided to tell javac to compile all *java files in the tree, even though it could have been enough with just compiling the top-level file (PackagePrivateTestSuite). However, when this is done only the timestamp of that single file is checked, and the target would not recompile other changed files as long as PackagePrivateTestSuite remained unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have uploaded &apos;derby-3149-2a-conditional_compilation_fix.diff&apos; to fix these issues, and also chose to always compile with debug=true, added some comments and removed all references to &apos;derby.pptesting.src.dir&apos;.&lt;br/&gt;
Note that the compilation classpath still have to be fixed/replaced before the issue is closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dag, thanks for testing the patch &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12542205" author="dagw" created="Tue, 13 Nov 2007 19:36:11 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I looked at the patch, it works for me! Thanks, Kristian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small note; I would omit the echo in the task :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   java/testing/org/apache/derby/build.xml#pptesting-build&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;since silence is the default elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making &quot;debug&quot; always true makes sense here,&lt;br/&gt;
but is there a compelling reason to not use the prevailing pattern&lt;br/&gt;
of expanding $&lt;/p&gt;
{debug}
&lt;p&gt;? If sounds equally reasonable for all testing code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+1&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12542213" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 13 Nov 2007 19:58:42 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thank for looking at the second patch Dag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll remove the message stating that the build is complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not quite convinced about the debug-comment though. I don&apos;t see any reason not to compile with debug=true when it comes to test code, if something fails (expected or unexpected) in a test I would like to get as much information as possible. When I do a find-grep for debug=&quot;true&quot;, I get 44 matches. All except one are in the java/testing directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heartily agree with you on expanding $&lt;/p&gt;
{debug}
&lt;p&gt; in non-testing code, but I need more convincing to change it in the targets compiling the testing code &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12542372" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 14 Nov 2007 09:33:55 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;&apos;derby-3149-2b-conditional_compilation_fix.diff&apos; is equal to version 2a except that the echo-message is removed.&lt;br/&gt;
Committed to trunk with revision 594809.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m still awaiting the commit of another patch to replace the Java SE 6 compile classpath with that of Java SE 5.0.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12542404" author="dagw" created="Wed, 14 Nov 2007 10:38:07 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Ok, I was not aware that setting debug always true is a common pattern in the testing code.&lt;br/&gt;
If that&apos;s the case, I agree its good. I just seemed to remember once having to go through hoops&lt;br/&gt;
to get the debug variable set for some testing code which had not inherited the debug flag correctly&lt;br/&gt;
on the basis of sanity=sane, so I assumed it used the pattern common elsewhere in the code&lt;br/&gt;
(outside testing). Lesson: don&apos;t assume, check first &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12543844" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 20 Nov 2007 10:18:16 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Fixed invalid @link tag in the PackagePrivateTestSuite JavaDoc with revision 596598.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12543860" author="olav" created="Tue, 20 Nov 2007 11:09:17 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I have tested the two new ant targets and they worked fine for me. The only suggestion I have is that it could be a good idea to update the following wiki pages with information about the new ant targets and the new test suite:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyTopLevelJunitTests&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyTopLevelJunitTests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyJUnitTesting&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyJUnitTesting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12543890" author="olav" created="Tue, 20 Nov 2007 13:35:04 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;One question about the ant junit-pptesting target: why do we have to include junit.jar explicitly in the CLASSPATH in order for this target to find junit.jar while the ant pptesting target is able to locate the junit.jar in the tools/java directory? Couldn&apos;t also the junit-pptesting target use the tools/java/junit.jar file?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12544480" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 21 Nov 2007 14:33:43 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reminding me about updating the wiki, Olav!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have updated  &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyTopLevelJunitTests&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyTopLevelJunitTests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
I chose not to update &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyJUnitTesting&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://wiki.apache.org/db-derby/DerbyJUnitTesting&lt;/a&gt;, as I expect there will be several changes regarding running the package private tests in the future. They are also pretty new, so things might change quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12555851" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 4 Jan 2008 08:59:52 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Regarding why junit-pptesting isn&apos;t adding junit.jar automatically, I&apos;m not quite sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented a little bit, but it seems that with my ant version (1.6.5) adding the jar in the target isn&apos;t enough. Even if I add tools/java/junit.jar to the classpath for target junit-pptesting I&apos;m not able to run it without already having told ant where to find it (I currently have a junit.jar in ~/.ant/lib). I think ant needs junit.jar to &quot;initialize&quot; the junit task. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this area is a bit tricky with ant, and they also have a FAQ-entry for it: &lt;a href=&quot;http://ant.apache.org/faq.html#delegating-classloader-1.6&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://ant.apache.org/faq.html#delegating-classloader-1.6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Maybe ant 1.7 solves the problem for us, but we only require 1.6.3 (or higher) to build Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be nice if someone knowing ant well could help find the best way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12555876" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 4 Jan 2008 10:25:25 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Is there already a variable for Java SE 5.0 compile classpath in the build script(s)?&lt;br/&gt;
If not, are there any plans to introduce one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see there is a java15compile.classpath in the root build.xml, but as far as I can tell, it is only set when using the new &quot;autoprop&quot; feature and I haven&apos;t found any targets using it yet.&lt;br/&gt;
I see that many targets are using compile.classpath. This is currently set to java14compile.classpath, and changing it would probably be a bad idea.&lt;br/&gt;
Last, I see that we require J2SE 5.0 or higher in BUILDING.txt. Don&apos;t we need a variable for this &quot;default&quot; compile classpath?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case I&apos;m using J2SE 5.0 features in some tests, and I would like these tests to be built when JDK 1.5 is available. Currently they are only built if JDK 1.6 is available.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12556721" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 7 Jan 2008 21:47:38 +0000"  >
&lt;p&gt;I would like to make a small change to the build.xml file to use the jdk16 executable to build the pptesting target. It currently uses the default javac to compile against $&lt;/p&gt;
{java16compile.classpath}. This can cause problems when jdk 1.5 is the default javac and ${java16compile.classpath}
&lt;p&gt; is set to IBM 1.6&lt;br/&gt;
See attached patch pptesting_use_jdk16_executable_diff.txt&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12556746" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 7 Jan 2008 22:29:32 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Kathey,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not mind the change you have proposed, I just want to make clear that what the target really needs is to compile against the Java SE 5.0 libraries. There is no need for JDK 1.6, but as far as I know there is no java15compile.classpath, and compile.classpath is set to J2SE 1.4.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+1 to commit, unless someone knows how to get Java SE 5.0 libraries. If committed, I assume the target will revert back to Java SE 5.0 when the &quot;infrastructure&quot; is in place.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12556859" author="knutanders" created="Tue, 8 Jan 2008 09:50:33 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I think java15compile.classpath is initialized by the property setter added in &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3117&quot; title=&quot;Adjust master build script to require the Java 5 compiler to build Derby&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-3117&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-3117&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was enabled by default in revision 605224, so it should be safe to use it now.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12556880" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 8 Jan 2008 12:33:32 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;&apos;derby-3149-4a-compile_against_15_libraries.diff&apos; changes the build files to build the package-private test classes against Java SE 5.0 libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried pointing j15lib to Sun JDK 1.6 and it worked fine.&lt;br/&gt;
People using the IBM VMs might want to try the same before the patch is committed (build target is &apos;pptesting&apos;, run clobber/clean or delete classes.pptesting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ready for review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12556982" author="kmarsden" created="Tue, 8 Jan 2008 19:15:05 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Building with IBM 1.5 and dontAutosetProps=true in my  ant.properties I get:&lt;br/&gt;
compile:&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;mkdir&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Created dir: C:\svn2\trunk\classes.pptesting&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Compiling 8 source files to C:\svn2\trunk\classes.pptesting&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;javac&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Fatal Error: Unable to find package java.lang in classpath or bootclasspath&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BUILD FAILED&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume since I am not using the autoprops I need to set $&lt;/p&gt;
{java15compile.classpath}
&lt;p&gt; manually in my ant.properties. This should be spelled out in BUILDING.txt I think when  the change goes in.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12557046" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 8 Jan 2008 21:27:36 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Kathey,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I have understood, based on assumptions and bits of info here and there, the automagic property setter will not change j14lib and j15lib if they are specified in ant.properties.&lt;br/&gt;
However, it will still set java15compile.classpath based on j15lib.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess we should go back and check if the case with dontAutosetProps=true is documented properly, and if it is really needed at all? If it ignores already set variables, isn&apos;t that good enough?&lt;br/&gt;
Why would you need to explicitly disable it if it ignores already set variables?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12557050" author="kmarsden" created="Tue, 8 Jan 2008 21:56:51 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;As long as I set j15lib I don&apos;t need to set dontSetAutoProps and pptesting builds ok.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12557246" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 9 Jan 2008 12:11:14 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I take that as a go. You might want to try building with JAVA_HOME set to JDK 1.6, unless you have already done that.&lt;br/&gt;
Committed &apos;derby-3149-4a-compile_against_15_libraries.diff&apos; to trunk with revision 610358.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless there are problems, I don&apos;t plan to do more work under this issue.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12579193" author="kristwaa" created="Sun, 16 Mar 2008 14:41:06 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Closing the issue.&lt;br/&gt;
More work needs to be done to support running the package-private tests with jars, but that belongs under a separate issue.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12368351" name="derby-3149-1a.diff" size="8108" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 25 Oct 2007 10:12:35 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12368352" name="derby-3149-1a.stat" size="183" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 25 Oct 2007 10:12:35 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12369234" name="derby-3149-1b.diff" size="7926" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 9 Nov 2007 15:24:15 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369362" name="derby-3149-2a-conditional_compilation_fix.diff" size="3158" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 12 Nov 2007 11:09:51 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369489" name="derby-3149-2b-conditional_compilation_fix.diff" size="3170" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 14 Nov 2007 09:33:55 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12372707" name="derby-3149-4a-compile_against_15_libraries.diff" size="1327" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 8 Jan 2008 12:33:32 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12372665" name="pptesting_use_jdk16_executable_diff.txt" size="469" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 7 Jan 2008 21:47:37 +0000"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>7.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Tue, 13 Nov 2007 19:36:11 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>30742</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0z4n:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>39509</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>