<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:54:10 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-3176/DERBY-3176.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-3176] J2ME support for phoneME platform disabled in 10.3</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3176</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Derby 10.2 runs on the phoneME small device platform. However, on that platform Derby 10.3 fails to boot databases, complaining that Derby cannot find an appropriate implementation of DataValueFactory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For details on how to install and run the phoneME platform, please see &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.sun.com/wittyman/entry/javadb_on_sun_javame_cdc&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://blogs.sun.com/wittyman/entry/javadb_on_sun_javame_cdc&lt;/a&gt; These are great instructions but I needed to adjust them as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) I had to use 10.2 because 10.3 and the development mainline would not run on this platform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) I needed to to set LD_LIBRARY_PATH so that the vm could find the necessary shared libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the phoneME startup script which worked for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#! /bin/bash&lt;br/&gt;
#&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Run an ij script in the phoneME vm&lt;br/&gt;
#&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;$1 is the script to run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=$CDC_HOME/lib&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cd ~/demo/tearoffToPhone/data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$CDC_HOME/bin/cvm -Xbootclasspath/a:$JSR169_HOME/lib/jsr169.jar \&lt;br/&gt;
  -cp $DERBYJARS/derby.jar:$DERBYJARS/derbytools.jar \&lt;br/&gt;
  -Dij.dataSource=org.apache.derby.jdbc.EmbeddedSimpleDataSource \&lt;br/&gt;
  -Dij.dataSource.databaseName=sample  \&lt;br/&gt;
  -Dij.dataSource.createDatabase=create \&lt;br/&gt;
  org.apache.derby.tools.ij $1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12381918">DERBY-3176</key>
            <summary>J2ME support for phoneME platform disabled in 10.3</summary>
                <type id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/bug.png">Bug</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="rhillegas">Rick Hillegas</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="rhillegas">Rick Hillegas</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Tue, 6 Nov 2007 14:52:45 +0000</created>
                <updated>Tue, 30 Jun 2009 16:55:43 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Tue, 20 Nov 2007 14:45:12 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>10.3.1.4</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.3.2.1</fixVersion>
                                    <component>JDBC</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12540448" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 15:03:32 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching derby-3176-01-phoneME-aa.diff. This patch allows Derby to run on the phoneME platform. This adds custom logic to JVMInfo so that Derby recognizes this platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this patch, there are now at least 2 small device implementations which Derby supports. Additional implementations may require additional custom cases.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540449" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 15:05:02 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I am marking this as a regression because the phoneME platform was supported in 10.2 but is not supported in 10.3.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540460" author="johnemb" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 15:44:08 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;From derby-3176-01-phoneME-aa.diff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+		else if (javaSpec != null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &quot;Personal Basis Profile Specification&quot;.equals( javaSpec ) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shouldn&apos;t this rather say&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+		else if (javaSpec != null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &quot;Foundation Profile Specification&quot;.equals( javaSpec ) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least that&apos;s what my fairly recent, self-built phoneME cvm reports... (I need to test it against Derby, not sure I have all the required parts wired in yet). If the Personal Basis Profile works against Derby, perhaps we should check for both Strings?&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12540467" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 16:11:36 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the quick feedback, John. Please stand by while I consult the phoneME experts...&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540494" author="djd" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 17:29:49 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Could you specify what J2ME specification you are adding support for here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think we can add specific support for PhoneME as it is GPL licenced, thus any dependence on phoneme api&apos;s would mean Derby would have to be GPL, which is unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+			// Sun&apos;s phoneME platform is JDK 1.3 based&lt;br/&gt;
+			id = J2SE_13;&lt;br/&gt;
+			isJ2ME = true;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure what this is trying to say, J2ME and J2SE are exclusive, so how can a platform be J2SE1.3 and J2ME?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in code like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+ else if (javaSpec != null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &quot;Personal Basis Profile Specification&quot;.equals( javaSpec ) ) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the check for null is redundant.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540503" author="djd" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 17:52:26 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;+ // Sun&apos;s phoneME platform is JDK 1.3 based&lt;br/&gt;
+ id = J2SE_13;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also doesn&apos;t make sense because PhoneME claims it implements CDC, Foundation &amp;amp; Personal based upon 1.1.2, which I assume means JSRs 218,219,219 which are all subsetted from JDK 1.4.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540521" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 18:28:58 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the quick feedback, Dan. I don&apos;t think I understand the GPL issue. We are not including any GPL code so I don&apos;t see how the GPL is infecting us. Can you explain more about the legal issue you see here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the setting of &quot;id&quot; goes, I was just following the pattern set by the preceding block which handles the IBM WCTME case. I think your points are valid and I think they apply to the preceding WCTME block as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is another point that is puzzling me: The default java.specification.version is 1.3. That is the value which we force into javaVersion if we can&apos;t figure out what the version really is. Why is 1.3 the default value? Now that 1.3 has been deprecated (at least by Sun), I would think that 1.4 would be a better default.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540533" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 19:38:38 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching derby-3176-01-phoneME-ab.diff. This addresses John&apos;s comment about java.specification.name. This also addresses Dan&apos;s concerns about the code modelled on the IBM WCTME block. I have not corrected the WCTME block but am leaving that to someone who is an expert on that platform.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540539" author="djd" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 20:01:39 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I think some cleanup needs to happen here, I now see that the JDK_ID should be set to the base level of the specification and the J2ME flag set to true if it&apos;s a J2ME platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus J2ME/CDC/Foundation 1.1 should have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JDK_ID=J2SE_14&lt;br/&gt;
J2ME=true&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should be the case for the existing J2ME support (the so called WCTME code) and the Phone ME code (which probably should be a single code block).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that default java version should be 1.4, but  because Derby only supports JDK 1.4, not because a single vm vendor has deprecated their vm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For GPL, we just need to ensure that we depend on nothing that could be seen as part of the phone me api, e.g. a specific phoneme system property or a phoneme value of a system property. To be careful do we need this comment?&lt;br/&gt;
  // Sun&apos;s phoneME platform is JDK 1.4 based&lt;br/&gt;
It&apos;s really the case that CDC/Foundation 1.1 is jdk1.4 based.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540544" author="djd" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 20:12:30 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Note that it&apos;s also the purpose of the JVMInfo class to decide what Java specification Derby is going to run at, not to report what the actual real environment is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus I don&apos;t think this is valid (as in the phoneme case):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDC_FP_VERSION = javaVersion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derby runs at CDC/Foundation 1.1, if the phoneME code changes its version to 1.2 with no Derby changes it doesn&apos;t mean Derby is running in the CDC/Foundation 1.2 version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these lines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 		case J2SE_13: return J2ME ? &quot;J2ME - JDBC for CDC/FP 1.0&quot; : &quot;J2SE 1.3 - JDBC 2.1&quot;;&lt;br/&gt;
+		case J2ME_JDK: return &quot;J2ME - JDBC for CDC/FP &quot; + CDC_FP_VERSION;&lt;br/&gt;
 		case J2SE_14: return &quot;J2SE 1.4 - JDBC 3.0&quot;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;should be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 		case J2SE_14: return J2ME ? &quot;J2ME - JDBC for CDC/FP 1.1&quot;  : &quot;J2SE 1.4 - JDBC 3.0&quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12540563" author="johnemb" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 20:54:54 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Dan wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Note that it&apos;s also the purpose of the JVMInfo class to decide what Java specification Derby is going to run at, not to report what the actual real environment is. &quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a crucial piece of information which helps a lot for understanding why JVMInfo behaves the way it does. This was not clear to me from reading the Javadocs and other code comments.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540579" author="johnemb" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 21:31:47 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Since &quot;Foundation Profile Specification&quot; is a subset of &quot;Personal Basis Profile Specification&quot; which is a subset of &quot;Personal Profile Specification&quot;, I suspect we need to include support for the latter as well. Also, since the official name of the mobile platform has changed to &quot;Java ME&quot;, shouldn&apos;t we use that in the returned String instead of &quot;J2ME&quot;?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540789" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 16:46:10 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the continuing feeback, Dan and John. Attaching derby-3176-01-phoneME-ac.diff, which attempts to incorporate your recent observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that if I set JDK_ID to J2SE_14 for the small devices, then database boot failed because Derby tried to bring up a storage system which relied on the nio packages. Those packages are not present on the CDC 1.1.2 javadoc. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540809" author="djd" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 17:27:47 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The correct fix for the nio problem is for the modules.properties to include properties that indicate that module requires those classes. See derby.env.classes settings for existing modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that it would be clearer if the current scheme was kept leading to J2ME/CDC/Foundation 1.1 having:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JDK_ID=J2SE_14&lt;br/&gt;
J2ME=true &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540821" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 18:07:29 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the pointer to derby.env.classes. I will take a look at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am concerned that it is misleading to apply the label &quot;J2SE_14&quot; to a J2ME environment. As you note in your first comment on Nov 6, J2ME and J2SE are mutually exclusive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Can you explain why it is important that the j2me and jdk1.4 environments have the same JDK_ID?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) I think it would be less confusing if we renamed this label to something like &quot;J2ME_OR_J2SE_14&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12540840" author="djd" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 18:49:34 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Well the main reason is that is how the code is intended to work &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; I was mistaken in my earlier comment, the id indicates the base JDK level and the boolean indicates its the J2ME subset. Just adding a new id without modifying the rest of the code to handle this new type of id will not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are modules that will work in J2ME CDC/Foundation 1.1 and J2SE 1.4, they indicate this by specifying their jdk level as 4 in modules.properties. Any module that requires classes that are in J2SE 1.4 and not in the J2ME subset indicate this by explicitly stating they need that class: E.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;derby.module.jdbcJ4=org.apache.derby.jdbc.Driver30&lt;br/&gt;
derby.env.jdk.jdbcJ4=4&lt;br/&gt;
derby.env.classes.jdbcJ4=java.sql.Driver&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order of the id (jdk levels) is also significant, for any two modules that can run in a given environment, the one with the highest jdk id will be selected and currently the code works in that they are the base jdk levels. Inserting values in the middle for J2ME I think has the potential to lead to confusion, especially when migrating changes across branches. E.g. for the J2ME based upon Java 5, what would a new id be, since there is no gap between J2SE_142 and J2SE_15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to implement a different scheme, but it will require more than just adding an id in JVMInfo.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12540920" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 23:06:26 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the continued advice, Dan. I am attaching derby-3176-01-phoneME-ad.diff. This sets JDK_14 as you suggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that setting derby.env.classes.* was not sufficient to short-circuit the booting of the nio-based DataFileFactory. There is special logic for this factory in BaseMonitor itself. I have modified BaseMonitor accordingly. However, this logic is complicated and I would appreciate your advice about whether this is an acceptable solution. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12541340" author="rhillegas" created="Fri, 9 Nov 2007 15:10:03 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Dan: If you&apos;d like to think some more about this, let me know. Otherwise, I&apos;d like to check this in on Monday. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12541802" author="djd" created="Mon, 12 Nov 2007 15:19:17 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch looks good, I haven&apos;t tested it with any J2ME vm though.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12541808" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 12 Nov 2007 15:34:05 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Dan. I have committed derby-3176-01-phoneME-ad.diff at subversion revision 594184. I think that some diffs may now turn up in the WCTME test runs because the CDC/Foundation profile version, reported by sysinfo, has changed to 1.1. I would appreciate it if someone who tests on that platform could submit the new canons. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12542055" author="myrna" created="Tue, 13 Nov 2007 07:20:51 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I was fairly certain there are no masters that log the info from sysinfo in that much detail.&lt;br/&gt;
But, just to be on the safe side, I did run derbyall, and suitesall with ibm&apos;s weme6.1, but saw only failures related to the new errorStream test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only relevant junit test I could think of is tests.tools.SysinfoAPITest which doesn&apos;t run in the nightlies. I did verify that your change made no difference in the behavior of that test.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12542148" author="johnemb" created="Tue, 13 Nov 2007 13:52:08 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I wasn&apos;t able to try the latest patch before the commit, but when testing my phoneME binaries with the current trunk I get this error message when invoking IJ:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERROR (no SQLState): org.apache.derby.jdbc.EmbeddedDriver is not registered with the JDBC driver manager&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the same error whether I run with pre-built phoneME Advanced binaries and a self-built JSR-169 implementation, or self-built phoneME binaries including the self-built JSR-169 support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve also tried another approach by using a java class instead of IJ (attached: MobileSanityTest.java), but I get the same error. The exception originates in the EmbeddedSimpleDataSource.findDriver() method. With 10.2 it works fine, and with 10.3.1.4 I get the DataValueFactory error, as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sysinfo seems to be correct, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;java.specification.name: Foundation Profile Specification&lt;br/&gt;
java.specification.version: 1.1&lt;br/&gt;
--------- Derby Information --------&lt;br/&gt;
JRE - JDBC: J2ME - JDBC for CDC/FP 1.1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rick, are you able to use IJ/Derby successfully using phoneME and the current trunk?&lt;br/&gt;
If so, what could I be doing wrong?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12542456" author="johnemb" created="Wed, 14 Nov 2007 13:22:17 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The problem I was having was caused by not setting jsr169compile.classpath in the ant.properties file I was using. I hope this fix gets into 10.3 once we are confident there are no problems associated with the patch (it works for me at least).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12543669" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 19 Nov 2007 20:18:36 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Ported 594184 from trunk to 10.3 branch at subversion revision 596424.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12543911" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 20 Nov 2007 14:45:12 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Resolving this issue because it has been ported to 10.3.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12369423" name="MobileSanityTest.java" size="1126" author="johnemb" created="Tue, 13 Nov 2007 13:52:08 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369028" name="derby-3176-01-phoneME-aa.diff" size="1408" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 15:03:30 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369044" name="derby-3176-01-phoneME-ab.diff" size="1798" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Nov 2007 19:38:38 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369118" name="derby-3176-01-phoneME-ac.diff" size="3037" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 16:46:10 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12369146" name="derby-3176-01-phoneME-ad.diff" size="4502" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 7 Nov 2007 23:06:26 +0000"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>5.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310200" key="com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.customfieldtypes:multicheckboxes">
                        <customfieldname>Bug behavior facts</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                                <customfieldvalue key="10420"><![CDATA[Regression]]></customfieldvalue>
    
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Tue, 6 Nov 2007 15:44:08 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>23478</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310090" key="com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.customfieldtypes:multicheckboxes">
                        <customfieldname>Issue &amp; fix info</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                                <customfieldvalue key="10102"><![CDATA[Patch Available]]></customfieldvalue>
    
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0uxz:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>38831</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>