<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:34:32 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-3598/DERBY-3598.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-3598] Modify ReleaseNoteGenerator and ChangesGenerator to exclude issues that are fixed in earlier releases</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3598</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Since we cannot create a Jira filter which selects issues with a set fix versions and at the same time EXCLUDE issues with another set of fix versions, it would be nice if the *Generator programs could filter out those issues already fixed in previously released versions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12393266">DERBY-3598</key>
            <summary>Modify ReleaseNoteGenerator and ChangesGenerator to exclude issues that are fixed in earlier releases</summary>
                <type id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/improvement.png">Improvement</type>
                                            <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="myrna">Myrna van Lunteren</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="dyret">Dyre Tjeldvoll</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Sun, 6 Apr 2008 16:14:20 +0100</created>
                <updated>Fri, 21 Jan 2011 17:51:51 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Tue, 9 Jun 2009 17:31:07 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.4.1.3</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.5.2.0</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>10.6.1.0</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Build tools</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12586138" author="dyret" created="Sun, 6 Apr 2008 16:30:37 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Small hack that has worked well for the 10.4 release work. Admittedly not the most elegant solution, but it seems to work.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12586371" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 7 Apr 2008 13:58:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Dyre,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this patch will do what you want. However, I would be tempted to solve this problem a different way. Instead. of specifying the excluded versions on the command line, I would give releaseSummary.xml a new element for the excluded version list. That element can have a variable number of version sub-elements. The purpose of releaseSummary.xml is to hold a number of inputs which would otherwise make the command line unwieldy.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12594263" author="dyret" created="Mon, 5 May 2008 17:31:59 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve attached a new patch (v2) which implements Rick&apos;s suggestion. The patch is rather large because I included some additional changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Read the current version number from main.properties, so that doesn&apos;t have to be specified in releaseSummary.xml&lt;br/&gt;
2. Added excludeVersion as a tag in releaseSummary.xml (there can be any number of such tags with different values)&lt;br/&gt;
3. Refactored identical code from ReleaseNoteGenerator and ChangesGenerator into a common base class&lt;br/&gt;
4. Factored out the duplicated nested class JiraIssue to an ordinary class&lt;br/&gt;
5. Removed the nested class GeneratorState&lt;br/&gt;
6. Renamed &quot;pamphletFile&quot; to &quot;outputFile&quot; which I found more intuitive (possibly because English is not my native language) &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12595509" author="dyret" created="Fri, 9 May 2008 09:58:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m unassigning myself from this issue, as don&apos;t plan to do more work on it. Personally I think the latest patch warrants inclusion but I won&apos;t be pursuing that myself. Future release managers may want to take a look.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12688441" author="myrna" created="Mon, 23 Mar 2009 22:12:35 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Removing 10.5 from fix in. I&apos;ve looked into merging the patch with the current state of the source, specifically ReleaseNotesGenerator.java, but some changes - notably revision 683346 for &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3820&quot; title=&quot;Tasks for managing the 10.4.2 release&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-3820&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-3820&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - which make the patch invalid. I&apos;m giving up on it for the first 10.5 release candidate.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12713346" author="myrna" created="Wed, 27 May 2009 01:54:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve tried to consolidate the v2.diff patch with the changes made with revision 683346, but so far it&apos;s doing the same thing with, or without my changes.&lt;br/&gt;
I debugged this as far as finding that the excludeVersion item gets read, but the fixversions aren&apos;t available when the comparison is done (in JiraIssue.createJiraIssueList()).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d appreciate a hint if anyone has the time/inclination to look at this attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try out Dyre&apos;s original v2.diff patch, but that one no longer picks up any bugs at all - presumably this is why the changes of revision 683346 were made.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12713576" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 27 May 2009 14:59:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Myrna,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds like the logic at the end of the constructor for JiraIssue may not be properly parsing the list of fixed versions in the new xml format for JIRA issues.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12713763" author="myrna" created="Wed, 27 May 2009 22:44:37 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;How do we get an XML file?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more looking, I figure that in fact, my report - which was the same xml file I used to generate the 10.5.1.1 release notes - indeed did not have FixVersion tags at all.&lt;br/&gt;
We&apos;d need to go out to JIRA and get an xml for an individual bug, or, add the fixVersion to the list of fields included in the printout of the JIRA report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when I tried to get an XML out of JIRA, I got RSS instead.&lt;br/&gt;
I am almost certain that for 10.5.1.1 I just used firefox, brought up the filter, clicked on XML, then saved that as xhtml. But now, when I do that, I get RSS output rather than XML.&lt;br/&gt;
Is something wrong with JIRA?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12716097" author="myrna" created="Thu, 4 Jun 2009 00:01:29 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching a patch in which I went back to dyre&apos;s patch - undoing Rick&apos;s changes - except for one small adjustment in JiraIssue, where I added a little boolean skip check (before, issues got added whether they were fixed in previous releases or not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also attaching a sample RELEASE-NOTES.html which I obtained by copying the changed files to my 10.5 environment, running the same filters I used for 10.5.1.1 and saving the .xml files, then running ant genrelnotes in the tools/release directory. &lt;br/&gt;
Note that this did indeed skip some issues that had been fixed in earlier releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note also, that the JiraConnector class will get similar .xml files as saving the filter results, except that that includes other types of issues (duplicates, for instance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d like to commit these changes, unless someone thinks we should harrangue infrastructure about the lack of &apos;XML&apos; (again, it seems we only get &apos;rss&apos;) in JIRA. In that case I&apos;ll have to pass on doing further work on this.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12717355" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 8 Jun 2009 19:28:37 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for tackling this issue, Myrna. I am unable to comment on the code changes. The edits are largely stylistic and refactoring changes, which obscure the functional improvements. If there is a particular functional change or design decision which you&apos;d like to draw my attention to, please let me know. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12717528" author="myrna" created="Tue, 9 Jun 2009 02:55:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I committed patch v4.diff to trunk with revision 782867.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12717739" author="myrna" created="Tue, 9 Jun 2009 17:31:07 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I merged revision 782867 to 10.5 with modifications because of the removal of the changes file during the 10.5.1.1 release work. &lt;br/&gt;
I&apos;m resolving this issue, I&apos;m sure more tweaking can/will be done for 10.5.2.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12409105" name="DERBY-3598.v3.diff" size="144620" author="myrna" created="Wed, 27 May 2009 01:54:08 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12409826" name="DERBY-3598.v4.diff" size="142859" author="myrna" created="Thu, 4 Jun 2009 00:01:28 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12409827" name="RELEASE-NOTES.html" size="85601" author="myrna" created="Thu, 4 Jun 2009 00:01:29 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12379505" name="derby-3598.diff" size="12485" author="dyret" created="Sun, 6 Apr 2008 16:30:37 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12381432" name="derby-3598.v2.diff" size="139574" author="dyret" created="Mon, 5 May 2008 17:31:59 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12381433" name="derby-3598.v2.stat" size="515" author="dyret" created="Mon, 5 May 2008 17:31:59 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>6.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Mon, 7 Apr 2008 12:58:52 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>30918</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0lh3:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>37297</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>