<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:42:01 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-3731/DERBY-3731.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-3731] Improve calculation of refSize in ClassSize.java </title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3731</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;java/engine/org/apache/derby/iapi/services/cache/ClassSize.java has a static code block which calculates the size of a reference for the architecture.  This code could be improved by adding garbage collection before measuring memory, to give a consistent  reading.     Also there have been suggestions that we use os.arch or sun.arch.data.model to make the measurement more reliable, especially on 64bit machines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12398641">DERBY-3731</key>
            <summary>Improve calculation of refSize in ClassSize.java </summary>
                <type id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/bug.png">Bug</type>
                                            <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="kristwaa">Kristian Waagan</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="kmarsden">Kathey Marsden</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 19 Jun 2008 22:40:30 +0100</created>
                <updated>Mon, 4 May 2009 19:22:06 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Wed, 18 Mar 2009 16:43:29 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>10.5.1.1</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.4.2.1</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>10.5.1.1</fixVersion>
                                    <component>SQL</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12606569" author="kmarsden" created="Thu, 19 Jun 2008 22:45:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached is an initial patch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3731&quot; title=&quot;Improve calculation of refSize in ClassSize.java &quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-3731&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-3731&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;_diff.txt)  for this issue that adds the garbage collection before reading totalMemory()  and freeMemory(). This I would like to check into trunk and backport to 10.4 and 10.3.   Any additional changes for using os.arch can go in subsequent to this and probably should only go into the trunk as they might destabilize query plan selection. Running tests now.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12606927" author="knutanders" created="Fri, 20 Jun 2008 23:48:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Not directly relevant for this issue, but I&apos;m posting some&lt;br/&gt;
observations here so that they are not lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used DTrace to check how much memory that was allocated in JDK 6 on&lt;br/&gt;
OpenSolaris 2008.05 and compared the results to what ClassSize would&lt;br/&gt;
estimate. I found these differences (assuming that refSize was&lt;br/&gt;
correctly set to 4 on 32-bit VMs and 8 on 64-bit VMs):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) a better name for minObjectSize would be minArraySize, as it&lt;br/&gt;
attempts to estimate the fixed overhead for arrays&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) minObjectSize is set to 4*refSize (16 bytes on 32-bit, 32 bytes on&lt;br/&gt;
64-bit). The actual value is 3*refSize, but because of 8-byte word&lt;br/&gt;
boundaries the size of an empty array is refSize*3+4 == 4*refSize on&lt;br/&gt;
32-bit VMs (and the unused space can be exploited, so byte&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;0&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; and&lt;br/&gt;
byte&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;4&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; use the exact same number of bytes). On 64-bit VMs, 3*refSize&lt;br/&gt;
matches the word boundaries, so the correct value is 24 (and byte&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
uses 8 more bytes than byte&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;0&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) booleanSize should be 1, not 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) charSize and shortSize should be 2, not 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) estimateBaseFromCoefficients() uses minObjectSize as the minimum&lt;br/&gt;
object size, whereas it actually is objectOverhead*refSize.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12607246" author="knutanders" created="Mon, 23 Jun 2008 15:50:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Although sun.arch.data.model is not a required property, it is present in both Sun&apos;s and IBM&apos;s JVMs.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12611342" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 7 Jul 2008 21:51:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;ported fix to do gc before memory estimation to 10.4 and 10.3. Leaving the issue open for possible other improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12613257" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 14 Jul 2008 09:16:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Relying on Runtime.gc is not the best solution in my opinion and the call can even be disabled on the command line (at least for the Sun JVMs), causing it to have no effect. I&apos;ve seen this done in appserver environments to reduce impact of ill-behaved applications doing explicit GC.&lt;br/&gt;
The calculations are also sensitive to other kinds of activities in the JVM, so I&apos;d like to see further improvements to  these calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t know much about this code, but I see Knut Anders has already posted a list of potential issues.&lt;br/&gt;
It seems feasible to code an algorithm using the following mechanisms to determine the refSize (i.e. 32 or 64 bit system):&lt;br/&gt;
 1) Use system property &quot;sun.arch.data.model&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
 2) Use system property &quot;os.arch&quot; (requires some more logic/investigation)&lt;br/&gt;
 3) Fall back to the existing logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If nobody else feels the itch, I can make a change proposal for the refSize calculation, and if accepted, see how that affects our tests.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12614729" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 18 Jul 2008 14:50:49 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&apos;derby-3731-1a-refsize_from_properties.diff&apos; is a first shot at&lt;br/&gt;
determining the reference size by looking at system properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the following results from a run on my own machine when specifying&lt;br/&gt;
-d64 for the VM, using Sun JDK 1.6:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;ol&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;model: 8 (sun.arch.data.model)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;arch amd64: 8 (os.arch)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;sz: -26 (sz calculated by heuristic)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;REFERENCE SIZE: 4 (final value calculated by heuristic)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ol&gt;
		&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ol&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, in this case the estimation was off and the results are&lt;br/&gt;
reproducible.  However, when I tried the same with JDK 1.5, the&lt;br/&gt;
estimation was correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s a few things I haven&apos;t checked with the patch:&lt;br/&gt;
 a) Do we need some extra permissions?&lt;br/&gt;
    I was able to run with the default policy file.&lt;br/&gt;
 b) Do we need to document the permissions?&lt;br/&gt;
 c) Should the code be more defensive in making sure the data model code&lt;br/&gt;
    returns either 4 or 8?&lt;br/&gt;
 d) Is using &apos;os.arch&apos; worth the hassle?&lt;br/&gt;
 e) How many values are there for &apos;os.arch&apos;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments on this issue (and the patch) are welcome.&lt;br/&gt;
If people think it is a safe enough change, I would suggest to commit&lt;br/&gt;
the final version and see how it works out with the test runs. We have&lt;br/&gt;
individuals running off trunk, we have the tinderbox and the nighly&lt;br/&gt;
tests.&lt;br/&gt;
I also believe we have people developing on various platforms&lt;br/&gt;
(Solaris, Linux, Windows, Mac, maybe more).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12615971" author="knutanders" created="Wed, 23 Jul 2008 12:46:18 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think the patch looks good. We can always add more os.arch values later as we discover new ones. Since os.arch is defined by the spec, I think it is a good thing to check it if sun.arch.data.model is not found or not accessible. Later, if this change doesn&apos;t cause any problems, should we also mention these properties in the documentation and put them in the default policy installed by the network server?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small suggestion to make the code slightly simpler: The two loops in the checking of os.arch could be replaced by&lt;br/&gt;
  if (Arrays.asList(b32).contains(arch)) return 4;&lt;br/&gt;
and&lt;br/&gt;
  if (Arrays.asList(b64).contains(arch)) return 8;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe the code to get the value of a system property could be moved into a separate method to save some code duplication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should the THROWASSERT() be replaced with a DEBUG_PRINT() so that we don&apos;t prevent people from running the debug builds on platforms not used by the developers?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12615981" author="knutanders" created="Wed, 23 Jul 2008 13:03:55 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Logged &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-3794&quot; title=&quot;Improve estimates in iapi.services.cache.ClassSize&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-3794&quot;&gt;DERBY-3794&lt;/a&gt; for the problems with some other estimates in ClassSize.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12615999" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 23 Jul 2008 13:46:13 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for looking at the patch, Knut Anders.&lt;br/&gt;
Your comments are all valid, I&apos;ll incorporate them in the next revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I investigated a little more regarding the permissions. Seems Derby isn&apos;t allowed to read sun.arch.data.model with the current policy file, but it is allowed to read os.arch for some reason.&lt;br/&gt;
Adding code to print the current permissions shows that reading the property os.arch is indeed granted, but it is not in our default policy file. Since I don&apos;t know if this is specific for the Sun JVM or not, maybe we should document and add both permissions to the default policy file?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616009" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 23 Jul 2008 14:25:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch 1b addresses the suggestions from Knut Anders and it adds permissions for the two system properties to the default server policy file and the testing policy file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentation must be added later.&lt;br/&gt;
Patch ready for another review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616428" author="knutanders" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 11:02:19 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I downloaded the 1b patch and tried to run some of the tests that have had unstable query plans without noticing any problems (tried both on a 32-bit JVM and on a 64-bit JVM). The changes look good to me, +1 to commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, should we catch NumberFormatException when parsing the data model property so that we don&apos;t prevent users from booting Derby if there is a platform that sets this property to something that&apos;s not a number?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616439" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 11:35:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the testing, Knut Anders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, catching the NFE should be done. I have found out that the property can be set to &quot;unknown&quot;. I&apos;m also wondering if we should enforce 4 and 8 as return values to avoid any surprises on &quot;exotic VMs&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616443" author="knutanders" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 12:06:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The old code doesn&apos;t enforce 4 or 8, but it does make sure that refSize&lt;br/&gt;
is at least 4. Perhaps the new code should do the same? I don&apos;t think we&lt;br/&gt;
need to do anything more advanced than that. If the JVM tells us it&apos;s&lt;br/&gt;
using a 97-bit data model, why should we assume it&apos;s lying? &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12616453" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 13:02:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Revision 1c catches the NumberFormatException, moves/changes the debug print, removes the null-checking of &apos;dataModel&apos;, and changes the if-sentence so that the heuristic is run if the reference size found so far is less than 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect to commit patch 1c later today, unless more issues are found.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616787" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 25 Jul 2008 08:46:17 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed &apos;derby-3731-1c-refsize_from_properties.diff&apos; to trunk with revision 679690.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m leaving the issue open for a while to see if there are any side-effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must also be decided whether to keep the added privileges in the testing policy file and the default server policy file. If so, the privileges must be documented and maybe added to the template policy file as well.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12619692" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 4 Aug 2008 21:43:18 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Marking this as Fix Version 10.4.2 because it appears that the fix was ported to 10.4 with subversion revision 673892.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12625656" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 26 Aug 2008 08:36:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The 1c patch hasn&apos;t been ported to 10.4, nor 10.3.&lt;br/&gt;
I don&apos;t think the patch has caused any serious problems on trunk. With the patch, refSize is more likely to be correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following tasks remain:&lt;br/&gt;
 a) Document the required privileges.&lt;br/&gt;
 b) Add the privileges to the template policy file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The permissions to read the properties are not mandatory. If they are missing, the old heuristic will be used.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12671831" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 9 Feb 2009 12:40:37 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch 2a adds the permission to read the two system properties used to determine if the JVM is 32 or 64 bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding documentation, all I can find are the examples in the &quot;Derby Server and Administration Guide&quot;, under &quot;Running the Network Server under the security manager&quot;. I can&apos;t find any detailed explanation of each of the permissions granted. Have I missed them?&lt;br/&gt;
At the very least, I think the examples should be updated with the two new permissions. Note that they are optional, if the permissions aren&apos;t granted Derby will use the old heuristic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I don&apos;t hear anything, I&apos;ll try to update the two examples mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12671915" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 9 Feb 2009 16:43:07 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;You are right about the documentation missing the detailed explaination of each of the permissions needed.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-2792&quot; title=&quot;Document permissions needed by derbyclient.jar derbynet.jar and derbytools.jar in the documentation &quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-2792&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-2792&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has been filed to improve the documentation in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12672236" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 10 Feb 2009 11:18:33 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Kathey.&lt;br/&gt;
From your feedback I now see that the existing section in the development guide &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; should be updated, as the permissions referred to in this issue concern derby.jar (the engine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/devguide/cdevbabejgjd.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/devguide/cdevbabejgjd.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12677294" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 27 Feb 2009 09:13:27 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed patch 2a to trunk with revision 748448, and backported it to 10.4 with revision 748451.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12677326" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 27 Feb 2009 11:32:00 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch 3a adds the two properties to the examples for the basic security policy and the custom security policy. In addition, the properties are described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following pages have been changed:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/adminguide/adminguide-single.html#tadminnetservrun&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/adminguide/adminguide-single.html#tadminnetservrun&lt;/a&gt; (examples)&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;2&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/devguide/cdevbabejgjd.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/dev/devguide/cdevbabejgjd.html&lt;/a&gt; (description)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not sure if the right level of detail has been used.&lt;br/&gt;
Patch ready for review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12679227" author="chaase3" created="Thu, 5 Mar 2009 15:59:35 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The docs look just fine, Kristian. +1 to commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems odd to have a property that starts with &quot;sun&quot; &amp;#8211; seems like &quot;sun.arch.data.model&quot; is specific to the Sun JVM while &quot;os.arch&quot; applies to the others?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12679584" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 6 Mar 2009 13:11:56 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for looking at the patch, Kim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, several JVMs use the &quot;sun.arch.data.model&quot;, but I also think it is an undocumented feature of the Sun JVM. That&apos;s why it is optional, and Derby has other mechanisms to determine the &quot;bitness&quot;. The nice thing about the property is that it gives a definite answer if it is present (although it can be &quot;unknown&quot; I think). The logic for &quot;os.arch&quot; depends on knowing the architecture, and if an entry for a specific architecture hasn&apos;t been added, we can&apos;t conclude on the bitness. In these cases, the original heuristic will be used, which isn&apos;t working in all cases (i.e. Derby may use the wrong bitness, which affects size calculations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know at least some versions of the IBM JVM use &quot;sun.arch.data.model&quot;. The IBM JVMs also have their own version of this property: com.ibm.vm.bitmode&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681661" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 13 Mar 2009 09:50:00 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed patch 3a to trunk. This was only documentation updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before resolving/closing this issue, we have to agree on whether to backport the latest fixes to 10.4 and/or 10.3.&lt;br/&gt;
The original fix was ported to both 10.4 and 10.3, however there was a request to not backport any other fixes to those branches. Is this request still standing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have committed a change of the policy files to 10.4, but neither the fix nor the documentation changes have been backported. If we don&apos;t backport, I think I will revert that change on the 10.4 branch for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12682895" author="myrna" created="Wed, 18 Mar 2009 03:23:12 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The state of this issue is somewhat unclear for 10.4...But it seems clear for 10.5. If there&apos;s no objection, I&apos;d like to close it while I&apos;m working on the 10.5 release notes.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12683067" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 18 Mar 2009 16:43:29 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Pulled out a commit on the 10.4 branch with revision 755636, since the rest of the changes won&apos;t be backported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the first patches contributed by Kathey did go into both 10.4 and 10.3, but the later patches did not.&lt;br/&gt;
This means that the fix version is slightly inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t expect to do any more changes for this issue. Feel free to close the issue.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="10030">
                    <name>Reference</name>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is related to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12400814">DERBY-3794</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12384324" name="DERBY-3731_diff.txt" size="861" author="kmarsden" created="Thu, 19 Jun 2008 22:45:11 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12386394" name="derby-3731-1a-refsize_from_properties.diff" size="4786" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 18 Jul 2008 14:50:49 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12386717" name="derby-3731-1b-refsize_from_properties.diff" size="6406" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 23 Jul 2008 14:25:25 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12386718" name="derby-3731-1b-refsize_from_properties.stat" size="206" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 23 Jul 2008 14:25:25 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12386792" name="derby-3731-1c-refsize_from_properties.diff" size="6478" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 13:02:08 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12399814" name="derby-3731-2a_update_of_policy_template.diff" size="805" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 9 Feb 2009 12:40:37 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401103" name="derby-3731-3a-doc_changes.diff" size="2868" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 27 Feb 2009 11:32:00 +0000"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>7.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Fri, 20 Jun 2008 22:48:40 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>23812</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0xyf:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>39319</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>