<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:47:30 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-4267/DERBY-4267.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-4267] Investigate why Derby 10.5.1.1 is not available in the maven2 repositories</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-4267</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Only 10.4.2.0 and older are available in the maven 2 repositories.&lt;br/&gt;
May you please also provide the new version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-4220&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-4220&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12427675">DERBY-4267</key>
            <summary>Investigate why Derby 10.5.1.1 is not available in the maven2 repositories</summary>
                <type id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/task.png">Task</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="kristwaa">Kristian Waagan</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="dirk.schmitt">H.-Dirk Schmitt</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 11 Jun 2009 19:31:31 +0100</created>
                <updated>Mon, 17 Jun 2013 10:19:32 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 15:47:53 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>10.5.1.1</version>
                    <version>10.6.1.0</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.6.1.0</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Build tools</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>8</votes>
                                    <watches>11</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12718745" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 12 Jun 2009 08:11:16 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I have taken the liberty of adjusting this existing issue instead of creating a new one for tracking Maven2 related work. Details will follow.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12718747" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 12 Jun 2009 08:19:06 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The existing background material for this issue can be found in a dev@maven thread and a derby-dev@db thread:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nabble.com/Apache-Derby-artifacts-for-Maven-2-td23958179.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.nabble.com/Apache-Derby-artifacts-for-Maven-2-td23958179.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nabble.com/Maven-artifacts---time-to-move-to-Maven2--td23965723.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.nabble.com/Maven-artifacts---time-to-move-to-Maven2--td23965723.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;automatic conversion of Maven1 artifacts to Maven2 has been stopped&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;it seems the Maven community will convert the 10.5.1.1 Maven1 artifacts to Maven2 for us&lt;br/&gt;
   (we need to monitor / follow up on this, see &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the Derby community should start producing Maven2 artifacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; I think the M2 artifacts should appear here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12725225" author="kmarsden" created="Mon, 29 Jun 2009 16:47:10 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think the 10.5.1.1 release has shown up yet.  Probably more useful than getting the release posted  for us, would be getting instructions on how to do it  ourselves.  Kristian, since you started the conversation with the maven folks, could you follow up?  I am willing to do the mechanics if we get instructions.  It will be good practice for 10.5.2.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12727550" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 6 Jul 2009 15:32:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m attaching a preview patch for adding Maven 2 support. It isn&apos;t done, but it&apos;s a start.&lt;br/&gt;
Before I continue, I&apos;d appreciate some early comments on the questions below. Shortly I&apos;ll create a new Jira to track the addition of M2 support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Do the metadata values look reasonable?&lt;br/&gt;
   (i.e. mailing lists, descriptions, titles etc)&lt;br/&gt;
b) Do we want to keep the M1 stuff around?&lt;br/&gt;
c) Where do we put the new files?&lt;br/&gt;
   (the existing build files are in trunk/maven)&lt;br/&gt;
d) I have defined a dependency between derbynet and derby. Are there more dependencies we should add?&lt;br/&gt;
e) Do we want to publish derbyTesting?&lt;br/&gt;
f) When publishing a new release, should we update the SubVersion repos URL to be the branch instead of trunk?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known remaining tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Add artifacts for the localizations.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Update the documentation (build/snapshot process)&lt;br/&gt;
(- What have I forgotten?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To test the POMs, download Maven 2, extract the attached zip file to the Derby workspace,  go to &apos;maven2&apos;,  and type &apos;mvn install&apos;.&lt;br/&gt;
This should leave some files around in various &apos;target&apos;-directories and also files in your local Maven repository (~/.m2/repository on *nix).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other questions or comments, go ahead and post them so that we can address them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12736860" author="kmarsden" created="Wed, 29 Jul 2009 22:57:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Kristian, I would like to try to get maven2 updated for the 10.5.2 release. I would like to do whatever I can to help get the procedure finalized, but don&apos;t feel at all qualified to answer your questions or review the patch. I will download it and give it a try. Meanwhile here is my feeble input on some of your questions:&lt;br/&gt;
b) Do we want to keep the M1 stuff around?&lt;br/&gt;
If we can avoid it I think that would be good. I would say lets just publish maven2 for 10.5.2 and see if anyone complains.&lt;br/&gt;
c) Where do we put the new files?&lt;br/&gt;
Does /trunk/maven2 seem like a good place?&lt;br/&gt;
d) I have defined a dependency between derbynet and derby. Are there more dependencies we should add?&lt;br/&gt;
I am not sure what the dependency relationship means but there is definitely a relationship between the locale jars and derby.jar and derbyrun.jar and the other jars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;e) Do we want to publish derbyTesting?&lt;br/&gt;
I think it would be useful but don&apos;t know if it causes problems for those that download all the jars. Would there be a problem with footprint? I don&apos;t think we published it with maven1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;f) When publishing a new release, should we update the SubVersion repos URL to be the branch instead of trunk?&lt;br/&gt;
I think that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12737182" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 30 Jul 2009 18:13:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the comments, Kathey.&lt;br/&gt;
I&apos;m definitely not a Maven expert either, so join the club &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have attached patch 1a, which contains the following improvements;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;builds artifacts for the localizations and the derby.war servlet&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added a settings.xml (for deployment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some more comments;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt; d) I have defined a dependency between derbynet and derby. Are there more dependencies we should add?&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; I am not sure what the dependency relationship means but there is definitely a relationship between the locale jars and derby.jar and derbyrun.jar and the other jars.&lt;br/&gt;
We&apos;re currently not shipping derbyrun.jar, and I intend to skip that for the first iteration of the move from M1 to M2.&lt;br/&gt;
I think defined dependencies are mandatory, so they would have to be from the various locale jars to derby.jar? It guess it would be safe to skip this step for the time being as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; e) Do we want to publish derbyTesting?&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; I think it would be useful but don&apos;t know if it causes problems for those that download all the jars. Would there be a problem with footprint? I don&apos;t think we published it with maven1.&lt;br/&gt;
It is correct that we haven&apos;t published it with M1. Since nobody has requested it, maybe we can skip / postpone this too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;FYI, here are some very brief instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;apply patch&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;modify relevant properties and metadata&lt;br/&gt;
   (for a release, I guess this is derby.version and specifying the correct path for the source code in svn, i.e replacing trunk with branches/10.5)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;build: mvn install&lt;br/&gt;
   (this installs the artifacts in your local cache/repos)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;deploy to Apache repository:&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;first edit settings.xml&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;mvn deploy&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;sign files etc as specified in the release process document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think as soon as the files are up on the server, they can&apos;t (or aren&apos;t allowed to) be deleted.&lt;br/&gt;
A first step of the testing is to ensure the jar files are included and that the content of the poms look good, which can be done in the local cache and/or the source files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the file permissions has been set to 644, which was stated in a readme I found on the Apache server. The reasoning behind this is perhaps that a different person than the one who deployed the artifacts shouldn&apos;t be allowed to change them.&lt;br/&gt;
For directories, the permissions should be 775.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12737606" author="dagw" created="Fri, 31 Jul 2009 18:26:22 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for doing this, Kristian!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am new to maven, but I read this helpful intro: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.javaworld.com/javaworld/jw-05-2006/jw-0529-maven.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.javaworld.com/javaworld/jw-05-2006/jw-0529-maven.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
and tried to understand our *.pom&apos;s, I also downloaded Maven and tried an &quot;mvn install&quot; (NOTE: this had to be done from inside the maven2 directory, I found), and then it seemed to work: I found the Derby artifacts in my ~/.m2 directory structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspecting the poms, I only found one item which seemed to contradict the intro: The module poms lack &amp;lt;version&amp;gt;, which the intro claims is mandatory, but I did not see any error message, so I suppose it is inherited from the top pom, then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question: We specifiy &amp;lt;filtering&amp;gt; to true; is that needed for Derby? It seems potentially dangerous in that&lt;br/&gt;
strings inside jars could be replaced?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me the dependencies from locale jars to derby.jar should be included.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12737628" author="dagw" created="Fri, 31 Jul 2009 19:13:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hmm, I see several of these warnings when running &quot;mvn install&quot;, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Using platform encoding (ISO8859-1 actually) to copy filtered resources, i.e. build is platform dependent!&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; JAR will be empty - no content was marked for inclusion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;something seems wrong. The installed jars seem mostly empty, too. I must be doing something wrong..&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12737916" author="kristwaa" created="Sat, 1 Aug 2009 18:20:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Dag, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for looking at the patch. Regarding your questions:&lt;br/&gt;
a) mvn install: Yes, this must be run from withing the maven2 directory.&lt;br/&gt;
b) Correct, the version is inherited and set in the parent pom (&quot;derby-project&quot;).&lt;br/&gt;
c) filtering: You are correct it should be turned off, if we continue to use this plugin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the warning messages you see, I think they are coming from jar:jar (jar-default), as I have set the encoding for the resources plugin.&lt;br/&gt;
However, I have obviously failed to instruct maven to add the Derby jar files. We&apos;re not following Maven conventions, because we&apos;re not using it to build the artifacts. All that is needed is to tell Maven to use the pre-built jar as the artifact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way I have managed to do this so far, is to use the antrun plugin with the ant copy task. It is more of a hack though, since I&apos;m overwriting the artifact built by Maven itself (which is the almost empty jar you&apos;re mentioning, containing some metadata).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless anybody gives me a hint, or provides a better solution, I&apos;m going to add the other dependencies and switch to using the antrun task.&lt;br/&gt;
Also, is there a way to make Maven2 not execute or not try to package anything for the jar:jar goal?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Help from an experienced Maven2 user would be nice at this point! Help from not-so-experienced users is also welcome &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747400" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 25 Aug 2009 14:29:55 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch 2a uses an ant task to simply copy the Derby jar files. The jar generated by maven is overwritten. This isn&apos;t exactly elegant...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that you will get three warnings per artifact being built, and these are to be expected with the current patch. They can be ignored because these phases aren&apos;t needed, but I haven&apos;t found out how to suppress them:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Using platform encoding (UTF-8 actually) to copy filtered resources, i.e. build is platform dependent!&lt;br/&gt;
...&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Using platform encoding (UTF-8 actually) to copy filtered resources, i.e. build is platform dependent!&lt;br/&gt;
...&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; JAR will be empty - no content was marked for inclusion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test, apply patch, make sure you have built the correct Derby jar files (insane by default), then go to maven2/ and type mvn &amp;lt;action&amp;gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;package  : builds the artifacts into the various target directories&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;install : builds the artifacts and installs into the local repository (~/.m2/repository/org/apache/derby/&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;artifactId&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; on *nix)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you grep for &quot;RELEASE_DATA&quot; in the files in the maven2 dir, you can see the values you have to change to generate release artifacts.&lt;br/&gt;
Currently there are two occurences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the Derby version&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;user credentials to deploy to Apache maven2 site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still feel I don&apos;t have enough confidence in this patch, mostly based on the fact that I don&apos;t know Maven very well, so I&apos;d like at least one other person to sanity check the patch (metadata, generated artifacts, deploy site, etc.).&lt;br/&gt;
Patch 2a ready for review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747407" author="henryju" created="Tue, 25 Aug 2009 14:41:36 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;To suppress&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Using platform encoding (UTF-8 actually) to copy filtered resources, i.e. build is platform dependent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you simply have to define the encoding of your files and set the following property in the POM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;code panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;codeContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;code-xml&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;code-tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;properties&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;code-tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;code-comment&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- All plugins should use this value. See http://docs.codehaus.org/display/MAVENUSER/POM+Element+for+Source+File+Encoding --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;code-tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;project.build.sourceEncoding&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;UTF-8&lt;span class=&quot;code-tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/project.build.sourceEncoding&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;code-tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/properties&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is a standardized Maven properties that all plugins will use except compiler plugin that is not yet released.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747623" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 25 Aug 2009 21:25:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Kristian and Julien. I have applied Kristian&apos;s 2a patch and added the UTF-8 property to pom.xml as Julien recommended. The following 2 commands produced no errors and reported that they ran successfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mvn package&lt;br/&gt;
mvn install&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This produced a tree of objects under ~/.m2/repository/org/apache/derby. Those artifacts are jars, poms, and maven-metadata-local.xml files. The jars appear to be the correct size. The poms and metadata files appear to be non-vacuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far so good I think. Comparing this to the old maven1 process, I now expect that I am supposed to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) sign or generate checksums for these artifacts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) upload the artifacts, signatures, and checksums somewhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a script or set of instructions for doing (1) and (2)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
-Rick&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747626" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 25 Aug 2009 21:28:44 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This is the structure of the artifact tree (without signatures and checksums). Looks good to me, but what do I know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;./derby&lt;br/&gt;
./derby/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derby/10.5.3.0/derby-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derby/10.5.3.0/derby-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derby/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derby-project&lt;br/&gt;
./derby-project/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derby-project/10.5.3.0/derby-project-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derby-project/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyclient&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyclient/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyclient/10.5.3.0/derbyclient-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyclient/10.5.3.0/derbyclient-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyclient/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_cs&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_cs/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_cs/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_cs-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_cs/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_cs-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_cs/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_de_DE&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_de_DE/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_de_DE/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_de_DE-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_de_DE/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_de_DE-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_de_DE/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_es&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_es/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_es/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_es-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_es/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_es-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_es/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_fr&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_fr/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_fr/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_fr-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_fr/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_fr-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_fr/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_hu&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_hu/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_hu/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_hu-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_hu/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_hu-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_hu/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_it&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_it/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_it/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_it-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_it/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_it-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_it/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ja_JP&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ja_JP/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ja_JP/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_ja_JP-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ja_JP/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_ja_JP-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ja_JP/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ko_KR&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ko_KR/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ko_KR/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_ko_KR-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ko_KR/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_ko_KR-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ko_KR/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pl&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pl/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pl/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_pl-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pl/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_pl-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pl/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pt_BR&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pt_BR/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pt_BR/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_pt_BR-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pt_BR/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_pt_BR-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_pt_BR/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ru&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ru/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ru/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_ru-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ru/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_ru-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_ru/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_CN&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_CN/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_CN/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_zh_CN-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_CN/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_zh_CN-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_CN/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_TW&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_TW/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_TW/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_zh_TW-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_TW/10.5.3.0/derbyLocale_zh_TW-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbyLocale_zh_TW/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbynet&lt;br/&gt;
./derbynet/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbynet/10.5.3.0/derbynet-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbynet/10.5.3.0/derbynet-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbynet/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbytools&lt;br/&gt;
./derbytools/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbytools/10.5.3.0/derbytools-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbytools/10.5.3.0/derbytools-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbytools/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;br/&gt;
./derbywar&lt;br/&gt;
./derbywar/10.5.3.0&lt;br/&gt;
./derbywar/10.5.3.0/derbywar-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
./derbywar/10.5.3.0/derbywar-10.5.3.0.war&lt;br/&gt;
./derbywar/maven-metadata-local.xml&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747804" author="henryju" created="Wed, 26 Aug 2009 08:06:21 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;1) To sign the artifacts you can use the GPG plugin.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-gpg-plugin/usage.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-gpg-plugin/usage.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I think this is what is used for all Maven plugins themself.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/maven/pom/trunk/asf/pom.xml?view=co&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/maven/pom/trunk/asf/pom.xml?view=co&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) To have your Maven artifacts ultimately on central there are several possibilities. Either host yourself a server where you can put your files. Maven is able to deploy using ssh, ftp, webdav, ... For example for JWebUnit project we are deploying next to Sourceforge site files via ssh (&lt;a href=&quot;http://jwebunit.sourceforge.net/m2-repo/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://jwebunit.sourceforge.net/m2-repo/&lt;/a&gt;). Then you can ask Maven team to replicate your repo on the central.&lt;br/&gt;
The other option is to ask for a repo on Nexus OpenSource (&lt;a href=&quot;http://nexus.sonatype.org/oss-repository-hosting.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://nexus.sonatype.org/oss-repository-hosting.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747965" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 26 Aug 2009 15:59:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks to  Julien Henry for the information on Maven, and thanks to Rick for testing the patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uploaded patch 2b with the following changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added the UTF-8 encoding property.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added checksum property (these are generated on install or deployment time)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added use of the GPG plugin to sign the artifacts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added a README.txt file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To deploy the artifacts locally, execute &apos;mvn clean install&apos;.&lt;br/&gt;
To deploy the artifacts remotely, on the Apache repository, execute &apos;mvn clean deploy&apos;.&lt;br/&gt;
NOTE: Once deployed, I&apos;m not sure if there is a way to make sure the artifacts are removed from all existing mirrors. So be careful &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; And of course, you have to specify your own credentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deploy repository is set to &apos;scp://people.apache.org/www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository&apos;. Does this look correct?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patch 2b ready for testing and further review!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12747988" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 26 Aug 2009 16:41:36 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Kristian. I will test-drive the 2b patch. In the meantime, I have asked the pmc for advice about where to deploy the artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12748096" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 26 Aug 2009 20:21:16 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for the 2b patch, Kristian. By liberally using -D arguments, I was able to test-drive the clean and install targets without having to edit the scripts themselves. This is what I did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  mvn &quot;-Dgpg.passphrase=$PASSPHRASE&quot; -Dderby.version=$RELEASE clean install&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That filled a local directory tree with artifacts, signatures, and checksums. I verified one of the signatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I am seeing the checksummed signature problem to which the README alluded. For instance, the directory &quot;.m2/repository/org/apache/derby/derby/10.5.3.0&quot; contains the following files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;derby-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.asc&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.asc.md5&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.asc.sha1&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.md5&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.sha1&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.asc&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.asc.md5&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.asc.sha1&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.md5&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.sha1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected to see only&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;derby-10.5.3.0.jar&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.asc&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.md5&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.jar.sha1&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.asc&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.md5&lt;br/&gt;
derby-10.5.3.0.pom.sha1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any idea what I&apos;m doing wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
-Rick&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12748307" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 27 Aug 2009 10:04:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Rick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think you are doing anything wrong. I can&apos;t see ane &quot;*.asc.asc&quot; files in your list.&lt;br/&gt;
Here&apos;s what I think is happening:&lt;br/&gt;
 1) You generate the &quot;real artifacts&quot;, typically a jar file and a POM.&lt;br/&gt;
 2) These are then signed, resulting in two more files (*.asc)&lt;br/&gt;
      You now have four files.&lt;br/&gt;
 3) In the install/deployment step, you are checksumming all the artifacts you have.&lt;br/&gt;
      The jar, the jar signature, the POM, and the POM signature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, with two &quot;real artifacts&quot;, you end up with twelve files as you described. This because there are two checksums for each artifact (md5 and sha1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checking the following random projects that sign their artifacts, this seems to be the way it is done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/maven/maven-ant-tasks/2.0.6/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/maven/maven-ant-tasks/2.0.6/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/httpcomponents/httpclient/4.0/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/httpcomponents/httpclient/4.0/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/shindig/shindig-common/1.0-incubating/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/shindig/shindig-common/1.0-incubating/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/tomcat/jasper/6.0.20/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/tomcat/jasper/6.0.20/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, these projects don&apos;t (no checksumming of the signatures):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/hadoop/avro/1.0.0/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/hadoop/avro/1.0.0/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/lucene/lucene-core/2.4.1/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/lucene/lucene-core/2.4.1/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Personally I would prefer to keep the scripts simple instead of writing more code/XML to delete some of the checksum files.&lt;br/&gt;
Or is there a way to specify files to exclude? &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12748438" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 27 Aug 2009 17:48:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that explanation, Kristian. I think the checksummed signatures are goofy but harmless. I agree that we can leave this alone since other projects tolerate the goofiness too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I noticed that all of the projects you cited, except for shindig, have artifacts at the deployment location you&apos;re proposing: people.apache.org/www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository&apos;. I don&apos;t understand the relationship between that deployment location and the repositories you just cited, which are all on repo1.maven.org, not people.apache.org. For the record, my apache credentials work on people.apache.org but not on repo1.maven.org.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12748448" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 27 Aug 2009 18:07:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;A little more information. I see that the repo1.maven.org repository has directories for the following projects, which are not present in the proposed repository:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;apache&lt;br/&gt;
derby&lt;br/&gt;
felix&lt;br/&gt;
jdo&lt;br/&gt;
openejb&lt;br/&gt;
rat&lt;br/&gt;
shindig&lt;br/&gt;
wink&lt;br/&gt;
xmlrpc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe someone pushes artifacts from people.apache.org to repo1.maven.org and the extra projects have some other backdoor arrangement with the maven repository.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12749427" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 31 Aug 2009 09:46:34 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Rick, does this help?&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://apache.org/dev/repository-faq.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://apache.org/dev/repository-faq.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12753702" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 10 Sep 2009 17:52:54 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Kristian. The FAQ you pointed me at suggests that we should deploy to /www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository/ rather than /www/people.apache.org/repo/m1-ibiblio-rsync-repository/ The patch looks like it is going to deploy to the second location--at least that&apos;s the setting of maven.repo.apache.directory in maven/project.properties.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12753723" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 10 Sep 2009 18:39:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Scotch that last comment. I was poking around in the old maven directory, not in the new maven2 directory. In the maven2 directory, the patch uses the m2 repository in pom.xml.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12753778" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 10 Sep 2009 20:28:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I tried using the patch to deploy to the maven2 repository, but was stymied by authentication problems. I issued the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mvn &quot;-Dgpg.passphrase=$PASSPHRASE&quot; -Dderby.version=10.5.3.0 -Dmy_login=rhillegas -Dmy_password=$APACHE_PASSWORD clean deploy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also tried leaving off the login and password properties and, instead, hardwiring them into settings.xml. In both cases, deployment failed with the following exception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Error deploying artifact: Authentication failed: Cannot connect. Reason: Algorithm negotiation fail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my bad experience with deployment under maven1, I abandoned this approach. Instead, I tar&apos;d up the artifacts, copied the tarball to people.apache.org and untar&apos;d the contents under /www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository/org/apache I changed the group ownership of the artifacts to apcvs and gave the group write access to the top level directory.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12754114" author="rhillegas" created="Fri, 11 Sep 2009 13:47:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The following conversation happened on irc after I hand-deployed the artifacts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; hi&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; where&apos;s the largest derby chan?&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; I think I&apos;ve seen a larger one once&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; there&apos;s an error in the lastest pom&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ahfeel (n=ahfeel@84.207.19.58) has left #derby&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;ERROR&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; FATAL ERROR&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Invalid uri &apos;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/derby-project/$
{derby.version}/derby-project-${derby.version}
&lt;p&gt;.pom&apos;: escaped absolute path not valid&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/derby/10.5.3.0/derby-10.5.3.0.pom&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/derby/10.5.3.0/derby-10.5.3.0.pom&lt;/a&gt; contains &amp;lt;version&amp;gt;$&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.version}
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/version&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; it would be cool if anyone could fix this&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;kahatlen&amp;gt; oxi: You may want to add that comment here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-4267&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-4267&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; kahatlen: thanks&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; is there a maven repository with a fixed pom?&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;kahatlen&amp;gt; oxi: I don&apos;t think so. from the latest comment on the jira issue, it seems like there were problems getting 10.5.3.0 deployed.&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;kahatlen&amp;gt; I haven&apos;t followed the discussion closely, but I think someone is getting really close to making it work now  &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;oxi&amp;gt; kahatlen: I see.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have looked inside the poms and they all have this error. That is, instances of derby.version were not replaced with 10.5.3.0. It seems that if you set derby.version on the java command line when you run mvn, the version is picked up when the file names of the artifacts are created but the version number is not substituted into the contents of the poms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think that I should fix these poms by hand. I think we should improve the patch to handle this and then redeploy. I don&apos;t know if there is any harm in leaving the broken poms in the repository until we can post fixed poms.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12756099" author="cregganna" created="Wed, 16 Sep 2009 17:30:41 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This is holding up our development as we we require the Fetch and Offset query clauses introduced in 10.5. We are currently stalled on maven build and deploy as the 10.5.3.0 pom has this issue. If you could deploy a temporary fix (by putting in the versions) it would allow us to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12756422" author="mccalli" created="Thu, 17 Sep 2009 09:40:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Another voice in favour of a resolution to this one please - similar reasons to the previous comment, there&apos;s 10.5.x functionality we&apos;re looking for but we can&apos;t get access to it via our standard build process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks in advance for the help.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12756660" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 17 Sep 2009 18:55:51 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Tony and Ian,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are experiencing technical difficulties. Kristian, who prepared the patch, had a serious accident and is out of the office for a while. In the meantime, my machine is up on the blocks and won&apos;t be repaired for a couple more days. I&apos;ll take a look at hand-repairing the poms when my machine comes back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Rick&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12756710" author="mccalli" created="Thu, 17 Sep 2009 20:12:47 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the update, and please pass on the very best to Kristian. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ian&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12757075" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 18 Sep 2009 10:23:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m still on sick leave, and is restricted to typing with one arm only, but I thought I should share a few of my thoughts on this issue.&lt;br/&gt;
After searching the Maven forums, it appears I have led us into one of Maven&apos;s quagmires. What I instinctively tried to do (I haven&apos;t used Maven before), isn&apos;t yet supported and it seems fixing it isn&apos;t straight forward. The limitation/problem has been known for quite some time.&lt;br/&gt;
Due to a reboot I managed to loose my references to the relevant JIRAs, but I can dig them up again later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest we take action to fix the problem our users are experiencing by inserting the version in the POM &quot;manually&quot;. Since there are quite a few POMs to edit, maybe inserting a placeholder would be good? Then people can use whichever tool they&apos;re familiar with on their platform to replace the placeholder with an actual version (on *nix this could be perl or sed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the already deployed POMs shouldn&apos;t be edited, because that would mess up the checksums.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12757283" author="moizd" created="Fri, 18 Sep 2009 18:39:41 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Kristian,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you a speedy recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t understand your suggestion for a placeholder for the version. Maven will require a specific version number in the version tag. The poms will need to be redeployed with the specific version number for  maven to sucessfully process the poms.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12757399" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 18 Sep 2009 21:36:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi m,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The placeholder will only exist in Derby&apos;s source code repository.&lt;br/&gt;
When a release is cut, it will be replaced by a specific Derby version number - for instance 10.5.3.0.&lt;br/&gt;
The only purpose of the placeholder is to make it easier for the person generating the Maven artifacts to do a search and replace to insert the correct version number.&lt;br/&gt;
There are quite a few POMs, and doing it manually is a bit tedious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process above is generally what I would have expected the Maven install plugin to do, using the $&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.version}
&lt;p&gt; variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a placeholder, maybe we could just the current version number, but it may incur a little extra work as we generate release candidates (that we don&apos;t actually release).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the feedback,&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12758411" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 22 Sep 2009 21:16:30 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I have hand-replaced the $&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.version}
&lt;p&gt; variables with the literal &quot;10.5.3.0&quot; and regenerated the signed artifacts. I tar&apos;d them up and copied them to people.apache.org/www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository. Hopefully, they will be rsync&apos;d to the maven2 repository and be usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried a couple more experiments in using maven to deploy the artifacts but I could not get either scp or scpexe to work. For the record, I can ssh and sftp to people.apache.org without giving my password because I have setup a public key for my machine on people.apache.org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the top level pom (maven2/pom.xml) gives the deployment url as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &amp;lt;url&amp;gt;scp://people.apache.org/www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository&amp;lt;/url&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;deployment fails with this message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;ERROR&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; BUILD ERROR&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Error deploying artifact: Authentication failed: Cannot connect. Reason: Algorithm negotiation fail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I change scp to scpexe so that the deployment url is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &amp;lt;url&amp;gt;scpexe://people.apache.org/www/people.apache.org/repo/m2-ibiblio-rsync-repository&amp;lt;/url&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;deployment fails with this message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;ERROR&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; BUILD ERROR&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Error deploying artifact: Error executing command for transfer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exit code 255 - Permission denied (publickey,keyboard-interactive).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case it matters, I am running on a Macbook Pro laptop running Mac OS X version 10.5.7.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12758419" author="mccalli" created="Tue, 22 Sep 2009 21:31:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for that - will try the new artefact tomorrow and report back.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12758883" author="cregganna" created="Wed, 23 Sep 2009 22:05:30 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Likewise, thanks for your work on this - it is very much appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be trying your fix ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And - my very best wishes for a speedy recovery, Kristian.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12760901" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 30 Sep 2009 13:57:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Linking to derby-4390.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12760969" author="moizd" created="Wed, 30 Sep 2009 19:05:10 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Any updates on this? I am blocked from upgrading to 10.5.x. If it is further delayed it may no longer be an option since it will be too close to our release freeze date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12760979" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 30 Sep 2009 19:27:29 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I have created a new Maven distribution called 10.5.3.0_1 and staged it at &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.apache.org/~rhillegas/repository/org/apache/derby/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://people.apache.org/~rhillegas/repository/org/apache/derby/&lt;/a&gt; This distribution contains the Derby 10.5.3.0 jars plus better poms. Please test-drive this distribution. If users think that it&apos;s a good Maven packaging of Derby artifacts, then I can copy it to the ibiblio directory tree so that it will be sync&apos;d to the Maven 2 repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an explanation of why I generated a new Maven version id, please see the commentary on derby-4390.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
-Rick&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762247" author="cregganna" created="Mon, 5 Oct 2009 17:37:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Rick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for doing that - I have finally gotten round to testing with your patched distro (10.5.3.0_1). Maven downloaded correctly from the artifacts in your repo and I have run my unit tests to completion with no problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only issue I got was on a checksum:&lt;br/&gt;
Downloading: &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.apache.org/~rhillegas/repository/org/apache/derby/derby-project/10.5.3.0_1/derby-project-10.5.3.0_1.pom&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://people.apache.org/~rhillegas/repository/org/apache/derby/derby-project/10.5.3.0_1/derby-project-10.5.3.0_1.pom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
6K downloaded  (derby-project-10.5.3.0_1.pom)&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;WARNING&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; *** CHECKSUM FAILED - Error retrieving checksum file for org/apache/derby/derby-project/10.5.3.0_1/derby-project-10.5.3.0_1.pom - IGNORING&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am lookng fwd to your getting this into the offiicial repo as it means we can start to use the FETCH/OFFSET clauses on queries introduced in 10.5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thx,&lt;br/&gt;
    Tony Jewell&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762299" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 5 Oct 2009 19:33:41 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for test-driving the 10.5.3.0_1 distribution, Tony. I can see that there is no checksum for the pom in the derby-project/10.5.3.0_1 directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Kristian,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the artifact directories which I have inspected (except for derby-project/10.5.3.0_1) have the following files associated with the pom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pomfile&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc.md5&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc.sha1&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.md5&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.sha1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The derby-project/10.5.3.0_1 has these files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pomfile&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc.md5&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc.sha1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, derby-project/10.5.3.0 is missing these files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pomfile.md5&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.sha1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any theories about why the checksums weren&apos;t generated for these files?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
-Rick&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12762611" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 14:07:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached patch 2c, which contains the following changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;removed the now unused derby.version property.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;replaced &apos;$
{derby.version}
&lt;p&gt;&apos; with &apos;ALPHA_VERSION&apos; as a placeholder. Replace with the correct Derby version before installing / deploying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added workaround for a bug in the install plugin by requiring a newer version of the plugin. This should be removed at a later time. The bug caused the checksums for derby-project-VERSION.pom to not be generated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Hi Rick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see above, investigation showed that the reported checksum problem above was caused by a bug in maven-install-plugin. Please give patch 2c a try, or simply add the few lines required from the top level POM to you own environment (in case you want to change as little as possible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you have test-driven patch 2c, I plan to commit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One issue remains (I brought it up before):&lt;br/&gt;
Do we want to point to the 10.5 branch, or to trunk in the source code repository property for 10.5?&lt;br/&gt;
Currently it points at trunk, but that can easily be changed in the top level POM (see the scm tag).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762616" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 14:23:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Note that the new version of the install plugin doesn&apos;t generate checksums for the signature files.&lt;br/&gt;
That is, the following files are no longer generated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pomfile.asc.md5&lt;br/&gt;
pomfile.asc.sha1 &lt;br/&gt;
jarfile.asc.md5&lt;br/&gt;
jarfile.asc.sha1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an earlier discussion on this issue we saw projects both with and without these files. Maybe the differences were caused by the various projects using different versions of the install plugin?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762620" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 14:48:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the quick response, Kristian. I will test-drive the 2c patch today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;One issue remains (I brought it up before):&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;Do we want to point to the 10.5 branch, or to trunk in the source code repository property for 10.5?&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt;Currently it points at trunk, but that can easily be changed in the top level POM (see the scm tag).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just my $.02 since I don&apos;t know anything about how this pom is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that what you have right now is at least internally consistent. The source code url agrees with the &amp;lt;derby.version&amp;gt; element lower down, whose contents are &quot;trunk-alpha&quot;. If you change one, then I think that you should change the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the information in this pom is project-wide. That is, it&apos;s true regardless of the version of Derby you&apos;re seeking. For that reason too I think that the &amp;lt;scm&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;derby.version&amp;gt; elements look good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762629" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 15:09:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Rick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your last reply confuses me slightly.&lt;br/&gt;
The derby.version element has to go away, because it doesn&apos;t work as intended. I don&apos;t think we should hold our breath for a solution to the problem either.&lt;br/&gt;
The person generating the artifacts will have to insert the correct Derby version number in each and every POM. This can be done easier by using for instance Perl or sed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll rephrase my question.&lt;br/&gt;
When we deploy artifacts for the next 10.4 update release, should the scm tag point to the 10.4 branch?&lt;br/&gt;
When we deploy artifacts for the next 10.5 update release, should the scm tag point to the 10.5 branch?&lt;br/&gt;
Since we currently doesn&apos;t deploy artifacts for trunk (which would have had to be snapshots I suppose?), the scm tag of our official Maven artifacts will never point to trunk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an example on how the scm tag can be used, let&apos;s take NetBeans and a project where you have specified the Derby Maven artifacts as dependencies. In that case, you can choose to check out or browse the source code of Derby by right clicking the icon representing the Maven artifact. Do we want to point our users to the trunk (Derby development version), or to the branch of the official Derby version being used?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In any case, this is a rather minor matter &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762665" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 16:31:34 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Kristian,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see that this could be a religious discussion. From your description of how this element is used, the following answers make sense to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) &amp;lt;scm&amp;gt; could be a pointer to the head of the development codeline. That is what the element describes now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) &amp;lt;scm&amp;gt; could point at the svn tag for the release, the exact source code used to build the artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pointing &amp;lt;scm&amp;gt; at the head of the release branch falls somewhere between (1) and (2) and seems to me to be harder to motivate than the options above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any event, I&apos;m fine with your current solution, (1). And I know nothing. So take my advice at your peril!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12762681" author="bmargulies" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 17:47:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;There are broken artifacts at central. They have variable references in places where they are not supposed to  be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Downloading: &lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/derby-project/$&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/apache/derby/derby-project/$&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.version}/derby-project-${derby.version}
&lt;p&gt;.pom&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Unable to find resource &apos;org.apache.derby:derby-project:pom:$&lt;/p&gt;
{derby.version}
&lt;p&gt;&apos; in repository central (&lt;a href=&quot;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;ERROR&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; BUILD ERROR&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;INFO&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Error building POM (may not be this project&apos;s POM).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763002" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 7 Oct 2009 12:10:48 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hello Benson,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a known issue, and we&apos;re in the process of deploying a new set of Derby 10.5.3.0 artifacts.&lt;br/&gt;
The latest test artifacts we are testing are at &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.apache.org/~rhillegas/repository/org/apache/derby/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://people.apache.org/~rhillegas/repository/org/apache/derby/&lt;/a&gt; , but I think they will be regenerated once more due to some missing checksums (caused by a bug in maven-install-plugin).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I have understood, the next deployed artifacts will have version 10.5.3.0_1, because it is not possible (either technically or by policy, I don&apos;t know) to refresh an already deployed set of artifacts.&lt;br/&gt;
I&apos;m not the one deploying the artifacts, but I&apos;m under the impression it is being worked on actively. We&apos;ve had several other users reporting the error already, so we&apos;re aware it is causing people trouble.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Regards,&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763012" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 7 Oct 2009 12:27:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Rick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no strong opinions on the &amp;lt;scm&amp;gt; issue. I&apos;m fine with the path of least resistance: keeping the &amp;lt;scm&amp;gt; tag unchanged.&lt;br/&gt;
Regarding your item (2), I&apos;m not sure what the scm-tag offers with respect to specifying a revision. That&apos;s another data point suggesting we keep things as they are and get the new artifacts published sooner than later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have done this already, but if you use the newest patch, it would be good if you could keep the previous artifacts tested by Tony Jewell (see comment somewhere above) and compare the next rev with those.&lt;br/&gt;
I think you should observe the following differences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the derby.version property has been deleted from the top-level POM.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the workaround for the install plugin bug has been added in the top-level POM&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;all checksums of the signature files (*.asc) are gone&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;derby-project-VERSION.pom should have checksums (sha1 and md5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Good luck! I think we&apos;re getting close to the finishing line now &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763014" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 7 Oct 2009 12:37:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Linked to the issue for documenting the process of producing Maven 2 artifacts for Derby.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763104" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 7 Oct 2009 17:00:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The 2c patch looks good to me. I have re-generated the 10.5.3.0_1 distribution. This new version has checksums for the pom in derby-project. I compared the new rev to the previous rev, and the differences were what I expected except for this: the gpg signatures (the .asc) files changed. I have confirmed that if I use gpg to generate two signatures on the same file, then the signatures are different. I did not know that the signature computation was time-sensitive. I have verified the signatures so I&apos;m prepared to believe that what I am seeing is expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have deployed the new 10.5.3.0_1 distribution to the ibiblio rsync area. It should be picked up and copied to the Maven 2 repository. Hopefully, this distribution will be useful to Maven users and will not raise any warnings.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763128" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 7 Oct 2009 18:01:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi RIck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked the files at the ibiblio rsync area, and it looks good. You may want to give the group write access, but since this is a &quot;write-once media&quot; (with respect to the artifacts being distributed/rsync&apos;ed) it&apos;s not a big deal.&lt;br/&gt;
The files haven&apos;t been distributed to the central repos yet, but I&apos;ll give it another try tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763247" author="knutanders" created="Wed, 7 Oct 2009 21:28:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;As to the signatures that change, they contain a timestamp, which can be seen when you verify them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$ gpg --verify db-derby-10.5.3.0-lib.tar.gz.asc&lt;br/&gt;
gpg: Signature made Mon Aug 10 22:21:25 2009 CEST using DSA key ID 98E21827&lt;br/&gt;
gpg: Good signature from &quot;Rick Hillegas &amp;lt;rhillegas@apache.org&amp;gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763459" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 8 Oct 2009 12:59:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I was able to pull down some of the Derby 10.5.3.0_1 artifacts and use them in a trivial test project, so they seem to be live.&lt;br/&gt;
Let&apos;s wait and see what our users have to report &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&apos;t be surprised if we have to improve the POMs later, but let us deal with issues as they are reported.&lt;br/&gt;
Hopefully people will choose the 10.5.3.0_1 version over 10.5.3.0, since the latter artifacts are invalid.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12763477" author="mccalli" created="Thu, 8 Oct 2009 13:39:14 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Just built a project using 10.5.3.0_1 - all working fine here.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12770440" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 27 Oct 2009 09:54:15 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed patch 2c to trunk with revision 830107.&lt;br/&gt;
I need to follow up with documentation, and also some specifics on how to deploy the artifacts.&lt;br/&gt;
As far as a understand at this point, you can deploy using public key authentication with maven. It is is preferable if you log into the system using ssh afterwards to fix the file group permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll give the deploy a try and provide another patch (mostly documentation, I assume).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12860941" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 26 Apr 2010 15:47:53 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Resolving issue, any problems arising during the 10.6 release will be dealt with under a separate issue.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13685274" author="knutanders" created="Mon, 17 Jun 2013 10:19:32 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;bulk update&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; Close all resolved issues that haven&apos;t been updated for more than one year.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="12310010">
                    <name>Incorporates</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="incorporates">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12437495">DERBY-4400</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                        </issuelinktype>
                            <issuelinktype id="10030">
                    <name>Reference</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="relates to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12436886">DERBY-4390</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
            <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12463023">DERBY-4632</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is related to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12421902">DERBY-4140</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
            <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12425094">DERBY-4220</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12415037" name="derby-4267-1a-maven2.diff" size="58954" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 30 Jul 2009 18:13:58 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12415038" name="derby-4267-1a-maven2.stat" size="1193" author="kristwaa" created="Thu, 30 Jul 2009 18:13:58 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12417612" name="derby-4267-2a-using_ant_task.diff" size="57360" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 25 Aug 2009 14:29:55 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12417613" name="derby-4267-2a-using_ant_task.stat" size="1193" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 25 Aug 2009 14:29:55 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12417740" name="derby-4267-2b-using_ant_task.diff" size="62467" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 26 Aug 2009 15:59:09 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12417741" name="derby-4267-2b-using_ant_task.stat" size="1218" author="kristwaa" created="Wed, 26 Aug 2009 15:59:09 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12421423" name="derby-4267-2c-using_ant_task.diff" size="62787" author="kristwaa" created="Tue, 6 Oct 2009 14:07:58 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12412614" name="maven2.zip" size="7056" author="kristwaa" created="Mon, 6 Jul 2009 15:32:12 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>8.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Fri, 12 Jun 2009 07:11:16 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>31181</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0qrr:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>38155</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>