<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:09:44 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-516/DERBY-516.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-516] Need to incorporate client backward/forward  compatibility testing into testing procedures.</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-516</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Need to incorporate client backward/forward  compatibility testing into testing procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New versions of the Derby network server should work with old versions of the network client.  New versions of the Derby network client should work with old versions of the server.  Currently that means that the 10.1 client should be tested on the trunk.     The 10.2 client definitely needs to be tested with the 10.1  server before release, but it would be good to start testing snapshots of 10.2 client on the 10.1 branch earlier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bug fixes may mean that the canons differ for different versions.&lt;br/&gt;
The test harness I think is set up to allow different masters for different versions.  It at least has that functionality for the DerbyNet framework&lt;br/&gt;
 and it could  be expanded to cover DerbyNetClient.  The way it works is that&lt;br/&gt;
the harness checks for a masters in the following order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;functionTests/master/&amp;lt;framework&amp;gt;/ver&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;  &lt;br/&gt;
functionTests/master/&amp;lt;framework&amp;gt;/&lt;br/&gt;
functionTests/master/&lt;/p&gt;




</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12313524">DERBY-516</key>
            <summary>Need to incorporate client backward/forward  compatibility testing into testing procedures.</summary>
                <type id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/improvement.png">Improvement</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="-1">Unassigned</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="kmarsden">Kathey Marsden</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Fri, 19 Aug 2005 00:18:53 +0100</created>
                <updated>Mon, 7 Feb 2011 21:58:47 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Mon, 7 Feb 2011 21:58:47 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>10.1.1.0</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.2.1.6</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Test</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12331604" author="rhillegas" created="Sat, 8 Oct 2005 01:42:43 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This patch introduces a small JUnit test for checking the compatibility of clients&lt;br/&gt;
and servers running at different rev levels and on different vms. This&lt;br/&gt;
test initially simply checks that the expected datatypes can be&lt;br/&gt;
declared, inserted, selected, and coerced and that they appear as the&lt;br/&gt;
correct JDBC types in DatabaseMetaData and ResultSetMetaData.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that when committed, this patch will require developers to&lt;br/&gt;
download JUnit so that Derby will build correctly and derbyall will&lt;br/&gt;
run cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full suite runs correctly on my cygwin platform, testing all&lt;br/&gt;
combinations of clients, servers, and vms. Derbyall also runs cleanly,&lt;br/&gt;
including a single configuration of the compatibility test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief description of this patch follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M      tools\ant\properties\compilepath.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\README.htm&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\README.html&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\testScript.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\Pinger.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\JDBCDriverTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\harness\Sed.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\master\CompatibilityTest.out&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\suites\jdbcapi.runall&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\DerbyJUnitTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      BUILDING.txt&lt;br/&gt;
M      build.xml&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) BUILDING.txt has been amended to tell developers that they must&lt;br/&gt;
   download JUnit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) java/testing/README.htm has been amended to point at a web page&lt;br/&gt;
   which describes how to run the compatibility tests. It points at&lt;br/&gt;
   java/testing/org/apache/derbyTesting/functionTests/tests/compatibility/README.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) DerbyJUnitTest.java is a superclass for Derby JUnit tests. It is a&lt;br/&gt;
   useful place to put extra assertion machinery not included in the&lt;br/&gt;
   base JUnit classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) JDBCDriverTest.java is the actual JUnit test which checks expected&lt;br/&gt;
   datatypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) testScript.xml is an ant harness for running all combinations of&lt;br/&gt;
   the compatibility test. Hopefully, we can discard this harness when&lt;br/&gt;
   a more robust JUnit harness is checked into Derby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) CompatibilityTest.java is a thin wrapper which runs one&lt;br/&gt;
   configuration (embedded) of JDBCDriverTest inside the derbyall&lt;br/&gt;
   suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7) Sed.java has been amended to filter out JUnit diagnostics which&lt;br/&gt;
   derbyall interprets as noise. This filtering allows derbyall canons&lt;br/&gt;
   to be empty for JUnit tests.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12331953" author="davidvc" created="Thu, 13 Oct 2005 14:11:13 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi, Rick.  I&apos;ve been looking through your patch, a lot of good work here!  Here are my comments/thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, has anybody besides you run a full compatibility test?  I&apos;ll do it if I need to, but if somebody&apos;s already done it then I don&apos;t have to...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;testScript.xml&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The standard I have seen in this project is properties in ant are not capitalized.  Any particular reason you diverged from this?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The &quot;embeddedTrunk&quot; target: I don&apos;t understand what it means to run a JDBC compatibility test for an embedded engine (which you call an &quot;embedded server&quot; which is confusing).  The client and the engine are both in derby.jar &amp;#8211; how can they be incompatible?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I also noticed that the &quot;jdbcTrunk&quot; target is defined but never used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;JDBCDriverTest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I very much like your structure and form in this test.  You make solid use of subroutines that are coherent and simple, and it makes the code very readable.  That said, you&apos;re a little sparse on comments and have a tendency to use obtuse class names like &quot;TD&quot; and &quot;T_CN&quot; and it would be nice if you provided a little more running commentary for the new reader.  Comments on your member variables would be great too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Way cool comment on COERCIONS, it took me a few mos to realize I had to read top-to-bottom instead of left-to-right (what on earth does&lt;br/&gt;
  &quot;BBCBCDDDRILLNRSTTVV mean?!&quot;)  It also helps to read this in a tool that doesn&apos;t do auto-word-wrap.  You &lt;b&gt;might&lt;/b&gt; want to explain this for the poor person first reading this...  Also explain what this table is for (e.g. yes it can be coerced, not it can&apos;t).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Why do you use &quot;Y&quot; and &quot;_&quot; instead of &quot;T&quot; and &quot;F&quot;  or &quot;Y&quot; or &quot;N&quot; for your defines of true and false?.  It seems a bit obtuse...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a reason you check for a boolean return value of your &quot;minion&quot; subroutines rather than have each subroutine throw an exception if it fails?  Why are you catching the exceptions in the subroutines and then printing out a message?  This way you get no stack trace and the tester has to search for the string in the code.  I would much prefer you just throw the exceptions up to the top level and let JUnit report a failure with the message text to help you figure out what&apos;s going on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I must be missing something, you are only defining valid types for 10.0.  Is this because you haven&apos;t added the boolean type yet?  What will change when you add it?  Given the current situation, is there any possibility of getting an incompatibility in your tests, given that all versions support the same types?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;As usual, I like your choice of words, like &quot;firstTastyColumn&quot; and &quot;constructorMinion&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;



</comment>
                            <comment id="12332013" author="rhillegas" created="Fri, 14 Oct 2005 02:08:10 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, David, for reviewing this patch so thoroughly. Based on your review, I will make several changes and resubmit this patch. Here are my responses to your comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) No-one else has run this test yet. Thank you for voluteering to do so. If the instructions aren&apos;t clear enough, please let me know and I will fix them too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Concerning the casing of my symbols: I have tried to follow the same casing policy which I use in Java code. I uppercase constants and I camelcase variables, arguments, and methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) It&apos;s true that the embedded case isn&apos;t properly speaking part of a compatibility test. It&apos;s there as a sanity check to track discrepancies between the embedded and network clients. I will add a comment to explain this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) It&apos;s also true that jdbcTrunk is never invoked. It&apos;s a top level entry point which I included to help me debug the test and harness. It lets you run just one combination. I left it in because I expect it will be very useful as developers add additional cases to this test. I will beef up its comment to explain this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) In general, I will beef up my comments. I apologize for the cryptic names TD and T_CN. Originally these classes had more useful names: TypeDescriptor and TypeCoercion. I had to truncate these names in order to fit the ALL_TYPES and COERCIONS tables onto a readable screen. I think I&apos;ve given up on this fond dream for ALL_TYPES and so there&apos;s no reason that TD couldn&apos;t be replaced with its more useful name. I will make this change. I would like to leave T_CN short for the reason I just gave, but I will add a comment to its class header explaining this oddity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Similarly, I opted for Y and _ instead of Y and N because it made the table more readable. I experimented with a couple combinations and this is the one which made the salient Y really leap out at the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7) I agree with your objection to my exception handling in the startup code. I will fix this as you suggest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8) You are right, I am only testing the 10.0 datatypes in this first cut of the test. As I re-enable and add new datatypes, I will incorporate them in this test too. When I add a new datatype, it will be tested in all combinations in which the server lets a customer declare that datatype. In the current state of the test, there is only one minor (canonized) incompatibility, which I have logged as bug 584: the DRDA clients conflate NUMERIC and DECIMAL. No doubt, as we add more test cases, we will find more important existing incompatibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also address the issue which you and Dan discussed in email: I will amend the scripts and BUILDING.txt to tell the developer that she should be able to download any version of JUnit at level 3.8.1 or higher.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12332476" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 19 Oct 2005 23:40:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi, David: I have amended this patch as you suggested. I ran derbyall and one test failed: dataSourcePermissions_net. When I ran derbynetmats by itself, this test passed so I&apos;m writing it off as some kind of environmental hiccup. The files in this amended submission are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M      tools\ant\properties\compilepath.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\build\org\apache\derbyBuild\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\README.htm&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\README.html&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\testScript.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\Pinger.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\JDBCDriverTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest_app.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\copyfiles.ant&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\harness\Sed.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\master\CompatibilityTest.out&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\suites\derbynetmats.runall&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\DerbyJUnitTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\client\org\apache\derby\client\net\Reply.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      BUILDING.txt&lt;br/&gt;
M      build.xml&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12332533" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 20 Oct 2005 09:24:48 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This patch was scraped from a subversion client at revision 325900.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12355680" author="rhillegas" created="Tue, 25 Oct 2005 12:01:15 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Incorporate Andrew&apos;s suggestion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Amended BUILDING.txt and README.htm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Moved junit jar symbol from compilepath to extrapath and adjusted build files accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Eliminated vacuous Reply.java&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents of new patch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M      tools\ant\properties\extrapath.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\build\org\apache\derbyBuild\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\README.htm&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\README.html&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\testScript.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\Pinger.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\JDBCDriverTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest_app.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\copyfiles.ant&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\harness\Sed.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\master\CompatibilityTest.out&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\suites\derbynetmats.runall&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\DerbyJUnitTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      BUILDING.txt&lt;br/&gt;
M      build.xml&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12355902" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 26 Oct 2005 09:26:48 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Fix .../tests/compatibility/build.xml to use 1.3 compile classpath rather than generic compile classpath. This should fix the compile problem which Andrew was seeing. That should be the only diff between this and the last rev of the patch. Patch contents are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M      tools\ant\properties\extrapath.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\build\org\apache\derbyBuild\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\README.htm&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\README.html&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\testScript.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\Pinger.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\JDBCDriverTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\compatibility\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\CompatibilityTest_app.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\tests\jdbcapi\copyfiles.ant&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\harness\Sed.java&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\master\CompatibilityTest.out&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\suites\derbynetmats.runall&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
A      java\testing\org\apache\derbyTesting\functionTests\util\DerbyJUnitTest.java&lt;br/&gt;
M      java\testing\build.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M      BUILDING.txt&lt;br/&gt;
M      build.xml&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12356550" author="davidvc" created="Wed, 2 Nov 2005 09:15:17 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed, revision 330139, with a minor fix at revision 330147&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12360014" author="kmarsden" created="Sat, 10 Dec 2005 10:45:43 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I am reopening this bug as Rick plans to bring this test into derbyall by checking in the 10.1.1.0  release so that  compatiblity testing with the first official derby release can be included in  derbyall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Rick !&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12446994" author="rhillegas" created="Fri, 3 Nov 2006 15:49:44 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Unassigning myself since I haven&apos;t worked on this issue for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12991641" author="myrna" created="Mon, 7 Feb 2011 21:58:47 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve promoted the former subtask &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-1048&quot; title=&quot;Include run of junitTests/CompatibilitySuite, or converted compatibility test suite with 10.1/trunk combination into suites.All&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-1048&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-1048&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to an improvement, and am closing this issue again.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="10030">
                    <name>Reference</name>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is related to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12329428">DERBY-1048</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12320306" name="bug516.diff" size="87649" author="rhillegas" created="Wed, 26 Oct 2005 09:26:48 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>1.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Sat, 8 Oct 2005 00:42:43 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>29588</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hy0j7z:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>36932</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>