<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 03:27:54 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/DERBY-6061/DERBY-6061.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[DERBY-6061] Upgrade language is inconsistent</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061</link>
                <project id="10594" key="DERBY">Derby</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Developer&apos;s Guide we describe two kinds of upgrade, &quot;full&quot; and &quot;soft&quot;. I think we used to use the terms &quot;hard&quot; and &quot;soft&quot;, and &quot;hard&quot; was changed to &quot;full&quot; to provide a more accurate description of what happens. There are still a few leftover occurrences of &quot;hard&quot; in the docs here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &quot;soft&quot; doesn&apos;t provide much indication of what happens in that kind of upgrade. Would &quot;partial&quot; be more correct? If not, is there a good alternative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can go through the docs and fix the language based on whatever you all think makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12630173">DERBY-6061</key>
            <summary>Upgrade language is inconsistent</summary>
                <type id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/bug.png">Bug</type>
                                            <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="chaase3">Kim Haase</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="chaase3">Kim Haase</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 16:39:41 +0000</created>
                <updated>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 14:17:05 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 19:15:04 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>10.9.1.0</version>
                                    <fixVersion>10.10.1.1</fixVersion>
                                    <component>Documentation</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>8</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="13567810" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 31 Jan 2013 17:04:10 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for logging this issue, Kim. I agree that the terms &quot;hard&quot; and &quot;soft&quot; aren&apos;t very meaningful. However, I don&apos;t think that the terms &quot;full&quot; and &quot;partial&quot; are much better. I think that the defining behavior of the two types of upgrades can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;o Hard - In this kind of upgrade, on-disk data in the database is changed. This kind of upgrade is NOT reversible. That is, once you hard-upgrade the database, then you can no longer run older versions of the Derby engine jar file against the database. By &quot;older&quot;, I mean a version with a lower major.minor identifier. In addition, hard upgrade typically enables new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;o Soft - In this kind of upgrade, on-disk data in the database is NOT changed. If your application misbehaves after this upgrade, you can reverse the upgrade by running your old version of the Derby engine jar. Typically, soft upgrade does not enable new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need a pair of terms which capture these distinctions. Maybe &quot;feature&quot; vs. &quot;bugfix&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
-Rick&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13567816" author="rhillegas" created="Thu, 31 Jan 2013 17:10:00 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Another approach to the problem might be to eliminate all mention of soft upgrade. The user can&apos;t request or disable soft upgrade. It happens automatically. Maybe we should just talk about upgrade. It&apos;s the hard, irreversible, data-changing behavior when you specify &quot;upgrade=true&quot; after installing the jar files of a release whose major.minor id is greater than your old release. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13569439" author="dagw" created="Sat, 2 Feb 2013 05:54:06 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Another approach to the problem might be to eliminate all mention of soft upgrade&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be good for most users&apos; perspectives. Devs need two terms to cover the &quot;soft&quot; behavior as well, and dev terms easily slip into end user docs.&lt;br/&gt;
Bu also users need sometimes be aware that a new version of the database jar &lt;b&gt;could&lt;/b&gt; cause issues even without upgrade=true, and also sometimes new features/fixes &lt;b&gt;are&lt;/b&gt; available without hard upgrade, so it would be good to have an easy way to characterize that situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about code (or jar) upgrade vs. database upgrade ?&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13570660" author="chaase3" created="Mon, 4 Feb 2013 21:49:58 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m afraid I&apos;m getting cold feet on this. We&apos;ve been making the full upgrade/soft upgrade distinction since 10.2. References to soft upgrade seem to be limited to the Developer&apos;s Guide and Reference Manual upgrade topics; references to full upgrade are scattered here and there. I think it might confuse people more if we change the terminology than if we don&apos;t. It&apos;s probably more important to be consistent in our language than to try to find exactly correct terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get rid of references to &quot;hard upgrade&quot;. I find only two references to hard upgrade in the docs. There&apos;s one sentence in &lt;a href=&quot;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/10.9/devguide/cdevcsecureroles.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://db.apache.org/derby/docs/10.9/devguide/cdevcsecureroles.html&lt;/a&gt;, which at this point should probably be removed entirely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Old databases must be (hard) upgraded to at least Release 10.5 before roles can be used.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s also an error message in the error message list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;08004 &amp;#8211; User &apos;&amp;lt;authorizationID&amp;gt;&apos; cannot hard upgrade database &apos;&amp;lt;databaseName&amp;gt;&apos;. Only the database owner can perform this operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would probably be simple enough to remove &quot;hard&quot; from this message.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13570685" author="chaase3" created="Mon, 4 Feb 2013 22:21:25 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Here are two minimal patches that remove references to hard upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.diff removes a sentence from the &quot;Using SQL roles&quot; topic (cdevcsecureroles.html):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M       src/devguide/cdevcsecureroles.dita&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-code.diff removes the word &quot;hard&quot; from one of the messages in the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M       java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages.xml&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be all that is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13570715" author="mikem" created="Mon, 4 Feb 2013 22:47:32 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;i am wondering why you would remove the sentence about roles, the point of soft upgrade is that it is possible that users of the current release&lt;br/&gt;
software may still have databases that are at a version level prior to 10.5.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13570909" author="dagw" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 03:22:49 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m OK with keeping soft upgrade vs. (full) upgrade. In general, I think keeping hints in the docs that the database needs to be at a certain release before a feature is available is helpful, cf. Java&apos;s Javadocs which state from what SE release a new class or methods exists.&lt;br/&gt;
So I agree with Mike here; let the sentence on roles stand but with the harmonized language.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13571231" author="knutanders" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 11:19:47 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The code patch probably also needs to update ErrorCodeTest, which checks the exact message text of this error.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13571336" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 14:30:06 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for all the great advice. I will revise the Dev Guide topic and add to the code patch. While I am at it, I notice there is one other reference to hard upgrade in messages that I can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages_it.properties:08004.C.6=L&apos;&apos;utente &apos;&apos;&lt;/p&gt;
{0}&apos;&apos; non pu\u00F2 eseguire l&apos;&apos;aggiornamento hard del database &apos;&apos;{1}&apos;&apos;. Solo il proprietario del database pu\u00F2 eseguire questa operazione.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Interestingly, the other European-language properties files that contain this message don&apos;t seem to have the problem:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages_de_DE.properties:08004.C.6=Benutzer &apos;&apos;{0}
&lt;p&gt;&apos;&apos; kann kein Upgrade der Datenbank &apos;&apos;&lt;/p&gt;
{1}&apos;&apos; erzwingen. Hierzu ist nur der Datenbankeigent\u00FCmer berechtigt.&lt;br/&gt;
java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages_es.properties:08004.C.6=El usuario &apos;&apos;{0}&apos;&apos; no puede realizar una actualizaci\u00F3n completa de la base de datos &apos;&apos;{1}
&lt;p&gt;&apos;&apos;. S\u00F3lo el propietario de la base de datos puede realizar esta operaci\u00F3n.&lt;br/&gt;
java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages_fr.properties:08004.C.6=L&apos;&apos;utilisateur &apos;&apos;&lt;/p&gt;
{0}
&lt;p&gt;&apos;&apos; ne peut pas effectuer une mise \u00E0 niveau mat\u00E9rielle de la base de donn\u00E9es &apos;&apos;&lt;/p&gt;
{1}
&lt;p&gt;&apos;&apos;. Seul le propri\u00E9taire de la base de donn\u00E9es peut effectuer cette op\u00E9ration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German and French just use plain &quot;upgrade&quot;; Spanish uses &quot;full upgrade&quot; (how clever). I&apos;m helpless with the Asian ones, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New patches will be coming.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13571373" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 15:15:00 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s another thought: the Dev Guide topic &quot;Soft upgrade limitations&quot; is superfluous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At releases 10.1 and 10.2 this topic described specific features of those releases that were not available in a soft upgrade. Then for releases 10.3 through 10.5 this topic was not modified, so the features list was obsolete. Then we took out the feature-specific text and pointed readers to the release notes. Now almost all the information in that topic is also in the previous topic (&quot;Upgrading a database&quot;), with the exception of a couple of sentences that could be moved there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to revise the patch to make these changes &amp;#8211; what do you think?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13571445" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 16:44:39 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-2.diff, &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.stat, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.zip, with the following Developer&apos;s Guide changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D       src/devguide/tdevupgradesoft.dita&lt;br/&gt;
M       src/devguide/cdevcsecureroles.dita&lt;br/&gt;
M       src/devguide/tdevupgradedb.dita&lt;br/&gt;
M       src/devguide/derbydev.ditamap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also attaching &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-code2.diff and &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-code2.stat, with the following code changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M       java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages.xml&lt;br/&gt;
M       java/engine/org/apache/derby/loc/messages_it.properties&lt;br/&gt;
M       java/testing/org/apache/derbyTesting/functionTests/tests/lang/ErrorCodeTest.java&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope these help make the upgrade documentation and terminology more clear and consistent.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13572102" author="dagw" created="Wed, 6 Feb 2013 02:51:26 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Kim. Looks good. The sentence reintroduced for roles should probably say &quot;fully upgraded&quot; now: Since we retain the term soft upgrade, the term &quot;upgrade&quot; is not precise. Maybe we should state in the section &quot;upgrading a database&quot; that any usage of the unqualified term &quot;upgrade&quot; will (normally, unless with the soft qualifier) mean a full upgrade? Or did you do through other uses to check that they are properly qualified?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13572431" author="chaase3" created="Wed, 6 Feb 2013 14:13:28 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Dag, both those changes make sense. I did not check all uses of &quot;upgrade&quot; for the &quot;full&lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/thumbs_up.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&quot; qualification, but a spot check suggests that plain old &quot;upgrade&quot; is often used.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13572469" author="chaase3" created="Wed, 6 Feb 2013 15:00:36 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Attaching &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-3.diff and &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-2.zip (just to be confusing) with additional changes to cdevcsecureroles.dita and tdevupgradedb.dita. More feedback is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13577052" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 12 Feb 2013 21:50:03 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Haven&apos;t heard any comments in a week, so &amp;#8211;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committed patch &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-3.diff to documentation trunk at revision 1445404. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are any problems with this, please let me know. I plan to commit the code patch tomorrow and resolve the issue, but I can reopen it if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13577394" author="dagw" created="Wed, 13 Feb 2013 07:38:12 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;For the simplified Chinese, you can remove this character (&quot;hard&quot;): &#30828;&lt;br/&gt;
For traditional Chinese you can remove these two characters&lt;br/&gt;
(&quot;enforced&quot;): &#24375;&#21046;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netbeans let&apos;s you edit the properties files directly, but&lt;br/&gt;
unfortunately, it changes all the hex encoding to another case &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/sad.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
In any case, we know now they do contain the &quot;hard&quot; adverb (to the&lt;br/&gt;
extend the word category applies for Chinese.. &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
Dag&lt;/p&gt;


</comment>
                            <comment id="13577581" author="chaase3" created="Wed, 13 Feb 2013 14:11:37 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Dag. Unfortunately both my mailer and browser show the actual Chinese characters instead of the unicode versions (backslash-u followed by a 4-digit hex code), which are all I can see in the text editor. Could you please let me know the unicode equivalents? &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579017" author="dagw" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 07:47:25 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Kim, uploading a diff with for the localization files. If you apply it, you should be able to see that the texts have changed by removing the characters I indicated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579250" author="chaase3" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 15:36:50 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Dag! I will commit the first code patch, then apply and commit yours. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579270" author="chaase3" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 16:06:14 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed patch &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/DERBY-6061&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade language is inconsistent&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;DERBY-6061&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;DERBY-6061&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-code2.diff to code trunk at revision 1446656. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579277" author="chaase3" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 16:13:20 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Actually, your patch is in a different format from mine, and the patch command doesn&apos;t seem to know what to do with it. What command do you use to apply patches that have diff commands inside them?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579308" author="kristwaa" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 16:50:02 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Kim, did you try patch with -p1 instead of -p0?&lt;br/&gt;
Looks like Dag uploaded a git patch, which (by default) has an extra directory prefix you have to strip off.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579325" author="chaase3" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 17:05:00 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;A-HA! Of course that&apos;s it. Thanks, Kristian! (I&apos;ll put that in my cheat sheet...)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579430" author="chaase3" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 19:15:04 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed patch derby-6061-chinese.diff (thanks, Dag) to code trunk at revision 1446728. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue can be reopened to make more properties file changes as needed.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13579697" author="dagw" created="Sat, 16 Feb 2013 03:47:15 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The Russian localization does not have that error message localized at all yet (08004.C.6), as well as 08004.C.3 and 08004.C.4 and others, I&apos;m sure.&lt;br/&gt;
Rick, has Russian been left behind?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13580851" author="myrna" created="Mon, 18 Feb 2013 21:49:34 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The Russian, Czech, Hungarian and Polish language files were contributed by IBM a long time ago - but no further translations will be coming from that source. Oracle does not contribute translations for these languages.&lt;br/&gt;
So yes, Russian and those other languages will fall further and further behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derby should pop up the English version for messages for which there is no translation in a particular locale.&lt;br/&gt;
(Note that for this reason, if we &lt;b&gt;change&lt;/b&gt; languages, we &lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt; remove the translation from these comatose language files. Better to get a correct English message than nonsense in the local locale.).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13585845" author="rhillegas" created="Mon, 25 Feb 2013 13:14:50 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Dag,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Myrna says is correct. Oracle (and before that, Sun) has been keeping the following localizations evergreen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese (simplified and traditional)&lt;br/&gt;
French&lt;br/&gt;
German&lt;br/&gt;
Italian&lt;br/&gt;
Japanese&lt;br/&gt;
Korean&lt;br/&gt;
Spanish&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
-Rick&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13612654" author="chaase3" created="Mon, 25 Mar 2013 14:17:05 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Closing, since changes have appeared in Latest Alpha Manuals.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12568027" name="DERBY-6061-2.diff" size="6995" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 16:44:39 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12568230" name="DERBY-6061-2.zip" size="7493" author="chaase3" created="Wed, 6 Feb 2013 15:00:36 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12568229" name="DERBY-6061-3.diff" size="7622" author="chaase3" created="Wed, 6 Feb 2013 15:00:36 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12567892" name="DERBY-6061-code.diff" size="694" author="chaase3" created="Mon, 4 Feb 2013 22:21:25 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12568028" name="DERBY-6061-code2.diff" size="2710" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 16:44:39 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12568029" name="DERBY-6061-code2.stat" size="207" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 16:44:39 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12567891" name="DERBY-6061.diff" size="758" author="chaase3" created="Mon, 4 Feb 2013 22:21:25 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12568025" name="DERBY-6061.stat" size="163" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 16:44:39 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12568026" name="DERBY-6061.zip" size="7434" author="chaase3" created="Tue, 5 Feb 2013 16:44:39 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12567893" name="cdevcsecureroles.html" size="15343" author="chaase3" created="Mon, 4 Feb 2013 22:21:25 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12569476" name="derby-6061-chinese.diff" size="1572" author="dagw" created="Fri, 15 Feb 2013 07:47:25 +0000"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>11.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 17:04:10 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>310669</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hzbgrb:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>311014</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                            </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>