<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 05:37:57 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/TIKA-488/TIKA-488.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[TIKA-488] Add alternative search provider on site</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/TIKA-488</link>
                <project id="12310631" key="TIKA">Tika</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Add additional search provider (to existed Lucid Find) search-lucene.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initiated in discussion: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.search-lucene.com/m/uTJxE2kcRv1&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.search-lucene.com/m/uTJxE2kcRv1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Requirements (copied from discussion):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jukka Zitting: &quot;Ideally the search box would allow the user to choose which provider&lt;br/&gt;
to use. Something like a cookie that remembers the user&apos;s selection&lt;br/&gt;
would be nice. If the user doesn&apos;t make an explicit selection of the&lt;br/&gt;
provider, then one should be selected randomly for the first search&lt;br/&gt;
and remembered afterwards for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be great if the required logic was implemented on the client&lt;br/&gt;
side using javascript, as otherwise we&apos;d need to start messing up with&lt;br/&gt;
CGI scripts, etc.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12472089">TIKA-488</key>
            <summary>Add alternative search provider on site</summary>
                <type id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/improvement.png">Improvement</type>
                                            <priority id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/minor.png">Minor</priority>
                        <status id="5" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/resolved.png" description="A resolution has been taken, and it is awaiting verification by reporter. From here issues are either reopened, or are closed.">Resolved</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="chrismattmann">Chris A. Mattmann</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="alexb">Alex Baranau</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Fri, 20 Aug 2010 13:04:32 +0100</created>
                <updated>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 14:40:24 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 14:40:24 +0100</resolved>
                                                    <fixVersion>0.8</fixVersion>
                                    <component>documentation</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>2</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12900677" author="alexb" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 13:05:29 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attachment contains site.vm changes only.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900695" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:01:59 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Alex,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for this patch! I&apos;m wondering &amp;#8211; why keep the choice for a year? I don&apos;t really get that. How about we just expose a select list or something and let the user explicitly choose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
Chris&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900699" author="alexb" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:14:43 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Chris,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reviewing the patch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case user doesn&apos;t select any provider from the dropdown then it is determined randomly. And even if it was randomly determined we store the selection in s cookie. I got this idea from Jukka&apos;s comment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;...If the user doesn&apos;t make an explicit selection of the&lt;br/&gt;
provider, then one should be selected randomly for the first search&lt;br/&gt;
and remembered afterwards for consistency.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I understand his intention correctly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re &quot;one year&quot; life time: I thought it is a good term for this purpose. Please, let me know if you think we should adjust it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900702" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:21:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Alex,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In case user doesn&apos;t select any provider from the dropdown then it is determined randomly. And even if it was randomly determined we store the selection in s cookie. I got this idea from Jukka&apos;s comment:  &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;...&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would just force the user to make the selection. Why make it random?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
Chris&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900708" author="jukkaz" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:35:44 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Why make it random?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to just type in my query and hit enter. The average user shouldn&apos;t have to care about which provider is being used. See also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2010/08/19.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2010/08/19.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900709" author="alexb" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:40:37 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Chris,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you mean something like &quot;disable Search button until provider is selected&quot;? Looks not very user-friendly to me. It might makes sense to select some option from the list when user opens page for the first time (instead of doing it in case user didn&apos;t change default &quot;select provider&quot; choice after he presses the Search button). But &lt;b&gt;imo&lt;/b&gt; when we show user &quot;select provider&quot; message explicitly, we better &quot;advertise&quot; multiple options he has (so that user can note that he has a choice easier).&lt;br/&gt;
Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900710" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:43:20 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to just type in my query and hit enter. The average user shouldn&apos;t have to care about which provider is being used. See also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2010/08/19.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2010/08/19.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heh, yeah. It&apos;s simple if there is one provider. The problem is though, the randomness bugs me because it means the results aren&apos;t repeatable. As a user, if do a search and then on some days (or in the case of this patch, on some years &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; ) I see Lucid&apos;s skin and results and am taken to its website, bu then on others I see Sematext&apos;s, with possibly different results, and an entirely different skin, I&apos;m kind of like huh? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t feel strongly about this though since I rarely do searches via our search box, but at the very least if the choice is random it shouldn&apos;t be in there for a year. If it is, that means that we really remove the randomness, and then X% of our community will think that the search &lt;b&gt;always&lt;/b&gt; go to Lucid, and 100-X% will think that our search &lt;b&gt;always&lt;/b&gt; goes to Sematext. So, at the very least, that needs to be a more sensible number, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
Chris&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900712" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 15:47:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Alex:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you mean something like &quot;disable Search button until provider is selected&quot;? Looks not very user-friendly to me. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. There&apos;s more than one UI way to force a user to make a selection. One way would be to just make one of the items in the select box selected by default and let the user explicitly decide to choose the other one. We could make the &quot;selected&quot; attribute the thing that is random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It might makes sense to select some option from the list when user opens page for the first time (instead of doing it in case user didn&apos;t change default &quot;select provider&quot; choice after he presses the Search button). But &lt;b&gt;imo&lt;/b&gt; when we show user &quot;select provider&quot; message explicitly, we better &quot;advertise&quot; multiple options he has (so that user can note that he has a choice easier).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah like I said above I think what you&apos;re saying here is one of the options to make this happen. Also see my comments back to Jukka. I don&apos;t feel really strongly about the &lt;b&gt;how&lt;/b&gt; UI-wise this gets accomplished, but I do feel strongly about making magic defaults last for a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
Chris&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12900744" author="gsingers" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 16:57:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I&apos;d agree, a year is a bit much.  I think a drop down should suffice and it would be nice to be able to get the same results.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900772" author="alexb" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 18:01:15 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Let me elaborate on how the patch works (for those who don&apos;t have time to do check-out apply it and build things):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When user first opens the page he sees the dropdown with providers and &quot;select provider&quot; option is selected by default.&lt;br/&gt;
a) In case user leaves &quot;select provider&quot; (i.e. doesn&apos;t pick any provider) then system will determine the provider for him randomly. System will store the choice in cookie (one year length). Next time user opens a page the provider in dropdown will be pre-selected to the use the same search provider (user will see the same &quot;skin&quot; if he doesn&apos;t change provider). But user is able to change the provider using that dropdown (it is still available). If he does this, system acts as in point b).&lt;br/&gt;
b) In case user selects particular provider from the dropdown then system will store selection in a cookie (for a year) and will use it unless user one time selects to use different one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it&apos;s not that user is &quot;locked&quot; with some provider for a year if he doesn&apos;t make explicit selection: he/she is free to change it (I believe that the dropdown is quite noticeable). It&apos;s just that consistency of a &quot;skin&quot; that we support by storing selection (random or explicit) in a cookie for such a long period. We could change &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900803" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 19:03:57 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks Alex. I&apos;ll try and test the patch out. Again, my position is that a year is a bit long for a cookie expiration that sets an explicit default (even if it&apos;s overridable by a user).&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12900820" author="alexb" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 19:44:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Chris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to agree with that one year is too much. Let&apos;s come up with some time interval which will give user an impression of consistency (in terms of &quot;search skin&quot;) and also will allow users to find out that there are multiple search engines available.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12900899" author="otis" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 23:32:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m fine with whatever time period people think will work best for users.  Maybe that&apos;s just 3 months, maybe 6, maybe 12.  I suppose it&apos;s safer to pick a smaller value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do agree with Chris about picking a random provider and displaying its name as selected in the pull-down menu if we don&apos;t detect a previously stored cookie.  It feels a little better than picking a random provider &lt;b&gt;after&lt;/b&gt; the person clicks on the search button.  At the same time, showing something like &quot;select provider&quot; may nudge the person to actually open up the pull-down and explicitly look for and pick a provider (he/she will have to do this only once every N months) - picking a random provider and displaying it as selected may not get the person to look at what other providers are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see the benefits of both approaches, so I&apos;m fine with either choice.   Plus, we can change the behaviour later if after some use we feel the other approach might be better after all.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12904125" author="otis" created="Mon, 30 Aug 2010 10:55:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Chris, do you want to commit this as-is and refine later when more people get to try it, or should we change how things work with random search provider selection before committing?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12904245" author="chrismattmann" created="Mon, 30 Aug 2010 17:44:14 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Otis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah I don&apos;t want to get in the way on this. I&apos;ll probably just commit it with a shorter cookie lifespan (maybe a few months), and get the ball rolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
Chris&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12904624" author="chrismattmann" created="Tue, 31 Aug 2010 14:40:24 +0100"  >&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;patch applied to latest website in r991187. I changed the cookie time span from 1 year to 90 days. I think that&apos;s a fine default, and shouldn&apos;t create too much hassle for the users of the site for a default selection. Thanks to Alex for the patch and to those that commented!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12452624" name="adding_alternative_search_provider.patch" size="2929" author="alexb" created="Fri, 20 Aug 2010 13:05:29 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>1.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Fri, 20 Aug 2010 14:01:59 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>4373</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hxx3hb:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>16883</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>