<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 05:29:27 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/TIKA-6/TIKA-6.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[TIKA-6] Port Nutch (or better) MimeType detection system into Tika</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/TIKA-6</link>
                <project id="12310631" key="TIKA">Tika</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This patch will contribute a MimeType detection system for Tika, including MImeType data structure, and associated content-detection facilities. This will be based on Nutch&apos;s MimeType system as a baseline, however, I&apos;m open to suggestions. Jerome Charron mentioned that he had an implementation of a MimeType system based on FreeDesktop.org&apos;s system. We should look into this as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment>&lt;p&gt;Improvement is indep. of environment&lt;/p&gt;</environment>
        <key id="12371102">TIKA-6</key>
            <summary>Port Nutch (or better) MimeType detection system into Tika</summary>
                <type id="2" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/newfeature.png">New Feature</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="chrismattmann">Chris A. Mattmann</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="chrismattmann">Chris A. Mattmann</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 7 Jun 2007 05:12:16 +0100</created>
                <updated>Sat, 3 Nov 2007 05:42:15 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Fri, 21 Sep 2007 16:11:36 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>0.1-incubating</version>
                                    <fixVersion>0.1-incubating</fixVersion>
                                    <component>general</component>
                        <due>Wed, 20 Jun 2007 07:00:00 +0000</due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12528966" author="chrismattmann" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 04:14:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Folks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a long time coming. I&apos;ve ported Jerome&apos;s new Mime Type repository (based on freedesktop.org&apos;s mime system) to Tika, with most of the effort coming from Jerome and the legwork to clean it up for Tika coming from me &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments appreciated. If there are no objections, I&apos;d like to commit this in the next 48 hrs. There are some issues to talk through on this, which I&apos;ll send a separate email about soon.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12528993" author="bdelacretaz" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 07:07:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Two questions about this patch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also going to ask about Jerome&apos;s ICLA (as IIUC he wrote most of that code), but according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.apache.org/~jim/committers.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://people.apache.org/~jim/committers.html&lt;/a&gt; he&apos;s a Nutch committer so that looks good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Is the freedesktop.org stuff ok, license-wise, to be included in our codebase?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) IIUC this stuff is independently reusable, should we make it a separate Maven module? A standalone tika-mime-type.jar might be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12529120" author="chrismattmann" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 15:39:07 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Bertrand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reviewing the patch. I should have made this more clear earlier, so I apoligize. &quot;Jerome&quot; referenced in my prior comment is Jerome Charron. Jerome and I were the ones that originally came up with the idea for Tika while working on the Nutch project, and we proposed it to the list then. Jerome is one of the Nutch committers, as you noted above and had earlier contributed a MimeType repository capability to Nutch, but had not updated it for a while. Jerome had told me that he was working on a new version based on Freedesktop.org&apos;s mime system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AFAIK, with respect to question #1, I think it&apos;s ok to distribute the freedesktop.org mime database with our system because it&apos;s GPL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With respect to question #2, I&apos;m -1 for making the mime database a separate module. It was intended to be one of the core functionalitie and contributions of the Tika library, and provides much value added for a content analysis toolkit (mime detection is an integral part of it). Jerome and I had originally thought about taking the mime DB (before Tika) to jakarta commons, however, that idea evolved from providing a simple mime detection library to a full-fledged content analysis toolkit library, that including mime detection, Tika.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529124" author="bdelacretaz" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 15:54:23 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;About the freedesktop.org stuff, if it&apos;s indeed GPL (or even LGPL) we cannot redistribute it, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.apache.org/~cliffs/3party.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://people.apache.org/~cliffs/3party.html&lt;/a&gt; (not official policy but AFAIK all the info in there is valid).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding question #2, this is something that might be better discussed on the list, I should have brought that up there. Nothing urgent anyway, I&apos;m fine with having just one module for now.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529135" author="jukkaz" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 17:08:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think we can include the freedesktop.org.xml file in Tika. AFAIK the database originates from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/shared-mime-info&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/shared-mime-info&lt;/a&gt; and is distributed under the GPL. What we can do instead is to provide a configuration option (with a reasonable default) for a user to point Tika to the mime database file already available on a system. This way we don&apos;t need to include the viral component within Tika releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the source files have the following license header. I guess it&apos;s an oversight and easily resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    //Copyright (c) 2007, California Institute of Technology.&lt;br/&gt;
    //ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. U.S. Government sponsorship acknowledged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we should update the license headers to the latest version available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apache.org/legal/src-headers.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.apache.org/legal/src-headers.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529143" author="bdelacretaz" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 17:26:47 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Chris suggests (on the dev list):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; ...I propose&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt; that we remove the file freedesktop.org.xml, and then rename the DTD file&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;gt; from freedesktop.org.dtd to mime.types.dtd....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that DTD file was part of the freedesktop package, this would not be ok IMHO, as the whole package is covered by the GPL license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OTOH, if the DTD was &quot;independently created&quot;, reusing the same data model for our mime-type database is probably ok (do we want to confirm this?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry to be picky about that, but there were some interesting discussions about similar cases at the ASF recently &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;, and I much prefer to write code than having to handle stuff like this &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://mail-archives.apache.org/mod_mbox/www-legal-discuss/200708.mbox/browser&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://mail-archives.apache.org/mod_mbox/www-legal-discuss/200708.mbox/browser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529311" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 05:04:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hey Guys:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated patch that tries to address comments by Jukka and Bertrand. Thanks for the comments folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are no objections to this, I&apos;d like to get it committed within the next 48 hrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, once committed, it would be great to get some responses to my early email regarding configuring TIKA. It&apos;s the info that I need to know to link up the mime type detection here from &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/TIKA-6&quot; title=&quot;Port Nutch (or better) MimeType detection system into Tika&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;TIKA-6&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;TIKA-6&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to the parser stuff contributed by Rida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;br/&gt;
  Chris&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529325" author="jukkaz" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 08:28:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Looks good, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the files have an @author tag with Hari Kodungallur in addition to Jerome, do we have some history on the extent of his involvement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d be happier with larger indents (4 spaces as in the Sun Java coding style), but I&apos;m not too worried about that.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529427" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 15:02:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Jukka:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Some of the files have an @author tag with Hari Kodungallur in addition to Jerome, do we have some history on the extent of his involvement? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question: I don&apos;t know much about the history of Hari, but Jerome may. Doing a bit of research, the only code that has Hari&apos;s name in the author tags, are MimeType.java and MimeTypeException.java. These files are more or less based on their Nutch versions, which were contributed by Jerome, and covered by his CLA. The nutch versions are here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/nutch/trunk/src/java/org/apache/nutch/util/mime/MimeType.java&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/nutch/trunk/src/java/org/apache/nutch/util/mime/MimeType.java&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/nutch/trunk/src/java/org/apache/nutch/util/mime/MimeTypeException.java&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/nutch/trunk/src/java/org/apache/nutch/util/mime/MimeTypeException.java&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the spaces, I&apos;ve updated them to use Sun&apos;s style, 4 space chars for an indent. So, when I commit the patch that part will be fixed too. As an FYI: do we want to adopt the Sun convention across the board here? What do others think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I don&apos;t here anything else about the patch I will commit it sometime in the next few hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
  Chris&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529434" author="jukkaz" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 15:17:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;OK, thanks. As far as I&apos;m concerned it&apos;s OK to commit the patch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12529460" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 16:11:36 +0100"  >&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;included new Mime type detection system contributed in large part by J. Charron.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;added unit tests to exercise the new mime system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;TODO: link up the mime detection system with the Parser framework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12529462" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 16:12:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch applied to trunk:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc?rev=578161&amp;amp;view=rev&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc?rev=578161&amp;amp;view=rev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc?rev=578162&amp;amp;view=rev&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc?rev=578162&amp;amp;view=rev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for everyone&apos;s comments!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12539817" author="chrismattmann" created="Sat, 3 Nov 2007 05:42:15 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Jukka,&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;+1 for removing freedesktop.org.xml. I think that we should include the&lt;br/&gt;
tika-mimetypes.xml file (which is equivalent to the current nutch mime types&lt;br/&gt;
xml file, formatted using the freedesktop.org mime type dtd) though, since&lt;br/&gt;
it originated from an Apache project. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;+1 for this: my bad. I thought I had configured Tika within the project&lt;br/&gt;
settings for my eclipse, but neglected to double check that. I will fix it&lt;br/&gt;
in the latest patch.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;+1 for this too. I will update it in the latest patch and reattach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, what do folks think about the code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br/&gt;
  Chris&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;p&gt;______________________________________________&lt;br/&gt;
Chris Mattmann, Ph.D.&lt;br/&gt;
Chris.Mattmann@jpl.nasa.gov&lt;br/&gt;
Cognizant Development Engineer&lt;br/&gt;
Early Detection Research Network Project&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_________________________________________________&lt;br/&gt;
Jet Propulsion Laboratory            Pasadena, CA&lt;br/&gt;
Office: 171-266B                     Mailstop:  171-246&lt;br/&gt;
_______________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer:  The opinions presented within are my own and do not reflect&lt;br/&gt;
those of either NASA, JPL, or the California Institute of Technology.&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12539818" author="chrismattmann" created="Sat, 3 Nov 2007 05:42:15 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Guys,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Thanks Thilo, Bertrand and Jukka for chiming in. I&apos;m not exactly sure how&lt;br/&gt;
to proceed either since I&apos;m better at developing code than sorting out legal&lt;br/&gt;
issues &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I can only speak from my analogous experience within Nutch here in which&lt;br/&gt;
the Eclipse.org DTD format, more or less, is the basis of the&lt;br/&gt;
(near-equivalent) Nutch plugin.xml format. Nutch has its own plugin.dtd&lt;br/&gt;
(that I helped to draft, along with Jerome CHarron), based on the Nutch&lt;br/&gt;
plugin system developed primarily by Stefan Groschupf. Essentially, Stefan&lt;br/&gt;
developed a set of code to interpret plugin.xml files, and do things with&lt;br/&gt;
their data (process it, reformat it, make it available, etc.) to other Nutch&lt;br/&gt;
subsystems. This entire code base was developed specifically for Nutch. The&lt;br/&gt;
only thing that was reused was the plugin DTD&apos;s &quot;model&quot; (perhaps modulo an&lt;br/&gt;
attribute field or two in one of the tags).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Here, we have a very similar case. Jerome Charron has clearly used the&lt;br/&gt;
shared mime-info DTD format from freedesktop.org as the &quot;data model&quot; for his&lt;br/&gt;
mime type db format. However, the entire code-base that reads, interprets,&lt;br/&gt;
reformats, and processes the information made available by the mime type&lt;br/&gt;
database, was written by Jerome. Also, I&apos;m not sure that Jerome&apos;s mime DTD&lt;br/&gt;
(and associated mime XML format) provided in &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/TIKA-6&quot; title=&quot;Port Nutch (or better) MimeType detection system into Tika&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;TIKA-6&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;TIKA-6&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; doesn&apos;t add some new&lt;br/&gt;
capability (e.g., I notice that the Nutch mimes are in this new mime db as&lt;br/&gt;
well) that was not present in the freedesktop.org original one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; So, to me, and mind you, I have pretty much 0% experience interpreting OS&lt;br/&gt;
licenses, etc., as well as interpreting law &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;, this is an equivalent, and&lt;br/&gt;
acceptable case here. I guess what it really boils down to is IP on a &quot;data&lt;br/&gt;
model&quot;. For instance, must any mime databases developed in the future that&lt;br/&gt;
contain at least the shared mime-info database data elements defined in the&lt;br/&gt;
DTD as a subset of their information, restricted to being GPL? I would be&lt;br/&gt;
scared/shocked if the answer to that is &quot;yes&quot;. To me, it&apos;s hard to slap IP&lt;br/&gt;
issues onto a &quot;data model&quot;. If that were the case, wouldn&apos;t any software&lt;br/&gt;
developed for an ISO data model standard (e.g., ISO-11179) be required to&lt;br/&gt;
adopt whatever the license is that the 11179 model standards body decided?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; My 2 cents,&lt;br/&gt;
   Chris&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;p&gt;______________________________________________&lt;br/&gt;
Chris Mattmann, Ph.D.&lt;br/&gt;
Chris.Mattmann@jpl.nasa.gov&lt;br/&gt;
Cognizant Development Engineer&lt;br/&gt;
Early Detection Research Network Project&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_________________________________________________&lt;br/&gt;
Jet Propulsion Laboratory            Pasadena, CA&lt;br/&gt;
Office: 171-266B                     Mailstop:  171-246&lt;br/&gt;
_______________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer:  The opinions presented within are my own and do not reflect&lt;br/&gt;
those of either NASA, JPL, or the California Institute of Technology.&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12366247" name="TIKA-6.Mattmann.091907.patch.txt" size="903262" author="chrismattmann" created="Thu, 20 Sep 2007 04:14:52 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12366327" name="TIKA-6.Mattmann.092007.patch.txt" size="100642" author="chrismattmann" created="Fri, 21 Sep 2007 05:04:01 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Thu, 20 Sep 2007 06:07:04 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>4856</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hxx6g7:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>17364</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>