<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 05:50:52 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/ZOOKEEPER-1732/ZOOKEEPER-1732.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[ZOOKEEPER-1732] ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732</link>
                <project id="12310801" key="ZOOKEEPER">ZooKeeper</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a test in which I do a rolling restart of three ZooKeeper servers and it was failing from time to time.&lt;br/&gt;
I ran the tests in a loop until the failure came out and it seems that at some point one of the servers is unable to join the enssemble formed by the other two.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment>&lt;p&gt;Windows 7, Java 1.7&lt;/p&gt;</environment>
        <key id="12658778">ZOOKEEPER-1732</key>
            <summary>ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble</summary>
                <type id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/bug.png">Bug</type>
                                            <priority id="1" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/blocker.png">Blocker</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="abranzyck">Germ&#225;n Blanco</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="abranzyck">Germ&#225;n Blanco</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 17:14:57 +0100</created>
                <updated>Thu, 13 Mar 2014 18:17:14 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 03:22:24 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>3.4.5</version>
                                    <fixVersion>3.4.6</fixVersion>
                    <fixVersion>3.5.0</fixVersion>
                                    <component>leaderElection</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>10</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="13713797" author="abranzyck" created="Fri, 19 Jul 2013 17:17:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This are the logs of the three ZooKeeper servers in the cluster. The restart of server with myid=1 happened at 10:16:39. After that restart the server is unable to join the enssemble.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13713801" author="abranzyck" created="Fri, 19 Jul 2013 17:23:03 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;It seems that the two servers in the enssemble are sending Notifications with a different peerEpoch to the one out of the ensemble:&lt;br/&gt;
2013-07-19 10:17:00,833 &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;myid:1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; - INFO  [WorkerReceiver&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;myid=1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;:FastLeaderElection@542] - Notification: 3 (n.leader), 0xb800000099 (n.zxid), 0xb9 (n.round), FOLLOWING (n.state), 2 (n.sid), 0xb8 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)&lt;br/&gt;
2013-07-19 10:17:00,833 &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;myid:1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt; - INFO  [WorkerReceiver&lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;myid=1&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;:FastLeaderElection@542] - Notification: 3 (n.leader), 0xb900000052 (n.zxid), 0xba (n.round), LEADING (n.state), 3 (n.sid), 0xb9 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)&lt;br/&gt;
Is that correct?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13713933" author="fpj" created="Fri, 19 Jul 2013 19:48:29 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here is my analysis of the logs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server 3 has been elected two times, both times with support of Server 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;preformatted panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;preformattedContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;2013-07-19 10:16:09,746 [myid:3] - DEBUG [QuorumPeer[myid=3]/0:0:0:0:0:0:0:0:30103:FastLeaderElection@493] - About to leave FLE instance: leader=3, zxid=0xb800000099, my id=3, my state=LEADING

2013-07-19 10:16:26,667 [myid:3] - DEBUG [QuorumPeer[myid=3]/0:0:0:0:0:0:0:0:30103:FastLeaderElection@493] - About to leave FLE instance: leader=3, zxid=0xb900000052, my id=3, my state=LEADING
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server 2 elects Server 3 but loses the connection to Server 3 right after:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;preformatted panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;preformattedContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;2013-07-19 10:16:20,858 [myid:2] - INFO  [QuorumPeer[myid=2]/0:0:0:0:0:0:0:0:30102:Follower@63] - FOLLOWING - LEADER ELECTION TOOK - 47
2013-07-19 10:16:20,858 [myid:2] - WARN  [RecvWorker:3:QuorumCnxManager$RecvWorker@762] - Connection broken for id 3, my id = 2, error = 
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it doesn&apos;t seem to go into a new round of leader election. Because it is not trying to elect a new leader, its vote reflects the state of the first leader instance of Server 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Server 3 later on loses its connection to Server 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;preformatted panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;preformattedContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;2013-07-19 10:16:34,307 [myid:3] - WARN  [RecvWorker:1:QuorumCnxManager$RecvWorker@762] - Connection broken for id 1, my id = 3, error = 
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but it doesn&apos;t seem to care, so it must have the support of Server 2. Server 2 again seems to be referring to a previous leader instance of Server 3, so its support to Server 3 must be surviving the crash of Server 3 around &quot;2013-07-19 10:16:20,858 &lt;span class=&quot;error&quot;&gt;&amp;#91;myid:2&amp;#93;&lt;/span&gt;&quot; and my guess is that Server is getting confused about dropping the connection right after electing Server 3 and it is trying to establish a new connection, which succeeds when Server 3 comes back up. I think there is a race there....&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13714506" author="abranzyck" created="Sat, 20 Jul 2013 19:28:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot for your analysis, Flavio!&lt;br/&gt;
If that is the case, then it would be solved by refreshing the proposal after the Follower connects to the Leader, right?&lt;br/&gt;
I will try to make a modification with a refreshment of the proposal and run the test again to check what happens.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13714783" author="fpj" created="Sun, 21 Jul 2013 20:28:10 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If that is the case, then it would be solved by refreshing the proposal after the Follower connects to the Leader, right?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would you refresh the proposal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, there are three ways to solve this issue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If a follower receives a notification from the guy it thinks it is following and the notification is more recent (later round or higher zxid), then it stops following and goes back to LOOKING.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Same as before but instead of transitioning to LOOKING, the follower updates its notification and keeps trying to connect to the leader.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;We change LeanerInfo so that it carries leader election information for verification purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we should do the first one. The second one bypasses the LE protocol, so I&apos;m not in favor of going that direction, although it might not break anything if we do it. The third option changes the protocol, so it is a bit of a pain to deal with the backward compatibility stuff.  &lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="13714965" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 08:09:22 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I tried to refresh the proposal simply by doing &quot;updateProposal(getInitId(), getInitLastLoggedZxid(), getPeerEpoch());&quot;, before sending a notification when the server that sends it is part of an established ensemble. The test didn&apos;t run for long enough time, because of other reasons, but I think now that it can&apos;t work anyway. Reading your alternatives now and the way Votes are compared, I see that zxid and epoch need to be the same in all members of the ensemble and in this race case the follower hasn&apos;t received the zxid that the leader used to finish the election.&lt;br/&gt;
My personal preference would be &quot;3&quot;. Because it is faster (follower doesn&apos;t go back to LOOKING, it can just update the proposal with the info in LeaderInfo), and it doesn&apos;t depend on any more races that could lead to the follower not processing the notification from the leader.&lt;br/&gt;
If the protocol backward compatibility issues are just more work, then I will be very willing to help as much as I can.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13714986" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 08:35:21 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My personal preference would be &quot;3&quot;. Because it is faster (follower doesn&apos;t go back to LOOKING, it can just update the proposal with the info in LeaderInfo)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess my description was not clear for 3. The idea was that the learner sends its LE info so that the leader can drop it if the learner info is stale, so the follower goes back to looking in this option as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not worried about making this case fast because this is such a corner case: a follower f elects a leader l, l crashes, l comes back, l is re-elected by a quorum that does not include f, f is able to connect to connect to l.   &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715026" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 10:00:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I see, trying to make this a bit faster doesn&apos;t make sense at all.&lt;br/&gt;
Sorry, but I am confused about the epoch handling in the initial negotiation between the Follower and the Leader.&lt;br/&gt;
The current FOLLOWERINFO QuorumPacket seems to contain already the &quot;acceptedEpoch&quot;, isn&apos;t it already possible for the Leader to check that value and reject the connection if it is wrong?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715042" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 10:27:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Right, this is a bit confusing. Epoch in the context of leader election is not the same as the epoch of zxids, that&apos;s one reason why I often call it LE round, to disambiguate. The epoch you&apos;re referring to has to do with txn identifiers (zxids), not LE epochs (or rounds). &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715056" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 10:42:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Answering myself, I guess the acceptedEpoch in FOLLOWERINFO is not the epoch that was seen last in the election, but the epoch of the last transaction recorded by the Follower. So it doesn&apos;t help in this case.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715057" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 10:43:07 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Sorry, I forgot to refresh the page &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715060" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 10:46:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715069" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 11:07:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I am thinking that, giving that we don&apos;t care if this is solved a few milliseconds later, one way to handle the backward compatibility issues would be this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Follower/Observer sends an increased protocol number in FOLLOWERINFO/OBSERVERINFO.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When the Leader sees the new version, it sends the &quot;LE&quot; epoch and zxid in LeaderInfo.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Follower/Observer check if the Leader has an updated protocol version and if it does, they read the &quot;LE&quot; epoch and zxid from LeaderInfo. If they are not the same as the &quot;LE&quot; epoch and zxid that they have, they start LOOKING again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does that sound ok?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715077" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 11:21:19 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not sure why you think it is better to touch the Zab protocol rather than simply stop following if the follower vote is outdated. It is the simplest thing we can do and it is correct. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think touching the Zab protocol is a good idea, so I still prefer option 1 above.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715089" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 11:35:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I would prefer not to touch the Zab protocol as well, but I don&apos;t want to leave any loose ends. I thought that there was no guarantee that the Follower will receive a notification from the Leader after it connects. &lt;br/&gt;
Do you think that this will always happen?&lt;br/&gt;
This notification is sent through the leader election port, so I guess that it is difficult to make assumptions on when it reaches its destination with respect with when the Follower connects to the Leader. And going deeper in the unlikely combinations, the leader election connection could be lost at some point and Follower and Leader remain connected through the Zab connection.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715115" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 12:09:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I understand your concern, it is a valid one. Our goal however shouldn&apos;t be to have every follower having the most recent notification from the leader. Our goal is to have a leader that has enough supporters so that we can make progress. If all servers are either following/leading, then it doesn&apos;t matter if a follower has stale LE information. But, it does become an issue in the case that you uncovered with your logs. In this scenario, the stale follower will receive a more recent notification from either the leader, when it is trying to be re-elected, or from the follower that is stuck. In either case, it will be able to determine that it is stale and stop following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that the follower stops following only if it realizes that it is stale. If it doesn&apos;t hear anything, then it just keeps going. Does it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About changing the protocol, in my experience, changing messages is a pain because there are many subtle cases and it is quite easy to get it wrong. It is best not to touch it. I think we can take care of this case without really changing the messages we are sending. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715120" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 12:16:36 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;... I should have said &quot;from the server that is stuck&quot;, not &quot;from the follower that is stuck&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715130" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 12:45:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;If I am not wrong, the follower that is stuck never accepts the leadership of the Leader in the ensemble, because it is an established ensemble and it sees no quorum in it. So it will only send notifications proposing itself as the leader. And the leader of the ensemble sends the Notifications only to the follower that is stuck, or? So there is actually no chance for the stale follower to receive the updated leader election information after the initial election is finished.&lt;br/&gt;
I agree that one must be careful when changing network protocols and dealing with backwards compatibility, but if you asked me, I think that it is much easier to make mistakes doing multithreaded concurrent Java programming :-P&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13715474" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 19:13:03 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;there is actually no chance for the stale follower to receive the updated leader election information after the initial election is finished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the leader, upon receiving a notification, instead of responding only to the sender, it sends a batch of notifications? This way we can perform the check I was mentioning before and there is no real change to the protocol, we are just sending more messages every now and then. &lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13715514" author="fpj" created="Mon, 22 Jul 2013 19:43:05 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I was actually thinking that if we do what I just proposed above, then the follower should just update its vote. If a server is following another it believes to be the leader, then it doesn&apos;t matter how it got there, it matters that one believes it is following and the other believes it is leading. My proposal more concretely is to have the leader broadcasting its notification upon receiving a notification for a server that is LOOKING. If a follower receives a notification from the guy it is following and it notices that its vote is outdated, then it updates its vote accordingly. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13716152" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 23 Jul 2013 07:35:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;That sounds good to me.&lt;br/&gt;
I still see option 3 as more straight for solving the problem, but it does involve quite a mess with updating the protocol and test cases and so on for such a corner case. &lt;br/&gt;
It seems that there are no more opinions on this.&lt;br/&gt;
Is it ok if I prepare a patch with the change in the leader election process that you suggest?&lt;br/&gt;
The test case might be a bit tricky, do you have any suggestion for that?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13716210" author="fpj" created="Tue, 23 Jul 2013 08:44:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think you say that 3 is a more direct way of solving the problem because we would be enforcing that a follower is following the right instance of the leader. It is a fair observation, although I tend to think that leader election is unreliable in nature, so I can really go either way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that you are keen on implementing the changes to the recovery handshake, what if we try to outline the precise changes in both cases and try to determine which one to go with once we have that? He are some initial thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For option 3, we add LE information to the LearnerInfo message. The leader checks the version of the protocol and uses the new information in LearnerInfo in the case the protocol version is appropriate. In the case the leader instance information doesn&apos;t match, we have two choices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The leader drops the connection to the follower and the follower goes back to LOOKING;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The leader sends to the follower the LE instance information and the follower updates its vote info.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the second option, I believe we would need a new message, since LEADERINFO only contains a zxid. I&apos;d rather avoid adding another message, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don&apos;t change the recovery handshake and use the other approach I outlined, then I believe all changes are concentrated in the FLE class, perhaps some in QuorumPeer as well, I&apos;m not sure. We just need to call sendNotifications() upon receiving a notification while leading. For a follower, when receiving a notification from a LEADING server, it checks if its vote is still valid, updating otherwise. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it ok if I prepare a patch with the change in the leader election process that you suggest?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, it would be great if you could propose a patch, independent of the approach we end up choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The test case might be a bit tricky, do you have any suggestion for that?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some FLE test cases that implement a mock server. I think we should do something similar here. Instead of trying to reproduce the race, we could just test that the follower correctly updates its information upon receiving a notification.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13716227" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 23 Jul 2013 09:27:26 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;For option 3, we add LE information to the LearnerInfo message ... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would you add the information to the LearnerInfo message? If the receiving side doesn&apos;t support the same version fo the protocol it will not be able to parse the message, right? Do you have in mind to use some current unused field? My suggestion was that in the message with LearnerInfo, the Learner only reports that it supports the additional information i.e. sending 0x10001 as the protocol version. The Leader sees this and then it will include the leader election information together with the LeaderInfo, only if the Learner supports this additional information. The Learner receives the message and it will read the leader election info only if the protocol supported by the Leader is also 0x1001. At this point the Learner can just update its leader election information with the one it got from the Leader. No new message that way &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we don&apos;t change the recovery handshake and use the other approach I outlined, then I believe all changes are concentrated in the FLE class, ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also see it that way, and I would do it exactly as you say. It is around 20 lines of code near the end of FastLeaderElection$Messenger$WorkerReceiver, something like this: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/germanblanco/6060741&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/germanblanco/6060741&lt;/a&gt;. I don&apos;t see any changes in QuorumPeer, but maybe I am missing something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are some FLE test cases that implement a mock server. I think we should do something similar here. Instead of trying to reproduce the race, we could just test that the follower correctly updates its information upon receiving a notification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds very good.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13716234" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 23 Jul 2013 09:42:36 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The changes in option 3 could be something like this: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/germanblanco/6060844&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://gist.github.com/germanblanco/6060844&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
The regression test doesn&apos;t work for these changes, so they still need work, but maybe it helps to explain my intention.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13719372" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 25 Jul 2013 09:20:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;A colleague has suggested that maybe the leader election information of an established ensemble is not that relevant, since it actually doesn&apos;t take part in the leader election logic. The new server just checks if the ensemble has a quorum and the leader is alive (sends a notification voting for itself). I am not able to see all the implications, but at a first look it seems that the ensemble could agree to vote e.g. for the proposed epoch received in LEADERINFO as election epoch and zxid zero and things would work in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would avoid any additional information in the messages altogether.&lt;br/&gt;
What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13719402" author="fpj" created="Thu, 25 Jul 2013 09:56:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;By &quot;agree to vote&quot;, don&apos;t you need a different message pattern, even if the message content is the same? You&apos;re still changing the protocol here. Also, we don&apos;t need agreement, since different processes can have a different opinion about who the leader should be. They need to agree before they start a new epoch, but that&apos;s precisely what the recovery phase of zab does. It does a bit more actually, but the whole state sync up is not relevant to this discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;it actually doesn&apos;t take part in the leader election logic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not entirely true, the LE step exposes a leader that has the highest zxid among a quorum of servers. Also, I think that you&apos;re using LE as the recovery phase of Zab, not that the initial protocol that finds a prospective leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new server just checks if the ensemble has a quorum and the leader is alive (sends a notification voting for itself)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we have discussed this point in this jira. As you have observed, the ensemble is still able to make progress in the situation you have originally described, so the inconsistent LE information doesn&apos;t prevent zookeeper from doing work. The problem is getting a server stuck, which we fix by making sure that a follower is able to send notifications with state that reflects the latest leader election. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option I was actually considering is to loosen the constraint that all FOLLOWING/LEADING notifications need to come from the same LE round. This is possibly too conservative, so it might be ok to change it, but I need to think a bit more about it.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13719483" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 25 Jul 2013 11:39:44 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The proposal meant to set the election epoch to the same value during the initial phase of the Zab protocol. That &quot;same value&quot; would be the proposed epoch in the LEADERINFO structure. As you say, it is a change in the protocol, even if messages have the same information. And it wouldn&apos;t work if there are servers in the quorum with different behaviours (e.g. 3.4.5 and 3.4.6 with this change implemented), since they will end up reporting different election epoch.&lt;br/&gt;
I hope loosening the constrain works, that would really be an easy solution &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13719541" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 25 Jul 2013 12:54:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The file test_loosen_restrictions.tar.gz contains a patch to loosen the checking of election epoch when a new server joins an established ensemble. Also contains the report of the test case that failed when running the regression on branch-3.4 using this patch.&lt;br/&gt;
Test case is FollowerResyncConcurrencyTest, I can&apos;t tell the relationship between the failure and the change. I guess there are more things to think about, but maybe this points to some problem already.&lt;br/&gt;
I also started the long test with all the rolling restarts, so far it is going ok.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13720488" author="abranzyck" created="Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:20:49 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-LOOSEN_RESTRICTIONS.patch is the patch on the 3.4 branch removing the check for the election round when joining an established ensemble.&lt;br/&gt;
It seems that the failure in FollowerResyncConcurrencyTest had nothing to do with the change, and a lot to do with the fact that it was running in a virtual environment that introduced a few delays in the execution.&lt;br/&gt;
This change passes all the tests and it allows my test of continous rolling restarts to run without failures (at least 800 times, when it used to fail before the 200th).&lt;br/&gt;
The patch also removes a couple of possibilities that made me uncomfortable, namely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;joining an ensemble that votes me as the leader.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;taking into account my own votes or votes that put me as a leader when joining an ensemble.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;me&quot; is the server joining the ensemble.&lt;br/&gt;
Since leader election is intrinsically unreliable, and odd things may happen, I think it is better to avoid these just in case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13720595" author="fpj" created="Fri, 26 Jul 2013 10:58:48 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;joining an ensemble that votes me as the leader.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m ok with removing it, this is an optimization. If the leader is being re-elected, then it means that the ensemble it is trying to join is not functional, since the leader is not present. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do it, you might as well check the change of &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1514&quot; title=&quot;FastLeaderElection - leader ignores the round information when joining a quorum&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1514&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1514&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in checkLeader. I think the if block you added is not necessary if you make the change in check leader. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;taking into account my own votes or votes that put me as a leader when joining an ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think we are currently taking into account the vote of a LOOKING server when processing FOLLOWING/LEADING notifications. If you&apos;re talking about endVote, this is the vote corresponding to the leader it elected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;removing the check for the election round when joining an established ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give some insight here first. We need to have servers joining an established ensemble because a server may find that a quorum is already following some leader and if it follows the standard procedure of processing notifications, then there are some corner cases that can cause it to keep electing some other server that is also looking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The danger of joining an established ensemble is the following. Say that a minority of followers support a leader L, and a majority M supports L&apos;. L&apos; has enough supporters and is able to commit txns. Now say that a server S in the ensemble of L&apos; crashes and recovers. S talks to L and its minority now forming a majority (say there was one server missing to form a majority). L will tell all servers in its ensemble to truncate causing some txns to be lost. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a couple of mechanisms that prevent this incorrect truncation from happening. First, S needs to receive FOLLOWING/LEADING notifications from a quorum, not including itself. In this case, the incorrect truncation only happens if S receives a stale message, a message from a server S&apos; that later on followed L&apos;. We prevent this case by having maximum one outstanding notification in QuorumCnxManager in the queue of a peer. If S&apos; has followed L&apos;, then its notification must reflect it and S won&apos;t receive such a stale message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall it sounds fine to only consider the server the followers are following. Note that not only the round could be different, but I believe the zxid could also be different.&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="13720793" author="abranzyck" created="Fri, 26 Jul 2013 14:50:30 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot for the insight!&lt;br/&gt;
I read then that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The checking of the ensemble voting for the server that joins may remain.&lt;br/&gt;
  It is true that it is checked again in checkLeader (covering additional cases). &lt;br/&gt;
  Since we set all votes to round 0 and the current logicalclock starts counting with 1 then the server joining will not pass the check in checkLeader.&lt;br/&gt;
  However the additional checking is more readable and it avoids the processing of adding these invalid votes to the outofelection list and the rest of the checkings.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The other checking is removed, since it is not possible for those votes to arrive to this point.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;According to your explanation, the check of round and zxid when joining an ensemble may be avoided.&lt;br/&gt;
  It doesn&apos;t help to avoid that the server joins a broken ensemble in minority, since they will have anyway the same epoch and zxid.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The checking of the zxid also needs to be &lt;b&gt;loosened&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.patch removes the cheking of zxid and adds a test case.&lt;br/&gt;
In order to implement the test case, one additional line in FastLeaderElection.java was changed.&lt;br/&gt;
It changes logicalclock for current.getElectionEpoch(), which I believe must be the same when not in LOOKING state.&lt;br/&gt;
That allows me to change the value of the round sent in FLE Notifications.&lt;br/&gt;
I am guessing also that it is ok to SUBMIT the patch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13720809" author="abranzyck" created="Fri, 26 Jul 2013 14:57:36 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.patch loosens the checking of leader election round and zxid when a server joins an existing ensemble. It avoids a corner case in which the servers in an ensemble ended up with different leader election information. It includes one additional test case in FLETest.java&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13720835" author="hadoopqa" created="Fri, 26 Jul 2013 15:32:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12594398/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12594398/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1503101.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs (version 1.3.9) warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1522//testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1522//testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1522//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1522//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1522//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1522//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13724085" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 30 Jul 2013 18:12:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think now that we also need to do something with the peerEpoch. I can&apos;t explain why this hasn&apos;t failed so far in my tests, maybe the corner case causing this problem is even more unlikely than what I thought. But the peer epoch value does get sent from the leader to the follower after election, right? So it would be possible to just update the value in the leader election information of the follower, during the synchronization phase of the Zab protocol, instead of loosening the restriction. In that way, there will be at least one check verifying that all the votes come from an ensemble established with the same epoch.&lt;br/&gt;
What do you think?&lt;br/&gt;
I will also run the tests again with a trace to see when the inconsistent ensemble is created.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13728909" author="abranzyck" created="Sun, 4 Aug 2013 16:59:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The problem was difficult to reproduced, so I made this change in order to open the window of opportunity for bad things to happen.&lt;br/&gt;
It works, the inconsistencies appear 7 times in around 200 rolling restarts.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13728941" author="abranzyck" created="Sun, 4 Aug 2013 19:26:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The updated patch contains the changes to the handling of peerEpoch. The rolling restart test runs ok, even when the inconsistencies happen. However, I haven&apos;t been able to run the Zab1_0Test successfully. The virtual environment that I used for Linux times out and Windows fails with and without the patch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13730935" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 6 Aug 2013 17:45:08 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;... and now the patch &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.patch with date August 6th seems to work.&lt;br/&gt;
It is for the trunk branch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13730980" author="hadoopqa" created="Tue, 6 Aug 2013 18:22:23 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12596368/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12596368/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1503101.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs (version 1.3.9) warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1529//testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1529//testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1529//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1529//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1529//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1529//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13752196" author="abranzyck" created="Wed, 28 Aug 2013 08:51:35 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Could anybody please review this?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13752197" author="jgrasl" created="Wed, 28 Aug 2013 08:52:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;
I am out of the office from 2013-08-26 to 2013-08-31. I check my emails on 2013-09-01.&lt;br/&gt;
If you need immediate assistance or information about question, please contact Csaba Nagy(ecsanag).&lt;br/&gt;
This is an auto reply message sent by my Out of Office Assistance.&lt;br/&gt;
We only send and receive email on the basis of the term set out at&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ericsson.com/email_disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.ericsson.com/email_disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13754728" author="jgrasl" created="Fri, 30 Aug 2013 15:38:03 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the last comment, OoO assistant replied to Germ&#225;n&apos;s comment.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13774406" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 23 Sep 2013 10:18:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The correction can also be applied to the 3.4 branch. Would it make sense to correct this in 3.4.6?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13781428" author="abranzyck" created="Sun, 29 Sep 2013 17:38:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I am going to guess that if this is a Blocker to 3.5.0, it makes sense to fix it for 3.4.6 as well.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13781430" author="hadoopqa" created="Sun, 29 Sep 2013 17:41:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;-1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12604546/ZOOKEEPER-1732-3.4.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12604546/ZOOKEEPER-1732-3.4.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1527129.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    -1 patch.  The patch command could not apply the patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1604//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1604//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13781520" author="fpj" created="Sun, 29 Sep 2013 23:45:00 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for working on this one, German. It is fine with me to have this one in 3.4.6, and here are some comments on the patch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This check is redundant, isn&apos;t it? I&apos;d rather not have a redundant check. If you have an idea for making the code clearer, then we could give a try, but let&apos;s try to avoid redundant checks. Avoiding the additions to outofelection won&apos;t make much difference in this case.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I didn&apos;t understand why it is &quot;newEpoch - 1&quot; instead of &quot;newEpoch&quot; straight.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The indentation doesn&apos;t seem right in Learner.java. I also suggest to add a comment about updating the vote there, linking perhaps to this jira.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What if we replace &quot;updateElectionPeerEpoch&quot; with either &quot;updateElectionVote&quot; or &quot;updateCurrentVote&quot;? I also don&apos;t think it should be public.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;It would be simpler in updateElectionPeerEpoch() to have something like this:
&lt;div class=&quot;code panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;codeContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;code-java&quot;&gt;
setCurrentVote(&lt;span class=&quot;code-keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; Vote(currentVote.getId(), 
                                          currentVote.getZxid(), 
                                          currentVote.getElectionEpoch(), 
                                          newEpoch-1,
                                          currentVote.getState());
);
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13781639" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 30 Sep 2013 08:11:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot for taking a look at this, and for your comments.&lt;br/&gt;
1 - I guess you mean the  &quot;if (n.leader != self.getId())&quot; check in FastLeaderElection.java. I will remove that.&lt;br/&gt;
2 - This is because the final election vote in the leader will have &quot;newEpoch - 1&quot;. The winning vote will contain the epoch of the leader, but once the election finishes, the leader increments the epoch. So actually &quot;newEpoch&quot; is the epoch that won the election plus one. And the vote reported in the Fast Leader Election is the vote that won the election. If we set the vote to just &quot;newEpoch&quot;, then we need to update the vote also in the Leader, and not only on Learners as it is currently done. At least that is how I think it works.&lt;br/&gt;
3 - I will fix identation and add the comment. The identation is funny around those lines though.&lt;br/&gt;
4 - I will change the name and change to protected.&lt;br/&gt;
5 - Also will do.&lt;br/&gt;
Patches will be uploaded in some minutes.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13781747" author="hadoopqa" created="Mon, 30 Sep 2013 12:29:03 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12605873/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12605873/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1527398.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs (version 1.3.9) warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1606//testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1606//testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1606//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1606//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1606//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1606//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13784565" author="fpj" created="Wed, 2 Oct 2013 23:38:17 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I have downgraded this issue to major, it is a corner case and unlikely to happen often, but we still need to fix it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m thinking that we should update the peer epoch at the end of syncWithLeader rather than where it is in registerWithLeader. After syncing, we know the current epoch, so we should just update it there. I was also thinking that the we could update the zxid as well, although it doesn&apos;t matter too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The indentation is still wrong for me.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13784807" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 05:16:28 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I will update the patches as you propose. It also seems better to me to update this information when the ensemble is finally established.&lt;br/&gt;
With &quot;the current epoch&quot; I assume that you mean the new epoch for the ensemble and that this will have to be updated in the followers and in the leader (so no newEpoch-1, but newEpoch). If I misunderstood, please let me know.&lt;br/&gt;
I don&apos;t know how to choose a zxid that is agreed between the leader and all the followers. I will leave that for now, but if you know how to do it, please let me know.&lt;br/&gt;
I am assuming that you mean the modification in Learner.java for the indentation comment. The indentation was already wrong in that part of the code. If I am not wrong, there are 8 spaces and a tab in the lines above and below the modification. I believe I have put 8 spaces and a tab also in the modified lines. In the editors that I use it looks ok. If you want me to try to fix the indentation around the change, it is ok with me. If you mean another change or you don&apos;t see 8 spaces and a tab there or I should use a different combination for these lines, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13784822" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 05:56:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Oooops! I just noticed that the change in Learner.java is the one that needs to be moved to another method, so if the last indentation comment was about that change, then please never mind about my response. Hopefully I will get the indentation right in the new method &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13784922" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 09:35:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I think the latest attached patch covers the comments.&lt;br/&gt;
I noticed also that there was a problem in the test case in trunk. It was a copy of the test case for branch-3.4 and it actually required a few changes.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13784955" author="hadoopqa" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 10:57:10 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12606543/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12606543/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1528586.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs (version 1.3.9) warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1634//testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1634//testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1634//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1634//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1634//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1634//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13785329" author="marshall" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 17:43:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ve just run into this issue running tip of trunk 3.5.0 &lt;b&gt;without&lt;/b&gt; this patch applied. Are there any proposed workarounds to this problem? I tried removing the stuck node from the ensemble and adding another node in as a replacement but it is now hitting the same problem... It can&apos;t join the ensemble either. I&apos;m considering restarting all zookeeper servers in the hopes that a new round of leader election will reset things. Does this sound safe? Are there any other alternatives? Really appreciate any help.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13785332" author="fpj" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 17:47:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;You could try bringing the leader down instead of bringing the whole cluster down. It should do it.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13785345" author="marshall" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 18:02:31 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Flavio, that suggestion worked perfectly! Simply restarting the leader caused a new round of leader election and things sorted themselves out within a few seconds. Thank you so much for such a prompt reply. Love this community! &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13788947" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 8 Oct 2013 07:08:06 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Is there anything else to be done in this one?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13789374" author="fpj" created="Tue, 8 Oct 2013 17:46:59 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;One thing I&apos;m not happy about your patch is that you use zero as &quot;don&apos;t care&quot; values. For readability, I&apos;d rather have perhaps different method calls or constants reflecting the fact that we are not taking those values into account. Adding comments to the code explaining what&apos;s going on sounds like a good thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13790051" author="abranzyck" created="Wed, 9 Oct 2013 06:49:22 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thank you for the review and the comments.&lt;br/&gt;
The attached patch should cover the requested changes.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13790071" author="hadoopqa" created="Wed, 9 Oct 2013 07:23:31 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12607515/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12607515/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1530166.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs (version 1.3.9) warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1664//testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1664//testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1664//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1664//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1664//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1664//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13800109" author="fpj" created="Sun, 20 Oct 2013 10:00:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks, &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=abranzyck&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;abranzyck&quot;&gt;Germ&#225;n Blanco&lt;/a&gt;, for the changes. I have reorganized and reformatted a bit the 3.4 patch, could you make sure you agree with the changes, please? If you +1 it, then I can generate a trunk patch and I&apos;ll commit it.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13800150" author="abranzyck" created="Sun, 20 Oct 2013 16:36:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 to the 3.4 patch. Thank you &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=fpj&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;fpj&quot;&gt;Flavio Junqueira&lt;/a&gt;, for the review and for making those changes, I shouldn&apos;t have left it like that. &lt;br/&gt;
That means one blocker less to go for 3.4.6! Thanks a lot also for your work on the release.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13800766" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 17:11:47 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Sorry, I didn&apos;t realise you changed the name, and I was giving comments to my last version vs. the one before that.&lt;br/&gt;
To your changes, I only have the comment that I understand that you intend to apply the same formatting to the trunk patch, right?&lt;br/&gt;
I can do that if you want.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13800769" author="fpj" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 17:15:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m sorry too, I haven&apos;t been able to get to it. If you have some time and can generate the trunk patch, I&apos;d appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13800828" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 18:18:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The reformatted patches are attached.&lt;br/&gt;
Both &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.patch and &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-b3.4.patch, since there was an empty comment for the new constant.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13800881" author="hadoopqa" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 18:56:22 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12609472/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12609472/ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 1533161.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 3 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs (version 1.3.9) warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1713//testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1713//testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1713//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1713//artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1713//console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/PreCommit-ZOOKEEPER-Build/1713//console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13801129" author="fpj" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 22:37:56 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1, thanks, German.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branch 3.4: Committed revision 1534388.&lt;br/&gt;
Trunk: Committed revision 1534390.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13801717" author="hudson" created="Tue, 22 Oct 2013 12:09:06 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;SUCCESS: Integrated in ZooKeeper-trunk #2097 (See &lt;a href=&quot;https://builds.apache.org/job/ZooKeeper-trunk/2097/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://builds.apache.org/job/ZooKeeper-trunk/2097/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot; title=&quot;ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1732&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1732&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. ZooKeeper server unable to join established ensemble (German Blanco via fpj) (fpj: &lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/?root=Apache-SVN&amp;amp;view=rev&amp;amp;rev=1534390&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/?root=Apache-SVN&amp;amp;view=rev&amp;amp;rev=1534390&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;/zookeeper/trunk/CHANGES.txt&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;/zookeeper/trunk/src/java/main/org/apache/zookeeper/server/quorum/FastLeaderElection.java&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;/zookeeper/trunk/src/java/main/org/apache/zookeeper/server/quorum/Leader.java&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;/zookeeper/trunk/src/java/main/org/apache/zookeeper/server/quorum/Learner.java&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;/zookeeper/trunk/src/java/main/org/apache/zookeeper/server/quorum/QuorumPeer.java&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;/zookeeper/trunk/src/java/test/org/apache/zookeeper/test/FLETest.java&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13807102" author="rgs" created="Mon, 28 Oct 2013 18:48:40 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=fpj&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;fpj&quot;&gt;Flavio Junqueira&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=abranzyck&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;abranzyck&quot;&gt;Germ&#225;n Blanco&lt;/a&gt;: did you guys test this patch when joining a cluster of servers running without this patch (i.e.: trunk, only without this patch)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After rolling the first 2 followers - in a 5 member ensemble - the 3rd follower fails to join with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;preformatted panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;preformattedContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;2013-10-28 18:43:18,134 - INFO  [WorkerReceiver[myid=4]] - Notification: 4 (n.leader), 0x8900000415 (n.zxid), 0x6 (n.round), LOOKING (n.state), 4 (n.sid), 0x89 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)0 (n.config version)
2013-10-28 18:43:18,134 - INFO  [WorkerReceiver[myid=4]] - Notification: 2 (n.leader), 0x880000002c (n.zxid), 0xffffffffffffffff (n.round), FOLLOWING (n.state), 0 (n.sid), 0x89 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)0 (n.config version)
2013-10-28 18:43:18,135 - INFO  [WorkerReceiver[myid=4]] - Notification: 2 (n.leader), 0x880000002c (n.zxid), 0x6 (n.round), LEADING (n.state), 2 (n.sid), 0x88 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)0 (n.config version)
2013-10-28 18:43:18,135 - INFO  [WorkerReceiver[myid=4]] - Notification: 2 (n.leader), 0x880000002c (n.zxid), 0x6 (n.round), FOLLOWING (n.state), 3 (n.sid), 0x88 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)0 (n.config version)
2013-10-28 18:43:18,136 - INFO  [WorkerReceiver[myid=4]] - Notification: 2 (n.leader), 0x880000002c (n.zxid), 0xffffffffffffffff (n.round), FOLLOWING (n.state), 1 (n.sid), 0x89 (n.peerEPoch), LOOKING (my state)0 (n.config version)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am guessing IGNOREVALUE (0xffffffffffffffff) as the round value is causing issues? What was the expected behavior here (i.e.: when dealing with cluster members without this patch during an upgrade)?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13807553" author="fpj" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 01:02:59 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;hmm, this is odd. I don&apos;t understand why the notifications don&apos;t have the same round value, the don&apos;t care value in this case. The value is also not what I expected, so I might have done something wrong there. Let me have a closer look and report back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reporting, &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=rgs&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;rgs&quot;&gt;Raul Gutierrez Segales&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13807565" author="rgs" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 01:22:49 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;What&apos;s wrong with the round values? i.e.: the two new servers have IGNOREVALUE (sounds correct right?) and the older followers have the current round value (i.e.: 0x6). I thought the problem would be here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;preformatted panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;preformattedContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;                         * @see https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1732                                                                  
                         */
                        outofelection.put(n.sid, new Vote(n.leader,
                                IGNOREVALUE, IGNOREVALUE, n.peerEpoch, n.state));
                        if (termPredicate(outofelection, new Vote(n.leader,
                                IGNOREVALUE, IGNOREVALUE, n.peerEpoch, n.state))
                                &amp;amp;&amp;amp; checkLeader(outofelection, n.leader, IGNOREVALUE)) {
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IGNOREVALUE doesn&apos;t work here, because we are talking to un-patched cluster members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry if I am completely misleading you &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; That&apos;s as far as I got with my analysis today. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13807588" author="fpj" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 02:00:31 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I see, my mental model of the problem ignored the fact that there were servers with newer and older versions, my bad. I think the IGNOREVALUE is not really being ignored, I&apos;ll come up with a fix, but I&apos;ll do it in a different jira.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13807633" author="thawan" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 03:27:19 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;May be we should start considering automate rolling upgrade test?.  In jenkins we might be able to continuously grab 3.4 branch and perform rolling upgrade to 3.5 and verify that quorum come up&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13807673" author="fpj" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 04:47:33 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Given that rolling upgrades seem to be very common, it doesn&apos;t sound like a bad idea to automate the testing. I think we can&apos;t do it with junit, or at least I don&apos;t know how.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13807789" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 08:36:11 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I think that the problem might be in the epoch handling. When we used &quot;newEpoch&quot;, instead of &quot;newEpoch-1&quot; the result is that an old leader still reports &quot;newEpoch-1&quot;, but the updated followers report &quot;newEpoch&quot;. As a result, a new server that tries to join sees an inconsistency in the voting, even when it is ignoring zxid and election epoch information.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13808004" author="fpj" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 14:06:50 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I have to think about this one, but from the log excerpt that Raul posted, one problem I can see is that n.round has different values, so vote.equals in termPredicate when comparing the votes, no?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13808081" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 15:24:01 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Yes, that is what I mean.&lt;br/&gt;
The round value in the votes is updated in updateElectionVote() after the election is finished.&lt;br/&gt;
In the previous code (without the patch) the vote when the election was finished had the epoch of the leader. That is, the epoch that the new leader had when the election started.&lt;br/&gt;
In the code after the patch, the vote is updated in updateElectionVote() to the epoch that the leader is using after the election is finished, which is one more than the epoch that it was using when the election started.&lt;br/&gt;
I think that if &quot;newEpoch-1&quot; is used to update the election vote, then things should be ok. If that is done, then servers with and without the patch should have the same value of epoch in the vote after the election is finished.&lt;br/&gt;
It is very good that &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=rgs&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;rgs&quot;&gt;Raul Gutierrez Segales&lt;/a&gt; has spotted this so soon, since it would have been seen in all upgrades from 3.4.5 to 3.4.6. On the other hand, consequences are not too serious. It only happens when servers with different versions are running in the same quorum and it only happens if there is an ensemble running (so there should be no interruption of the service).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13808194" author="rgs" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 17:27:34 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Hmm, I still think this could confuse people rolling a cluster. Sounds like we should revert this for the next release unless we have a fix for it. Smooth upgrades through rolling restarts are an expectation that ZooKeeper has always maintained. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13808290" author="fpj" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 18:45:49 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=abranzyck&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;abranzyck&quot;&gt;Germ&#225;n Blanco&lt;/a&gt;, aren&apos;t you confusing rounds and epochs? Rounds become &quot;don&apos;t cares&quot; for non-looking servers with the patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/ViewProfile.jspa?name=rgs&quot; class=&quot;user-hover&quot; rel=&quot;rgs&quot;&gt;Raul Gutierrez Segales&lt;/a&gt;, the fix seems to be logically simple. I&apos;m not ready to revert it yet, and thanks for reminding us of the things that zookeeper has always maintained.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13808322" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 29 Oct 2013 19:09:49 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Yes, I am. Thank you for the correction.&lt;br/&gt;
If you replace &quot;round&quot; with &quot;peerEpoch&quot; in my comment I think that it will make sense.&lt;br/&gt;
Should we do this in a new JIRA then?&lt;br/&gt;
If so, then I can prepare a patch on the current trunk and branch 3.4 and test the rolling upgrade. Although I don&apos;t like too much the idea of leaving the patches in this JIRA without the correction.&lt;br/&gt;
The changes are very straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;remove the changes in Leader.java&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Change the line in Learner.java to: &quot;self.updateElectionVote(newEpoch-1);&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="13808709" author="fpj" created="Wed, 30 Oct 2013 03:22:24 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Moving the discussion to &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-1805&quot; title=&quot;&amp;quot;Don&amp;#39;t care&amp;quot; value in ZooKeeper election breaks rolling upgrades&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-1805&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-1805&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="13933794" author="fpj" created="Thu, 13 Mar 2014 18:17:14 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Closing issues after releasing 3.4.6.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="10030">
                    <name>Reference</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="relates to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12676539">ZOOKEEPER-1805</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                        </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12595813" name="CREATE_INCONSISTENCIES_patch.txt" size="1191" author="abranzyck" created="Sun, 4 Aug 2013 16:59:58 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12607514" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732-3.4.patch" size="8583" author="abranzyck" created="Wed, 9 Oct 2013 06:46:42 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12606540" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732-3.4.patch" size="7645" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 09:14:04 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12605872" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732-3.4.patch" size="6701" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 30 Sep 2013 11:39:22 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12604546" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732-3.4.patch" size="7631" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 23 Sep 2013 10:18:52 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12609471" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732-b3.4.patch" size="8973" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 18:15:39 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12609306" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732-b3.4.patch" size="8973" author="fpj" created="Sun, 20 Oct 2013 10:00:20 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12609472" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch" size="9086" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 21 Oct 2013 18:18:46 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12607515" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch" size="8535" author="abranzyck" created="Wed, 9 Oct 2013 06:49:22 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12606543" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch" size="7596" author="abranzyck" created="Thu, 3 Oct 2013 09:35:45 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12605873" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch" size="6787" author="abranzyck" created="Mon, 30 Sep 2013 11:45:29 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12596368" name="ZOOKEEPER-1732.patch" size="7668" author="abranzyck" created="Tue, 6 Aug 2013 17:45:08 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12595812" name="zklog.tar.gz" size="64563" author="abranzyck" created="Sun, 4 Aug 2013 16:53:54 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>13.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 18:48:29 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>338972</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310191" key="com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.customfieldtypes:multicheckboxes">
                        <customfieldname>Hadoop Flags</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                                <customfieldvalue key="10343"><![CDATA[Reviewed]]></customfieldvalue>
    
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hzgb53:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>339292</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>