<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 05:41:34 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/ZOOKEEPER-336/ZOOKEEPER-336.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[ZOOKEEPER-336] single bad client can cause server to stop accepting connections</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-336</link>
                <project id="12310801" key="ZOOKEEPER">ZooKeeper</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;One user saw a case where a single mis-programmed client was overloading the server with connections - the client was creating a huge number of sessions to the server. This caused all of the fds on the  server to become used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems like we should have some way of limiting (configurable override) the maximum number of sessions from a single client (say 10 by default?) Also we should output warnings when this limit is exceeded (or attempt to exceed).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12416770">ZOOKEEPER-336</key>
            <summary>single bad client can cause server to stop accepting connections</summary>
                <type id="4" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/improvement.png">Improvement</type>
                                            <priority id="2" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/critical.png">Critical</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="henryr">Henry Robinson</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="phunt">Patrick Hunt</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 12 Mar 2009 18:37:15 +0000</created>
                <updated>Wed, 8 Jul 2009 21:24:00 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Tue, 9 Jun 2009 06:05:19 +0100</resolved>
                                                    <fixVersion>3.2.0</fixVersion>
                                    <component>c client</component>
                    <component>java client</component>
                    <component>server</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>2</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12705895" author="henryr" created="Tue, 5 May 2009 05:18:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached is a patch which does the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Adds a configuration variable maxClientCnxns which defaults to 10, which limits the number of simultaneous connection attempts from an InetAddress. (This is the change that touches most files).&lt;br/&gt;
2. Update NIOServerCnxn.java to implement this change by closing a socket connection that contravenes this limit. I added a new constructor (called by the old one), plus the data structures to quickly find how many connections are already open from a particular address in O(1) (assuming finite maxClientCnxns) time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If maxClientCnxns is 0, there is no limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limitations: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If many clients are behind a NAT, this limit will have to be taken off as the code cannot distinguish between different NATted clients.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This probably isn&apos;t effective in the face of IPv6 if a single user has loads of addresses &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At present, clients that can&apos;t connect retry once every second. I also have a patch that adds a maxConnectionAttempt configuration variable, and have ClientCnxn enforce the limit, but I haven&apos;t found a clean way to call up to the ZooKeeper object and tell it to abandon the connection attempt (ZooKeeper.close() maybe seems to deadlock, I&apos;ll look further later).&lt;/p&gt;

</comment>
                            <comment id="12706550" author="henryr" created="Wed, 6 May 2009 19:32:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Just to update, I&apos;m preparing a second patch which - while it doesn&apos;t change the functionality - improves some formatting issues as per comments on another patch plus adds a unit test. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12706602" author="henryr" created="Wed, 6 May 2009 22:36:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here is the new patch. Improvements are: tidied up formatting / added some comments to a public constructor / added a new test which validates the connection limiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, the question of whether this functionality belongs in ZooKeeper and not an iptables rule or similar. I think it&apos;s helpful to have this in the ZK server to provide an easy fix for misbehaving clients.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12707073" author="phunt" created="Thu, 7 May 2009 21:05:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Hi Henry, from your comments it looks like you&apos;re ready for review, in ZooKeeper (hadoop in general) this is indicated&lt;br/&gt;
by clicking &quot;submit patch&quot; on the left hand side of the JIRA page. This triggers the review/commit workflow - in &lt;br/&gt;
particular it will run the hadoop qa bot and let us (committers) know to review for commit. The process is&lt;br/&gt;
documented here:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/ZooKeeper/HowToContribute&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/ZooKeeper/HowToContribute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s also fine to submit drafts and ask for review, but I think in this case you are saying it&apos;s ready for final review (correct&lt;br/&gt;
me if I&quot;m wrong). One nice thing about submitting is that it&apos;s listed on the project page as &quot;patch available&quot; and ensures&lt;br/&gt;
that we won&apos;t overlook it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will review this presently.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12707455" author="phunt" created="Fri, 8 May 2009 19:14:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Note to committer: we should flag this in the changes.txt and release notes as it could introduce issues for customers who&lt;br/&gt;
exceed the max (by design). For example system test environments. We just need to mention in release notes as potential &lt;br/&gt;
issue and how to address (set to 0).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12707517" author="phunt" created="Fri, 8 May 2009 21:34:50 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Some minor formatting changes, in particular 80 character limit on lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of note: I changed the log level to WARN rather than INFO when the max connection limit is exceeded.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12707524" author="phunt" created="Fri, 8 May 2009 21:52:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I noticed the following issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) it&apos;s great to see tests &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/wink.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; however the included test needs to be improved a bit. Two issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) under heavy load (like we see on hudson.zones.apache.org) the test may fail due to the use of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ve found that using sleep in tests is a two fold problem. What happens is that usually the test runs fine, however&lt;br/&gt;
under heavy load the sleep may not be long enough, resulting in invalid test failure. This is particularly onerous&lt;br/&gt;
on hudson.zones.apache.org, which is a virtualized system and gates commits. A second reason we generally&lt;br/&gt;
dont use sleep is that it artificially inflates the run time of the test, making agile/CI based development painful&lt;br/&gt;
(granted this is something we need to improve on, ie test run time, and are working towards)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of using sleep the test should first loop to start all the sockets, then loop to see if the sockets are either&lt;br/&gt;
connected or failed to connect, counting the number of success and checking against expected. The check should&lt;br/&gt;
wait for a socket result for some max period of time and if the time is exceeded (say 60sec) then the test fails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) we should really test the zk client code to ensure they handle this correctly/gracefully. It would be great to have&lt;br/&gt;
an additional Java and an additional C test that uses ZooKeeper objects and ensures that the first N &amp;lt; max work&lt;br/&gt;
properly when N &amp;gt; max clients are started, and that the clients &amp;gt; max give proper watcher notification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) this is a user externally visible change - the docs need to be updated. Hadoop uses forrest for docs, zookeeper&lt;br/&gt;
in particular uses simpledocbook xml format for the doc source markup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the source docs in src/docs/src/documentation/content/xdocs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can re-generate the documentation using forrest, which you can download from&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://forrest.apache.org/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://forrest.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Note: forrest requires jdk5 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run forrest as follows:&lt;br/&gt;
PATH=$PATH:/home/phunt/dev/apache-forrest-0.8/bin JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib/jvm/java-1.5.0-sun ant -Dforrest.home=/home/phunt/dev/apache-forrest-0.8 -Djava5.home=/usr/lib/jvm/java-1.5.0-sun docs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the generated docs are put into trunk/docs. You probably want to put this into the admin/ops docs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) in getClientCnxnCount there&apos;s no need for removeall (inefficient as well), just use an int and count unclosed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) in the updated patch I changed info to warning for the max connection exceeded. This happens infrequently&lt;br/&gt;
enough, and it&apos;s important enough to list as a warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Note: we have 80 character limit on line length. the updated patch fixes these issues. This is a  rule&lt;br/&gt;
we break it in certain rare instances but in generl keep line length to 80chars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you use eclipse you can set general-&amp;gt;editor-&amp;gt;texteditor-&amp;gt;showprintmargin, I find this useful&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12707532" author="henryr" created="Fri, 8 May 2009 22:12:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;1a) That makes a lot of sense, I&apos;ll do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1b) Should this be part of a separate issue? The clients don&apos;t yet do the right thing if they get refused; they should retry a few times then give up. Like I mentioned earlier, I&apos;ve got half of a patch to do this but haven&apos;t worked out the clean shutdown code path yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Will do&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. I was concerned about keeping around connections that have closed for ever. More efficient code is probably just to create a new set with all the live connections and swap it out for the old set?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the feedback!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12707536" author="phunt" created="Fri, 8 May 2009 22:47:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;1b) I expect the client to do the right thing, but as you are explicitly forcing a particular behavior, one that may not &lt;br/&gt;
happen very often, I thought it was best to ensure it works. Otw going to be hard bug to track down in production. (we&lt;br/&gt;
don&apos;t expect this code to be exercised very often, if at all). You should submit everything as single patch, rather than open a &lt;br/&gt;
potential hole - also saves on the back/forth of multiple jiras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) ah, yes, I missed that aspect, good point. In that case you should remove the cnxn from the ipmap during cnxn close operation.&lt;br/&gt;
Much like the factory.cnxns is being updated there. Of course it is a bit tricker due to concurrency.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12714700" author="henryr" created="Sat, 30 May 2009 13:08:46 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s another pass at the patch, with a better-written test and updated documentation.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12714734" author="hadoopqa" created="Sat, 30 May 2009 16:45:54 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12409460/ZOOKEEPER-336.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12409460/ZOOKEEPER-336.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 780122.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 6 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/97/testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/97/testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/97/artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/97/artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/97/console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/97/console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12715690" author="fpj" created="Tue, 2 Jun 2009 22:14:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Henry, I agree with Patrick that it would be good to have a C test as well. Could you please add one to this patch?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12715971" author="henryr" created="Wed, 3 Jun 2009 17:17:20 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve included a C and Java client test in this new patch. I have modified ZooKeeperServerMain to accept a further optional maxcnxns argument on the command line in order to be able to write the C test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both client tests work by having two clients connect to a server that only accepts one connection at a time. When the first client connects it is closed, allowing the second to connect as it retries. &lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12716007" author="hadoopqa" created="Wed, 3 Jun 2009 18:51:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;-1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12409788/ZOOKEEPER-336.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12409788/ZOOKEEPER-336.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 781266.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 23 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    -1 core tests.  The patch failed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/101/testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/101/testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/101/artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/101/artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/101/console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/101/console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12716017" author="henryr" created="Wed, 3 Jun 2009 19:18:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I can&apos;t reproduce this error here - all tests pass on my machine. Is it related to the fact that Hudson is currently reporting errors even without this patch?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12716025" author="phunt" created="Wed, 3 Jun 2009 19:37:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;resubmitting the patch - the test failure was cause by :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;java.net.BindException: Address already in use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in one of the tests - as Henry suspected it&apos;s a known problem. We have a fix for this, but not&lt;br/&gt;
yet committed (probably 3.3, it&apos;s part of the testng changes).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12716095" author="hadoopqa" created="Wed, 3 Jun 2009 23:53:42 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 overall.  Here are the results of testing the latest attachment &lt;br/&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12409788/ZOOKEEPER-336.patch&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/attachment/12409788/ZOOKEEPER-336.patch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  against trunk revision 781266.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 @author.  The patch does not contain any @author tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 tests included.  The patch appears to include 23 new or modified tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javadoc.  The javadoc tool did not generate any warning messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 javac.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of javac compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 findbugs.  The patch does not introduce any new Findbugs warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 release audit.  The applied patch does not increase the total number of release audit warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 core tests.  The patch passed core unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    +1 contrib tests.  The patch passed contrib unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/102/testReport/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/102/testReport/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Findbugs warnings: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/102/artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/102/artifact/trunk/build/test/findbugs/newPatchFindbugsWarnings.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Console output: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/102/console&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/Zookeeper-Patch-vesta.apache.org/102/console&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This message is automatically generated.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12716506" author="breed" created="Fri, 5 Jun 2009 06:31:54 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;collision with &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-431&quot; title=&quot;Expose methods to ease ZK integration&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-431&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-431&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12716508" author="breed" created="Fri, 5 Jun 2009 06:32:55 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Made compatible with &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-431&quot; title=&quot;Expose methods to ease ZK integration&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-431&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-431&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12717558" author="breed" created="Tue, 9 Jun 2009 06:05:19 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed revision 782878.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12717567" author="breed" created="Tue, 9 Jun 2009 06:33:18 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;i forgot to add the new files. new files added in revision 782883.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12718511" author="hudson" created="Thu, 11 Jun 2009 16:30:52 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Integrated in ZooKeeper-trunk #343 (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/ZooKeeper-trunk/343/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/ZooKeeper-trunk/343/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12409936" name="ZOOKEEPER-336.patch" size="31155" author="breed" created="Fri, 5 Jun 2009 06:32:55 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12409788" name="ZOOKEEPER-336.patch" size="31201" author="henryr" created="Wed, 3 Jun 2009 17:17:20 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12409460" name="ZOOKEEPER-336.patch" size="18761" author="henryr" created="Sat, 30 May 2009 13:08:46 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12407661" name="ZOOKEEPER-336.patch" size="14324" author="phunt" created="Fri, 8 May 2009 21:34:50 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12407394" name="ZOOKEEPER-336.patch" size="13093" author="henryr" created="Wed, 6 May 2009 22:36:09 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12407213" name="ZOOKEEPER-336.patch" size="8150" author="henryr" created="Tue, 5 May 2009 05:18:09 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>6.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Tue, 5 May 2009 04:18:09 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>47893</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310191" key="com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.customfieldtypes:multicheckboxes">
                        <customfieldname>Hadoop Flags</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                                <customfieldvalue key="10343"><![CDATA[Reviewed]]></customfieldvalue>
    
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hxzy4n:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>33513</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>