<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 05:41:12 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/ZOOKEEPER-38/ZOOKEEPER-38.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[ZOOKEEPER-38] headers (version+) in log/snap files</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-38</link>
                <project id="12310801" key="ZOOKEEPER">ZooKeeper</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Moved from SourceForge to Apache.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;amp;aid=1961767&amp;amp;group_id=209147&amp;amp;atid=1008547&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;amp;aid=1961767&amp;amp;group_id=209147&amp;amp;atid=1008547&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12398003">ZOOKEEPER-38</key>
            <summary>headers (version+) in log/snap files</summary>
                <type id="2" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/newfeature.png">New Feature</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="mahadev">Mahadev konar</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="phunt">Patrick Hunt</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Tue, 10 Jun 2008 23:42:12 +0100</created>
                <updated>Sun, 26 Oct 2008 01:10:37 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Wed, 1 Oct 2008 07:28:35 +0100</resolved>
                                                    <fixVersion>3.0.0</fixVersion>
                                    <component>server</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12604321" author="akornev" created="Wed, 11 Jun 2008 21:13:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached are the patches for the db file header and the CRC &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-32&quot; title=&quot;CRCs for ZooKeeper data&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-32&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-32&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; features, and the unit tests. The patches are generated against the latest code in Source Forge SVN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patch introduces a new zookeeper package: the persistence layer. The package declares a number of public (zookeeper server scope) interfaces: TxnLogFactory, DBInfo, LogReader and LogWriter. The ZooKeeperServer, SyncProcessor and QuorumPeer classes are now relying exclusively on these interfaces to perform snapshotting and logging operations. All of the existing persistence-related code has been factored out to the new package peristence.log which provides the implementations of the above public interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The persistence.ProviderRegistry class is used during the server initialization to obtain an instance of TxnLogFactory based on the user-provided URI. From that moment on, the server uses the factory to access LogReader and LogWriter interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my strong belief that this design improves decoulping and separation of concerns. As a result this will allow us to provide new implementations of the persistence layer more easily. Also, this is a step toward improved testability and simpler code structure, which ideally should make it easier for people to contribute to the project.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12604352" author="mahadev" created="Wed, 11 Jun 2008 22:47:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;lets wait for code base to have moved and the patch would need header changes. Cancelling the patch for now.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12607147" author="mahadev" created="Mon, 23 Jun 2008 06:54:58 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;i was reading through the patch. It would be good if a broad overview of what each class is doing ..lso there is a lack of javadocs &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; (it would help if javadocs are provided while reviewing ).... &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12608889" author="akornev" created="Fri, 27 Jun 2008 20:14:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;The same patch but is now built against the apache SVN. Please review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12608899" author="mahadev" created="Fri, 27 Jun 2008 20:56:24 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Property changes on: C:\work\apache\zookeeper\trunk\src\java\test\org\apache\zookeeper\server\DataTreeMock.java&lt;br/&gt;
___________________________________________________________________&lt;br/&gt;
Name: svn:eol-style&lt;br/&gt;
   + native&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;there are some changes that are not a patch fo this patch i think and are alos not relative to the src tree!! could you get rid of them andrew and upload the patch again?&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12608932" author="akornev" created="Fri, 27 Jun 2008 23:12:38 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Uploading the patch (fixed the paths for the property changes)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12611885" author="mahadev" created="Wed, 9 Jul 2008 03:29:45 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;the patch looks good &amp;#8212; here are some of my comments &amp;#8212; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;also I am not finished reviewing it &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;. its a long patch &amp;#8212; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0) overall there are too many interfaces in the patch. though i uinderstand that interfaces make things pluggable but I think we should restrict only wehn we need it and create interfaces only when we seriously think that it would be good to have it pluggable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) DataTereeBuilder is an interface and has only one subclass &amp;#8212; i think that we should not make this pluggable and just have a datatree class instead of the interfaces and implementing classes.&lt;br/&gt;
2) FileDBINFO implements DBINFO but  FILEDBINFO Is the only subclass of DBINFO. I think here again we should just keep it simple and not make this an interface and pluggable.&lt;br/&gt;
3) Snapshotting plicy is again pluggable &amp;#8211; we should also not make this pluggable and let it work our default implementation.&lt;br/&gt;
4) we have arguments passing around as url though there are not true url&apos;s in java &amp;#8211; but just strings. if we really want to make this pluggable and use url&apos;s then we should use URL class in java and use its methods for checking what kind of provider we want it to return. like create a URL(string) and url.getProtocol.equals(&quot;file&quot;) then we retrun our default one.&lt;br/&gt;
5) i dont see any use case of more persistence layers as -D expressions? what if we had something like this &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Dpersisten.provider=classname and then just use reflections to create the provider class else we just return the default provider. I think it makes the code simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i am not done reviewing the patch entirely. &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12612208" author="akornev" created="Wed, 9 Jul 2008 19:03:33 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;While JIRA comments is not the best place to discuss basics of object-oriented design, I&apos;d like to point out that interfaces are not about &quot;pluggability&quot; and the number of potential implementations is not an indication of whether or not an interface should be introduced. I highly recommend the reviewer take another look at Design Patterns by GoF (chapters 1 and 2) and Emergent Design by Scott L. Bain just to name a few (both of them are available on Safari).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recommend the reviewer take a look at the unit tests included with the patch. There, one can see how loose coupling (achieved thru the use of interfaces, among other things) improves testability of the code. It is now possible to unit test classes individually and in isolation &amp;#8211; something that has never been possible with the existing zookeeper code before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrt point 4, I&apos;ll update the code to use the URL class instead.&lt;br/&gt;
Wrt point 5, if I understand the question correctly, what if we want to run multiple zookeeper servers within the same JVM and you want to be able to associate different providers with each of those servers? Besides, we get this feature essentially for free. There is one extra line of code (the while() statement) that deals with loading multiple providers.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12613027" author="akornev" created="Sat, 12 Jul 2008 01:52:10 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Added more javadocs, use the URI class for passing provider URLs, implemented support for terminating the server if the database files format is not supported (wrong version).&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12614540" author="breed" created="Thu, 17 Jul 2008 23:03:12 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I really like how you pulled the code out of the scattered locations around the source tree. I wish you would have pulled them into a couple of classes rather than scattering them into new classes. It seems like it would be really nice to have a Snapshot class and a TxnLog class. I think classes like SerializeUtils, AsyncSnapshotPolicy, Util, FileLogWriter, FileLogProvider, FileDBInfo (perhaps others) could be pulled into these classes. I agree with Mahadev that the extra interfaces seem overkill for the simple requirements of this Jira. The provider classes are also overkill for this Jira. Perhaps in the future we may need something like that, but I&apos;d rather wait for the need than try and foresee a solution now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mahadev and I will take a crack at collapsing these classes down.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616627" author="akornev" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 21:16:03 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;How&apos;s the cracking been going so far?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12616637" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 24 Jul 2008 21:25:25 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;i am working on it... should get it out by next week .... &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12617488" author="mahadev" created="Mon, 28 Jul 2008 18:40:48 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;cancelling the patch for now. ill upload a new version of the patch with Ben&apos;s comments incorporated. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12617700" author="breed" created="Tue, 29 Jul 2008 06:10:42 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Mahadev is simplifying the patch.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12622753" author="mahadev" created="Fri, 15 Aug 2008 01:05:55 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;here&apos;s a first look at the patch. I am still in process of cleaning it up and adding javadocs. Please review and comment. Ben wil be making changes to the tests. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12624978" author="mahadev" created="Fri, 22 Aug 2008 22:03:34 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;here is a  patch that applies to the trunk. &lt;br/&gt;
the last 2 commits made the patch stale.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12628804" author="mahadev" created="Sat, 6 Sep 2008 01:42:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;this is the latest updated patch that applies to the trunk ... &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12632052" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 18 Sep 2008 02:57:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Here is a preliminary patch. I redid the patch for this issue. THe previous patch was complex. Now there are just two calss in the persistence layer. One for snapshot and the other for logs. There is another class FileTxnSnapLog that provides conviniecne methods for using the txnlog and snapshots. I think this is much more cleaner and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12632054" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 18 Sep 2008 02:59:05 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;forgot to mention that this does not pass the tests. I am still workong on making it more cleaner &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt; and pass the tests.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12632381" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 18 Sep 2008 21:55:02 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;here is aptch that passes the tests (exception recovery test). I am making some more interface cleanup changes. Ben can you take a look at this...&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12633537" author="mahadev" created="Mon, 22 Sep 2008 23:19:48 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;here is patch that passes all the tests. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12634267" author="breed" created="Wed, 24 Sep 2008 20:50:04 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;This looks great Mahadev. Just  small comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In ZooKeeperServerMain you changed from using the configuration methods to putting everything in the constructor. I think we should stick with the configuration methods. (This same comment applies to Leader and QuorumPeer&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In FileSnapLog.deserialize() if the snapshot is bad, you should try an earlier snapshot. (We should add a test case for this)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;SnapLog should really be called Snapshot since it does not have a log component&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In FileTxnLog.getLogFiles() you should add a comment to the first (fzxid &amp;gt; logZxid) check that you are taking advantage of the fact that the files are sorted, so the last time this condition is true will be for the log file that has snapshotZxid.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In FileTxnLog.getLastLoggedZxid() the comment is a bit unclear. I think this method will also have a problem if the last logfile consists of a single corrupt entry.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In FileTxnLog.truncate() you may need to delete files as well if the zxid you are truncing to is in a log file before the last file&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;TxnLogCompletion is not used and should be removed&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Util class has some methods that are not used that should be removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12634616" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 25 Sep 2008 21:59:40 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;here is an updated patch. I cleared the patch with nice javadocs and more testing. Fixed a few bugs i found during the testing.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In  ZooKeeperServerMain you changed from using the configuration methods to putting everything in the constructor. I think we   should stick with the configuration methods. (This same comment applies to Leader and QuorumPeer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i am not sure abt this. did i remove something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In FileSnapLog.deserialize() if the snapshot is bad, you should try an earlier snapshot. (We should add a test case for this)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; you are right... i would rather have it as another jira since this would be an improved over our earilier versions and would help getting this in without more delay &lt;img class=&quot;emoticon&quot; src=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/emoticons/smile.gif&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot; align=&quot;absmiddle&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;SnapLog should really be called Snapshot since it does not have a log component&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In FileTxnLog.getLogFiles() you should add a comment to the first (fzxid &amp;gt; logZxid) check that you are taking advantage of the fact that the files are sorted, so the last time this condition is true will be for the log file that has snapshotZxid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In FileTxnLog.getLastLoggedZxid() the comment is a bit unclear. I think this method will also have a problem if the last logfile consists of a single corrupt entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;done... thats is true... I will open another jira for this as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In FileTxnLog.truncate() you may need to delete files as well if the zxid you are truncing to is in a log file before the last file&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;TxnLogCompletion is not used and should be removed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Util class has some methods that are not used that should be removed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;done.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12634681" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 25 Sep 2008 23:57:41 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;the last patch went stale with commiting of &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-139&quot; title=&quot;Create Enums for WatcherEvent&amp;#39;s KeeperState and EventType&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-139&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-139&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12635561" author="mahadev" created="Mon, 29 Sep 2008 23:28:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;this patch reverts backs the changes for &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/ZOOKEEPER-82&quot; title=&quot;Make the ZooKeeperServer more DI friendly&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;ZOOKEEPER-82&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;ZOOKEEPER-82&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. my patch over rode all the changes.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12635921" author="mahadev" created="Wed, 1 Oct 2008 01:54:34 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;the last patch had a problem with compiling jmx ... since the jmx build is broken is didnt realize that I broke the jmx build with my patch... &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12635956" author="breed" created="Wed, 1 Oct 2008 07:28:18 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;+1 Looks good mahadev. Marked as an Incompatible change since the data format is not backwards compatible.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12636329" author="hudson" created="Thu, 2 Oct 2008 11:46:01 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Integrated in ZooKeeper-trunk #101 (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/ZooKeeper-trunk/101/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://hudson.zones.apache.org/hudson/job/ZooKeeper-trunk/101/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12642681" author="phunt" created="Sun, 26 Oct 2008 01:10:37 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;3.0.0 has been released, closing issues.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="12310010">
                    <name>Incorporates</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="incorporates">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12397990">ZOOKEEPER-27</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
            <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12397997">ZOOKEEPER-32</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                        </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12385912" name="ZOOKEEPER-38.patch" size="279919" author="akornev" created="Sat, 12 Jul 2008 01:52:10 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12384873" name="ZOOKEEPER-38.patch" size="254922" author="akornev" created="Fri, 27 Jun 2008 23:12:38 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12384857" name="ZOOKEEPER-38.patch" size="256224" author="akornev" created="Fri, 27 Jun 2008 20:14:38 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12388288" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_1.patch" size="220045" author="mahadev" created="Fri, 15 Aug 2008 01:05:55 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12391169" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_10.patch" size="146340" author="mahadev" created="Mon, 29 Sep 2008 23:28:26 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12391251" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_11.patch" size="146856" author="mahadev" created="Wed, 1 Oct 2008 01:54:34 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12388772" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_2.patch" size="233908" author="mahadev" created="Fri, 22 Aug 2008 22:03:34 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12389605" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_3.patch" size="232214" author="mahadev" created="Sat, 6 Sep 2008 01:42:02 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12390326" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_5.patch" size="214652" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 18 Sep 2008 02:57:40 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12390419" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_6.patch" size="138323" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 18 Sep 2008 21:55:02 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12390695" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_7.patch" size="138401" author="mahadev" created="Mon, 22 Sep 2008 23:19:48 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12390950" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_8.patch" size="147501" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 25 Sep 2008 21:59:40 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12390968" name="ZOOKEEPER-38_9.patch" size="147505" author="mahadev" created="Thu, 25 Sep 2008 23:57:41 +0100"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>13.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Wed, 11 Jun 2008 20:13:11 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>48095</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310191" key="com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.customfieldtypes:multicheckboxes">
                        <customfieldname>Hadoop Flags</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                                <customfieldvalue key="10342"><![CDATA[Incompatible change]]></customfieldvalue>
    <customfieldvalue key="10343"><![CDATA[Reviewed]]></customfieldvalue>
    
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hxzysn:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>33621</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>