<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 05:19:47 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/SOLR-868/SOLR-868.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[SOLR-868] Prepare solrjs trunk to be integrated into contrib</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/SOLR-868</link>
                <project id="12310230" key="SOLR">Solr</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;This patch includes a zipfile snapshot of current solrjs trunk. The folder structure is applied to standard solr layout.  It can be extracted to &quot;contrib/javascript&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it includes a build.xml:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant dist -&amp;gt; creates a single js file and a jar that holds velocity templates.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant docs -&amp;gt; creates js docs. test in browser: doc/index.html&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant example-init -&amp;gt; (depends ant dist on solr root) copies the current built of solr.war and solr-velocity.jar to example/testsolr/..&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant example-start -&amp;gt; starts the testsolr server on port 8983&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant example-import -&amp;gt; imports 3000 test data rows (requires a started testserver)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Point your browser to example/testClientside.html ,example/testServerSide.html or test/reuters/index.html to see it working.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12408682">SOLR-868</key>
            <summary>Prepare solrjs trunk to be integrated into contrib</summary>
                <type id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/task.png">Task</type>
                                            <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="gsingers">Grant Ingersoll</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="mepheser">Matthias Epheser</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Mon, 17 Nov 2008 20:57:30 +0000</created>
                <updated>Tue, 10 Nov 2009 15:51:51 +0000</updated>
                            <resolved>Thu, 10 Sep 2009 15:00:16 +0100</resolved>
                                    <version>1.4</version>
                                    <fixVersion>1.4</fixVersion>
                                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>1</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12648388" author="ryantxu" created="Mon, 17 Nov 2008 22:31:58 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;just noticed that the calendar widget is GPL&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dynarch.com/projects/calendar/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.dynarch.com/projects/calendar/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we can&apos;t include GPL code in apache....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m working on the NOTICE.txt now...&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12648396" author="ryantxu" created="Mon, 17 Nov 2008 22:48:07 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I just commited the majority of this patch.  However I did not commit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the test reuters data&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the jscalender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rather then include the large example data in the distribution, we should add a script that will download and import it for people who really want to.  If there is not a public location for the sample data, we can find a &quot;permanent&quot; location for it on solrstuff.org&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12648410" author="mepheser" created="Mon, 17 Nov 2008 23:29:57 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The dataset can be downloaded here as a tarball:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://kdd.ics.uci.edu/databases/reuters21578/reuters21578.html&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://kdd.ics.uci.edu/databases/reuters21578/reuters21578.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest to create the testdata dir and include a small sample file (~100 entries). So people see at least something when look at the examples. If folks want more, they just need to download and extract the files to testdata and run the importer again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning jscalendar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, forgot about that. It was used as a showcase for what such a widget may look like. There are some jquery calendar plugins out there with different complexity, I&apos;ll have a look at their potential for an integrated calendar widget. For people writing demo/non commercial things, we can leave the jscalendar plugin available at solrstuff.org.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12648527" author="shalinmangar" created="Tue, 18 Nov 2008 08:20:09 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Since this is a new feature, marking it for 1.4&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12648534" author="mepheser" created="Tue, 18 Nov 2008 09:08:14 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Just noticed that we need an (empty) &quot;test&quot; target in the build.xml in order to get a successful build of solr trunk. &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12648547" author="ehatcher" created="Tue, 18 Nov 2008 09:30:25 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Empty test target added.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12648548" author="ehatcher" created="Tue, 18 Nov 2008 09:32:38 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Matthias, could you detail build / demo instructions a bit more.  The example-start and example-import targets are commented out in what got committed to contrib/javascript.  Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wiki would be a good place to lay out how to run this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12649912" author="mepheser" created="Sat, 22 Nov 2008 11:41:08 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;As discussed thsi patch includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;creation of example/testdata&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;a small sample.sgm file with 69 test data rows&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;a script to load more data from download server&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;testClientside.html applied to exampleschema&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;reuters/index: calendar widget removed&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;build.xml: apllied test targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attached the binary &quot;reutersimporter.jar&quot; separately, it needs to be put into &quot;example/testdata&quot; &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12649913" author="ehatcher" created="Sat, 22 Nov 2008 11:47:34 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Where&apos;s the source code (and what is its license) of the reuters importer JAR?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we have the rights to check-in in this sample reuters data?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12649915" author="mepheser" created="Sat, 22 Nov 2008 11:59:07 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not an legal expert, and i&apos;ve no problem to use solr core testdata if there is any risk of copyright violence. My understanding of the copyright notice is that is should be ok:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kdd.ics.uci.edu/databases/reuters21578/README.txt&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://kdd.ics.uci.edu/databases/reuters21578/README.txt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The importer is a small maven project I created in summer, that uses one external library (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geonames.org/source-code/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://www.geonames.org/source-code/&lt;/a&gt;, Apache license). If necessary, I may check it again and attach the sourcecode to contrib to build it locally before the import using ant.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12650010" author="ehatcher" created="Sun, 23 Nov 2008 10:17:18 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I&apos;m not a lawyer either - just wanted to check.  Lucene&apos;s contrib/benchmark uses reuters data also, so probably no problem there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the importer - yeah, we&apos;d need the source code and a build procedure for it.  We wouldn&apos;t include a binary-only JAR file without there being an open source project behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still should set up an example of SolrJS using the default example data.  Many first timers to Solr will follow the tutorial, and it&apos;d be handy to have a ready-built example of a search UI with all the bells and whistles possible.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12656389" author="mepheser" created="Sun, 14 Dec 2008 13:59:50 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I had some time off at the beginning of december, but I managed to rearrange the examples this weekend. As I rearranged the directory structure to fit our emerged needs, I attach a whole new contrib/javascript dir in the new zip file. I tried to create a suitable patch to current trunk, but as a lot of directories moved, binary files were added and deleted, it got complicated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Split the example to &quot;core&quot; and &quot;reuters&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The &quot;core&quot; examples work out of the box with existing solr testdata, just run the server in solr/example as usual and open the files in the browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I removed the reuters src data files, leaving one sample with less than 100 rows. A script is attached so uers may automatically get the full dataset on purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For the reuters schema, only the solr config dir is provided and the standard example dist is used, pointing to the contrib javascript solr home.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I attached the source code of my reuters importer, removed all unnecessary dependencies (as this was a standalone maven project before). So now a single class with only deps to the standard solr distribution works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So to start the demo app:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant example in solr root&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant dist in contrib/javascript&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant reuters-start in contrib/javascript to start the server&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ant reuters-import to import the data (sample file or all files when downloaded before)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I think this new structure covers the thoughts that came up in this thread, the core examples can be used without doing the more complex reuters stuff, and the full demo can be used with 2 ant commands.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12656827" author="ryantxu" created="Tue, 16 Dec 2008 01:06:21 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;thanks Matthias&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just commited this &amp;#8211; can you check it out and see if it behaves as expected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erik, do you know how we could make velocity a dependency of the javascript contrib?  We really should remove the velocity libs and add them in at runtime:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;codeContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;code-java&quot;&gt;
Adding         javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib
Adding  (bin)  javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib/apache-solr-velocity-1.4-dev.jar
Adding  (bin)  javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib/commons-collections-3.2.jar
Adding  (bin)  javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib/commons-lang-2.4.jar
Adding  (bin)  javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib/solrjs-1.4-dev-templates.jar
Adding  (bin)  javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib/velocity-1.6-beta2.jar
Adding  (bin)  javascript/example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib/velocity-tools-2.0-beta2.jar
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12656886" author="mepheser" created="Tue, 16 Dec 2008 05:35:36 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;These dependencies can safely moved to svn.ignore, as they are put in place by the &quot;reuters-start&quot; ant task:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;copy todir=&quot;example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib&quot; overwrite=&quot;true&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;lt;fileset dir=&quot;../velocity/src/main/solr/lib/&quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/copy&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;copy file=&quot;dist/solrjs-$&lt;/p&gt;
{version}
&lt;p&gt;-templates.jar&quot; todir=&quot;example/reuters/testsolr/solr/lib&quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12670668" author="shalinmangar" created="Thu, 5 Feb 2009 08:48:04 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I guess this has already been committed. Is there anything else needed to resolve this issue?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12670799" author="mepheser" created="Thu, 5 Feb 2009 15:46:36 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;My bad, hadn&apos;t time to work on this in january.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve checked it locally and made some tweaks concerning examples bewteen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;simple examples using standard solr example instance&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;more confident example (reuters data) using its own index&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second one includes a script to import more testdata from the web. So the solr dist should be kept thin, and people can easily get the more confient one on purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll try to get a patch fpr this next week.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12735713" author="ehatcher" created="Mon, 27 Jul 2009 20:02:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;ping.  Anything left to do for this issue?   Note that we have moved solrjs to client/javascript in the mean time.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12735723" author="epugh" created="Mon, 27 Jul 2009 20:17:00 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think so unless we want to have it deploy into the /examples app and update the related tutorial pages?   That would mean we would need to change the data set that the example expects to use from Reuters data to shopping data.  Which we can do, and would raise the visibility...?  Should that be another ticket?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12738736" author="gsingers" created="Tue, 4 Aug 2009 02:26:59 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I&apos;m not a lawyer either - just wanted to check. Lucene&apos;s contrib/benchmark uses reuters data also, so probably no problem there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucene does not include the data, it has a download mechanism for it.  I don&apos;t think we should include any Reuters data in SVN or a release.  The license says the data is explicitly for research purposes.  That is somewhat murky to me.  I suppose you could argue a demo is for research (i.e. researching whether it works or not) but I don&apos;t think that is the intent of the license given the circumstances and the people who released it.  However, I&apos;m not a lawyer.  For a definitive answer we should either ask Dr. Lewis, but I suspect it is just easier to remove that one file and have the demo be based on the download.  The download is fast, as the doc set is small.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12739071" author="ryantxu" created="Tue, 4 Aug 2009 19:16:57 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;My apologies, this was actually resolved months ago!  (and solrjs is now in &lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/solr/trunk/client/javascript/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/solr/trunk/client/javascript/&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12739114" author="gsingers" created="Tue, 4 Aug 2009 20:39:53 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My apologies, this was actually resolved months ago! (and solrjs is now in &lt;a href=&quot;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/solr/trunk/client/javascript/&quot; class=&quot;external-link&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/lucene/solr/trunk/client/javascript/&lt;/a&gt; ) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was, but it seems like we committed the Reuters data, which I don&apos;t think we should.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12742515" author="gsingers" created="Wed, 12 Aug 2009 19:44:26 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think we have the right to include sample.sgm.  How about generifying the content or just automating the download?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12742528" author="yseeley@gmail.com" created="Wed, 12 Aug 2009 20:16:50 +0100"  >&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think we have the right to include sample.sgm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can&apos;t we just abide by their notification requirements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really dislike automated downloads - so if we can&apos;t include this, maybe we should just include something else.&lt;/p&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12742531" author="gsingers" created="Wed, 12 Aug 2009 20:23:39 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d prefer something else.  I think we could even just replace the content with our own made up content, but keep the structure.  Their license requirements explicitly state for research purposes only.  I&apos;d rather not distribute it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code panel&quot; style=&quot;border-width: 1px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;codeContent panelContent&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;code-java&quot;&gt;ant rat-sources&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; reports a lot of missing ASL headers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the licensing on JSDoc-Toolkit seems dubious to me.  While it appears to be MIT, it clearly states it is derived from a GPL work.  Do we really need to check in code to generate Javascript documentation?  Can&apos;t that just be an optional part of the build to go and run JSDoc-Toolkit after which the JS Docs are checked in?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12742533" author="epugh" created="Wed, 12 Aug 2009 20:25:11 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I won&apos;t get to it this week I think, but I want to just take solrjs and point it at our default dataset.  Not sure that it will expose &lt;b&gt;ALL&lt;/b&gt; of the cool widgets the way the reuters data does, but we could also point to the reuters demo, or make the download of the reuters data something we document, and not have it be automatic..  More of an &quot;Now you&apos;ve seen what it looks like with the example data, check this out...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12742588" author="ehatcher" created="Wed, 12 Aug 2009 22:34:09 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s already some of my own personal book data provided (generated through a couple of tools) as CSV data here: clients/ruby/solr-ruby/examples/delicious_library/sample_export.txt&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to use and abuse that.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12752634" author="gsingers" created="Tue, 8 Sep 2009 18:45:16 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m going to pull the Reuters demo for the release.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12753627" author="gsingers" created="Thu, 10 Sep 2009 15:00:16 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;Removed sample.sgm.  Users can download if they wish to run the Reuters example.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12775580" author="gsingers" created="Tue, 10 Nov 2009 15:51:51 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Bulk close for Solr 1.4&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                    <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12394479" name="SOLR-868-testdata.patch" size="90506" author="mepheser" created="Sat, 22 Nov 2008 11:41:08 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12396022" name="javascript_contrib.zip" size="1980644" author="mepheser" created="Sun, 14 Dec 2008 14:01:19 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12394480" name="reutersimporter.jar" size="1128644" author="mepheser" created="Sat, 22 Nov 2008 11:42:09 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12394099" name="solrjs.zip" size="9377518" author="mepheser" created="Mon, 17 Nov 2008 21:02:41 +0000"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>4.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Mon, 17 Nov 2008 22:31:58 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>6761</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hxxopr:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>20323</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>