<!-- 
RSS generated by JIRA (6.3.4#6332-sha1:51bc225ef474afe3128b2f66878477f322397b16) at Sun May 17 04:40:53 UTC 2015

It is possible to restrict the fields that are returned in this document by specifying the 'field' parameter in your request.
For example, to request only the issue key and summary add field=key&field=summary to the URL of your request.
For example:
https://issues.apache.org/jira/si/jira.issueviews:issue-xml/OPENJPA-878/OPENJPA-878.xml?field=key&amp;field=summary
-->
<rss version="0.92" >
<channel>
    <title>ASF JIRA</title>
    <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira</link>
    <description>This file is an XML representation of an issue</description>
    <language>en-uk</language>    <build-info>
        <version>6.3.4</version>
        <build-number>6332</build-number>
        <build-date>15-08-2014</build-date>
    </build-info>

<item>
            <title>[OPENJPA-878] Support default query hint for query timeout</title>
                <link>https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878</link>
                <project id="12310351" key="OPENJPA">OpenJPA</project>
                    <description>&lt;p&gt;Support default query hint for query timeout as defined in section 3.6.4 of the spec.&lt;br/&gt;
A new hint can be supplied for Java SE and Java EE environments -&lt;br/&gt;
    javax.persistence.query.timeout // query timeout in seconds&lt;br/&gt;
Can be used in the following:&lt;br/&gt;
    Methods - Query.setHint()&lt;br/&gt;
    Annotations (via QueryHint) - NamedQuery, NativeNamedQuery &lt;br/&gt;
    Properties - Persistence.createEntityManagerFactory, persistence.xml&lt;br/&gt;
The following methods can return a javax.persistence.QueryTimeoutException: getResultList(), getSingleResult(), executeUpdate().&lt;br/&gt;
If a QTE is thrown, the current transaction (if active) should not be marked for rollback.&lt;br/&gt;
If the DB query timeout causes a rollback, then a PersistenceException should be thrown instead (see 3.6.1).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
                <environment></environment>
        <key id="12413544">OPENJPA-878</key>
            <summary>Support default query hint for query timeout</summary>
                <type id="7" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/issuetypes/subtask_alternate.png">Sub-task</type>
                            <parent id="12416215">OPENJPA-956</parent>
                                    <priority id="3" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/priorities/major.png">Major</priority>
                        <status id="6" iconUrl="https://issues.apache.org/jira/images/icons/statuses/closed.png" description="The issue is considered finished, the resolution is correct. Issues which are closed can be reopened.">Closed</status>
                    <statusCategory id="3" key="done" colorName="green"/>
                                    <resolution id="1">Fixed</resolution>
                                        <assignee username="drwoods">Donald Woods</assignee>
                                    <reporter username="drwoods">Donald Woods</reporter>
                        <labels>
                    </labels>
                <created>Thu, 29 Jan 2009 18:11:32 +0000</created>
                <updated>Thu, 2 May 2013 03:29:21 +0100</updated>
                            <resolved>Wed, 25 Mar 2009 21:01:59 +0000</resolved>
                                    <version>2.0.0-M2</version>
                                    <fixVersion>2.0.0-M2</fixVersion>
                                    <component>query</component>
                        <due></due>
                            <votes>0</votes>
                                    <watches>0</watches>
                                                                <comments>
                            <comment id="12679304" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 5 Mar 2009 19:01:15 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Draft patch that implements Query timeout support.&lt;br/&gt;
So far, only tested on Derby.  Also, still have a couple cleanup TODOs, but wanted to post it to get some early feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12679624" author="techhusky" created="Fri, 6 Mar 2009 15:52:14 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Comments on &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090305-draft.patch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;General: OpenJPA uses an 80 column, 4 space indent formatting scheme  some lines were considerably longer than 80 chars.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;General: Looks like there is a lot of work to identify the query timeout condition for all the supported DBs...  We could consider making that a separate work item.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;FetchConfiguration.java and OpenJPAConfiguration.java are in the kernel module.  The kernel can be &amp;amp; is used by multiple ORM providers/solutions so kernel javadoc should not be specific to JPA.  I recommend removing the JPA 2.0 spec ... line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;SQLBuffer.java - I could be mistaken, but I don&apos;t think removing a public method or changing a method signature is a good idea.  Fay is more knowledgeable on the external uses of this class so it would be be good run these changes by her.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;It looked as if OpenJPA was only passing the fetch config when dealing with LRS.  Are there any additional side effects from passing the fetch config?  Does any behavior get triggered that should be LRS only by passing the fetch config on the prepare?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;JDBCStoreQuery.java - ditto on the method signature changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;TableJDBCSeq.java - I&apos;d like to see some feedback from other folks regarding the use of query timeout during this sensitive operation.  The sequence operation is part of the full operation so I think it makes sense to try to honor the timeout, if possible.  Although a separate work item, I think lock timeout should also be considered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;SQLStoreQuery.java - ditto on the method signature changes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TableSchemaFactory.java - IMHO, I don&apos;t think we should honor timeouts in the schema factory.  That&apos;s startup behavior vs. runtime behavior and I think this hint would be more expected to apply only to runtime behavior.  It would be good to have other opinions on this as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EntityManagerImpl.java - The changes to the clear method were part of Dianne&apos;s patch, but shouldn&apos;t have been in the patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TestQueryTimeout .java -  I noticed that the ability to retry an operation after a query timeout is database specific.  Could/should this fact get carried into QueryTimeoutException.isFatal()?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very thorough job on the tests!&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12679668" author="drwoods" created="Fri, 6 Mar 2009 17:54:43 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the review.&lt;br/&gt;
Yep, figured someone would catch the formatting, as I hate the 20+ year old standard of 80 column widths, given most everyone has hi-res wide screen displays now...  I can fix this in my Eclipse settings for the next patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the other DBs, I&apos;d like to open a subtask for I5.  I would also like to include additional tests for setting the property via Persistence.createEntityManagerFactory and persistence.xml in I5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method signature changes were the only way to get the queryTimeout value down into the prepareStatement() and prepareCall() methods, as they currently only have access to the Connection, which doesn&apos;t have handles to the FetchConfiguration or OpenJPAConfiguration classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding queryTimeout support to TableJDBCSeq.java would involve either more method signature changes and/or creating a FetchConfiguration just to hold the QueryTimeout value if it is &amp;gt; 0, as neither the TableJDBCSeq nor TableSchemaFactory classes have a FetchConfiguration passed to them today (but they do have access to the OpenJPAConfiguration data.)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12679749" author="drwoods" created="Fri, 6 Mar 2009 22:37:57 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated patch that only runs the junit tests only against Derby for now.&lt;br/&gt;
Additional JIRAs 963 and 964 opened against I5 to complete test coverage items.&lt;br/&gt;
EntityManagerImpl.java changes backed out.&lt;br/&gt;
JPA 2.0 spec comments removed from FetchConfiguration.java and OpenJPAConfiguration.java.&lt;br/&gt;
Usage of QueryTimeoutException.isFatal() not addressed, as the code matches what was done for lock timeouts.&lt;br/&gt;
Method signature changes not addressed, as these were required to enable access to the queryTimeout value.&lt;br/&gt;
Only reformatted TestQueryTimeout.java to 80 columns (using the &apos;where required&apos; option in Eclipse.)&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12680639" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 10 Mar 2009 22:00:27 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated patches that do not change the method signatures.&lt;br/&gt;
I&apos;ve attached both a svn diff and Subclipse version of the patch, as the svn diff version includes replacing Windows EOL on 2 files.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12680874" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 14:15:35 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated patch against Rev752306 which fixes the existing org.apache.openjpa.conf.TestQueryHints junit test, which was using getQueryTimeout() for lockTimeout comparison.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12680887" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 15:13:14 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated Eclipse patch that can be applied to existing trunk subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681009" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 19:57:35 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch to add definitions for javax.persistence.lock.timeout and javax.persistence.query.timeout to the 10.1.7 Query Hints section.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681031" author="ppoddar@apache.org" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 21:16:30 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The key changes are not very visible in &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090311.patch because often they are masked by large diffs created by EOL/white space character mismatch.&lt;br/&gt;
So&lt;br/&gt;
1. Create a patch that does have the real changes (e.g. something like svn diff -x --ignore-all-space)&lt;br/&gt;
2. Submit separate patch for source and test branches. Actually, the tests can be directly checked-in.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681142" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 02:12:08 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated the &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090311.patch by using &quot;svn diff -x --ignore-eol-style&quot;.  Pinaki, thanks for the pointer.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681365" author="techhusky" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 15:50:48 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Couple of comments on &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090311.patch (7:12pm).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) There is quite a bit of duplication of the setTimeout method (likely caused by refactoring to eliminate the need for interface changes per previous comments) across multiple subclasses.  Is it possible to implement the method in the abstract parent class (for store query, seq, and strats) to eliminate much of the duplication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Similar to connection, could a decorator pattern be applied to prepared statement to decorate the ps with query and lock timeout  hints vs. calling it explicitly after a statement is constructed?  This may be difficult depending on the availability of the configuration.  Something to think about though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The code uses &apos;max&apos; to calculate the timeout value when query &amp;amp; lock timeout are used in combination.  Given the way lock timeouts are currently implemented (with query timeout), that seems like the safest behavior. (Other opinions?)  Until lock timeouts are handled by the DB, I think this behavior should be documented.  A sentence in the lock and query timeout docs would be sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Should query timeout be applied to sequence queries?  I&apos;m on the fence.  Any thoughts on this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is anyone opposed to including the FIXME comments when these changes are committed?  They reference another JIRA so they aren&apos;t simply &apos;dangling&apos; out there.  Is there a convention for commenting on future work within code?  Should those comments only exist within a JIRA?&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681376" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 16:20:34 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll take a look at #1/#2 to see what can be done, but there were several abstract interfaces being used that didn&apos;t extend a common parent (and I was afraid of breaking APIs again.)&lt;br/&gt;
For #3, I&apos;ll add a comment in &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-957&quot; title=&quot;Support lock timeout hint on applicable methods&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-957&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-957&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to update the docs if we don&apos;t end up switching to use the db server lock timeout support.&lt;br/&gt;
For #4, my thoughts were that if someone provides a query.timeout value/hint, then we should try to honor it everywhere, as the usage of setQueryTimeout() is to prevent JDBC client apps from waiting forever on blocked or missed server responses due to network or db problems.&lt;br/&gt;
For the FIXME, I noticed in Eclipse there were tons of existing FIXME/TODO comment tags, so I also used it to denote pending work items....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681404" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 17:22:18 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated patch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090312-minimal.patch) that addresses Jeremy&apos;s #1 and #4 concerns by removing setTimeout() on seq/schema/counts/DBDictionary/... and only implements it on SelectImpl and SQLStoreQuery, so the TestQueryTimeout tests will still pass for the Spec required EM.find()/executeUpdate(), getResultList() and getSingleResult() operations.&lt;br/&gt;
Includes base QueryTimeoutException support with required updates to sql-error-codes.xml, StoreException, QueryException and DBDictionary/DerbyDictionary.&lt;br/&gt;
Includes doc updates to include new Query/Lock timeout hint definitions.&lt;br/&gt;
Still uses max() if a LockTimeout is specified, until &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-957&quot; title=&quot;Support lock timeout hint on applicable methods&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-957&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-957&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is resolved.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681406" author="ppoddar@apache.org" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 17:25:56 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The very fact that following code (or similar variants) appears 10+ times in the patch points that a better solution/refactoring is required. &lt;br/&gt;
It is not about that the patch is getting it wrong (in fact, the patch shows thoroughness) but the way existing things are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that&lt;br/&gt;
1) the research finds that time outs may better be handled database server side&lt;br/&gt;
2) JDBC does not support a lockTimeOut and we are emulating it by query time out&lt;br/&gt;
3) databases employ specific techniques for server side time outs&lt;br/&gt;
4) the current timeout requires us to duplicate same code block +10 times&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest&lt;br/&gt;
a) move the duplicated code to DBDictionary &amp;#8211; this default implement will do what we do today i.e. emulate locktimeout via querytimeout.&lt;br/&gt;
this will remove/minimize duplication of code and will localize the timeout function at one place&lt;br/&gt;
b) incrementally add specific database time out functions for server side time out&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;+    protected void setTimeout(PreparedStatement stmnt, JDBCStore store,&lt;br/&gt;
+        JDBCFetchConfiguration fetch)&lt;br/&gt;
+        throws SQLException {&lt;br/&gt;
+        if (store.getDBDictionary().supportsQueryTimeout) {&lt;br/&gt;
+            int timeout = fetch.getQueryTimeout();&lt;br/&gt;
+            if (timeout &amp;gt;= 0) {&lt;br/&gt;
+                if (timeout &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; timeout &amp;lt; 1000) &lt;/p&gt;
{
+                    timeout = 1000; 
+                    Log log = store.getConfiguration().getLog(JDBCConfiguration.LOG_JDBC);
+                    if (log.isWarnEnabled())
+                        log.warn(_loc.get(&quot;millis-query-timeout&quot;));
+                }
&lt;p&gt;+                stmnt.setQueryTimeout(timeout / 1000);&lt;br/&gt;
+            }&lt;br/&gt;
+        }&lt;br/&gt;
+    }&lt;br/&gt;
+    &lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681884" author="drwoods" created="Fri, 13 Mar 2009 20:13:28 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Updated patch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090313.patch) that addresses Pinaki&apos;s request to centralize the set query/lock timeout code into the DBDictionary.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12681896" author="techhusky" created="Fri, 13 Mar 2009 21:06:43 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Comments on &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090313.patch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinaki&apos;s suggestion was very good, IMHO.  This version looks much cleaner and allows for database specific behavior.  I was going to suggest eliminating the near duplicate set methods in DBDictionary with a single method that takes both timeout values as int params - but passing in the fetch config or jdbc config will allow simpler setting of future timeout values (if any should get added), without needing to modify all the setTimeouts method calls in the code.  Unless there is an objection, I&apos;ll commit this patch (with formatting updates) on 3/16.  That should provide ample time for others to review.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12682021" author="milosz" created="Sat, 14 Mar 2009 10:32:04 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Jeremy, as for performing formatting changes I noticed two little things in the patch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;in DBDictionary, from what I have seen, we usually don&apos;t use &quot;this&quot; in front of variable unless necessary,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;probably there are some unused Localizers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</comment>
                            <comment id="12682558" author="techhusky" created="Tue, 17 Mar 2009 05:04:59 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-20090313.patch (with updates) under revisions: 755113, 755114, 755115, 755116, 755117 for Donald.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;alternate&quot; type=&quot;square&quot;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cleaned up unused localizers per suggestion from Milosz&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Did not remove usage of &apos;this&apos; in new dictionary methods per suggestion from Milosz.  I&apos;ll catch that on the next update.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tagged two methods in TestQueryTimeout with AllowFailure(true) because they fail intermittently on my local build (but ran fine on a separate build server).  I&apos;ve sent the surefire report to Donald for investigation.  Failures look to be test procedure related.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


</comment>
                            <comment id="12682729" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 17 Mar 2009 17:33:20 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Attached patch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-DBDictionary.patch) to address Milosz&apos;s request to remove the &quot;this.&quot; usage from DBDictionary.&lt;br/&gt;
Attached patch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-TestQueryTimeout.patch) to address Jeremy&apos;s intermittent test failures on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12683048" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 18 Mar 2009 15:41:37 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Patch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-serialVersionUID.patch) that removes serialVersionUID additions, as requested by Pinaki.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12683049" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 18 Mar 2009 15:44:20 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;The following requested updates are ready for your review -&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-DBDictionary.patch - changes requested by Milosz&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-TestQueryTimeout.patch - changes requested by Jeremy&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-serialVersionUID.patch - changes requested by Pinaki&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12683287" author="techhusky" created="Thu, 19 Mar 2009 03:00:25 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Committed &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-TestQueryTimeout.patch for Donald under revision 755818.&lt;br/&gt;
Committed &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-878&quot; title=&quot;Support default query hint for query timeout&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-878&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-878&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-DBDictionary.patch for Donald under revision 755819.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue regarding the use of serialVersionUID will be resolved under another JIRA.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12688699" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 24 Mar 2009 14:41:08 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Code to setup DB2 for setQueryTimeout testing with TestQueryTimeout.java junit code.&lt;br/&gt;
First, create a DB called OPENJPA and make sure you have uid=db2admin setup.&lt;br/&gt;
Then, run DelaySetup.bat (which uses uid=db2admin) to create the jar with the delay() function, register the jar in DB2 and create a Delay function on the OPENJPA db.&lt;br/&gt;
I&apos;ve been testing this with DB2 v9.5 on Windows, but it should work for 9.1 and v8.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12689240" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 25 Mar 2009 21:01:56 +0000"  >&lt;p&gt;Remaining suggestion to fix serialVersionUID usage has been opened as &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/OPENJPA-1000&quot; title=&quot;Consistent usage of serialVersionUID&quot; class=&quot;issue-link&quot; data-issue-key=&quot;OPENJPA-1000&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;OPENJPA-1000&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                            <comment id="12693896" author="drwoods" created="Mon, 30 Mar 2009 21:26:07 +0100"  >&lt;p&gt;DB2 for Linux setup scripts for testing.&lt;/p&gt;</comment>
                    </comments>
                <issuelinks>
                            <issuelinktype id="10030">
                    <name>Reference</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="relates to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12416217">OPENJPA-957</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
            <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12419424">OPENJPA-1000</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is related to">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12411713">OPENJPA-849</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                            <issuelinktype id="10001">
                    <name>dependent</name>
                                            <outwardlinks description="depends upon">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12415069">OPENJPA-927</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </outwardlinks>
                                                                <inwardlinks description="is depended upon by">
                                        <issuelink>
            <issuekey id="12416565">OPENJPA-972</issuekey>
        </issuelink>
                            </inwardlinks>
                                    </issuelinktype>
                    </issuelinks>
                <attachments>
                            <attachment id="12401535" name="OPENJPA-878-20090305-draft.patch" size="72673" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 5 Mar 2009 19:01:15 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401649" name="OPENJPA-878-20090306.patch" size="72319" author="drwoods" created="Fri, 6 Mar 2009 22:37:57 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401868" name="OPENJPA-878-20090310-eclipse.patch" size="79754" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 10 Mar 2009 22:00:27 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401869" name="OPENJPA-878-20090310.patch" size="168725" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 10 Mar 2009 22:00:27 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401936" name="OPENJPA-878-20090311-eclipse.patch" size="167126" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 15:13:14 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12402007" name="OPENJPA-878-20090311.patch" size="79803" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 02:12:07 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401937" name="OPENJPA-878-20090311.patch" size="168642" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 15:13:14 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12402066" name="OPENJPA-878-20090312-minimal.patch" size="58454" author="drwoods" created="Thu, 12 Mar 2009 17:22:18 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12402168" name="OPENJPA-878-20090313.patch" size="80579" author="drwoods" created="Fri, 13 Mar 2009 20:13:28 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12402397" name="OPENJPA-878-DBDictionary.patch" size="1639" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 17 Mar 2009 17:33:20 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12402398" name="OPENJPA-878-TestQueryTimeout.patch" size="5851" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 17 Mar 2009 17:33:20 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12401964" name="OPENJPA-878-docs-20090311.patch" size="1457" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 11 Mar 2009 19:57:35 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12402489" name="OPENJPA-878-serialVersionUID.patch" size="4049" author="drwoods" created="Wed, 18 Mar 2009 15:41:37 +0000"/>
                            <attachment id="12404171" name="OpenJPA-878-db2.tgz" size="4641" author="drwoods" created="Mon, 30 Mar 2009 21:26:07 +0100"/>
                            <attachment id="12403521" name="OpenJPA-878-db2.zip" size="4240" author="drwoods" created="Tue, 24 Mar 2009 14:41:08 +0000"/>
                    </attachments>
                <subtasks>
                    </subtasks>
                <customfields>
                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310310" key="com.atlassian.jira.toolkit:attachments">
                        <customfieldname>Attachment count</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>15.0</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            <customfield id="customfield_12310220" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:firstresponsedate">
                        <customfieldname>Date of First Response</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>Fri, 6 Mar 2009 15:52:14 +0000</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    <customfield id="customfield_12310420" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Global Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>161179</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12311820" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-lexo-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>2|hyt553:</customfieldvalue>

                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                <customfield id="customfield_12310920" key="com.pyxis.greenhopper.jira:gh-global-rank">
                        <customfieldname>Rank (Obsolete)</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            <customfieldvalue>204013</customfieldvalue>
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        <customfield id="customfield_12310222" key="com.atlassian.jira.ext.charting:timeinstatus">
                        <customfieldname>Time in Status</customfieldname>
                        <customfieldvalues>
                            
                        </customfieldvalues>
                    </customfield>
                                                                </customfields>
    </item>
</channel>
</rss>